<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The Galway Election, Speeches by Mr Parnell, The Irish Times, 11 February 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The Galway Election, Speeches by Mr Parnell</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="144709869" level="j">The Irish Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-02-11">11 February 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7007082">Galway, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00049"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">  
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www-proquest-com.ucd.idm.oclc.org/hnpirishtimes/docview/514273146/pageviewPDF/13E846FE0043481BPQ/6?accountid=14507"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>At 12 o'clock to-day Mr Parnell, accompanied by the Rev. Peter Dooly, P.P.; Rev. John Carolan, P.P.; Rev. Eugene Sheehy, C.C.; Mr J. J. Kelly, M.P.; and Mr Campbell, M.P., left the Railway Hotel, and drove out to Castlegar for the purpose of addressing the electors there in reference to the election. After having stopped for a short time in the house of the parish priest, the Rev. John Carolan, he addressed a small crowd of persons who belonged to the village, and who had assembled to hear what part they had to take in connection with the proceedings of to-morrow.</p>
         <p>The Rev. Mr. Carolan said - I have great pleasure in introducing to you the illustrious leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party, who has done us the high honour of coming here to address you, and I am sure that we shall all remember with pride what we had the honour of a visit from the greatest Parliamentary leader of his time. (Cheers.) We have been always ardently attached to him, and all I can say on your behalf is that that attachment to him shall always last. (Cheers.)</p>
         <p>Mr Parnell, who was received with loud cheers, said - People of Castlegar, I am obliged to you for having assembled in such numbers and on such short notice. I am glad to be able to announce to you that the dispute in reference to the representation of Galway has been settled by the self-sacrifice of Mr Lynch and his friends, who have retired in favour of the candidate, Captain O'Shea, recommended by me to the constituency. (Cheers.) I shall take this opportunity of telling you that if I had known that Mr Lynch was coming forward for the representation I should have accepted him, for I believe that he is an honest man and a gentleman, in every way suited to represent with honesty and ability the people of Galway. But in the duty which has devolved on me as leader of the Irish party and of the nation, to advise the people of Galway with regard to the selection of a candidate, it became necessary for me ten days agoo to inquire as to whether there was any local candidate in existence who desired to offer himself to the constitutency, and I was informed by Mr T. P. O'Connor that the only local candidate, Mr Lynch, would not offer himself; that he had declined; and that, not under any circumstances, could he be induced to offer himself for the representation. It therefore became necessary for me to look to some outside person unconnected with Galway - for the best candidate I could find. I therefore took it on myself to recommend Captain O'Shea, but, owing to some misunderstanding, Mr Lynch was induced to put himself in opposition to Mr O'Shea. A crisis of some gravity, difficulty, and danger then arose, but, as I have told you, that crisis has happily terminated by the patriotic withdrawal of Mr Lynch. (Cheers.) I wish now to say a few words in favour of Mr O'Shea, and of his action in the last Parliament, and of his willingness to work with us. I say that you may go to the poll and record your votes in his favour. Although Mr Lynch has withdrawn it will yet be necessary for you to go to the poll and record your votes for Captain O'Shea. Mr Lynch's name is on the ballot paper, and it is possible that the Tories and Orangemen of Galway will go and vote for Lynch, and endeavour to return him if the people do not come forward in sufficient numbers to return Captain O'Shea. It will, however, not be Mr Lynch's fault should they do so, for he has done everything that an honourable man could do by withdrawing from the contest. It will therefore be your duty to go to-morrow to the poll and put a cross opposite the name of Mr O'Shea. Now, with regard to Mr O'Shea's candidature. He represented the County of Clare in the last Parliament. He was returned for the County of Clare without my recommendation - in fact he was not at that time my candidate; but notwithstanding this fact, immediately after his return in 1880 he came up to Dublin and attended a meeting of the Irish Parliamentary party, held in the City Hall, when the famous division took place on the question whether Mr William Shaw or I should be leader of the party, and at that crisis in the history of Ireland he cast his vote in my favour. (Cheers.) My election on that occasion was carried by a majority of two votes, and it is right for me to remember now the service then rendered by O'Shea to me and in the cause of Ireland. (Cheers.) If he and one other had voted against me then I should have been deprived of the leadership of the party, and many of the great things that have since been done would not have been accomplished. There are men in the Parliamentary Party who did not vote for me on that occasion, and if that be so why should not I remember that vote he then gave in my favour; I have one fault to find with Mr O'Shea's public action. I repeatedly told him that I should not recommend his election unless that fault were amended, and I declined to support him for Galway till he had given me a promise that his conduct in future should not be open to that charge. The only fault I found with him during the last Parliament was that he constantly refused to sit on the same side of the House with us in opposition. But he has now given me this promise, and I guarantee to you that he has given me this promise, that in future he will sit with us as the Irish Party. Therefore the last possible objection that could be raise aagainst him has disappeared. (Cheers.) Mr Parnell then said that he had done his duty in this matter and that he had never led the country astray. For the last eleven years he had worked and fought. Commencing with two men against six hundred and fifty they had held up the flag of Ireland, and had acquired strength till now wedge-like they were now to drive into the heart of the enemy and split them to pieces and grind them to powder if they refused to Ireland her rights. (Cheers.) He had led Ireland and the Irish Party straight, and he was not now leading them in a crooked way. He believed that the result of this election would show that Galway and Ireland had confidence in him. He asked them to go to the poll and vote for Captain O'Shea, and said that the cause of Ireland was in their hands, and that in a short time he should bring back the Irish Parliament to College green, when they would be masters of their own destinies and of the destinies of their country. (Loud cheers.)</p>
         <p>The Rev. Peter Dooley then made a speech in Irish, in the course of which he told them of the withdrawal of Mr Lynch, and called on them to vote for Captain O'Shea.</p>
         <p>Father Sheey also briefly addressed them to the same effect.</p>
         <p>Mr Parnell then returned to Galway and drove on to Barna, and by 3 o'clock he again reached the Railway Hotel, where he was loudly cheered by a large body of people who assembled in front of the hotel. Mr Parnell proceeded to his rooms, and shortly before 4 o'clock, accompanied by a number of influential local friends, lay and clerical, took up a position outside the steps of the hotel door, and from which he addressed the meeting.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr Parnell, who was received with loud cheers, said - Fellow-countrymen, I feel very proud and very happy in being able to address so magnificent and vast a meeting of the people of Galway. But the circumstances under which this meeting has been called give me greater encouragement and greater hope than any that I have ever felt since I first entered into public life. (Cheers.) The circumstances of the present contest have been well calculated to try your devotion and your spirit of union - (cheers) - and it is a remarkable fact that you should have stood the test. It is a very remarkable fact. I do not care to go into what has taken place during the last few days in your town, and I say that under these circumstances, in view of the events which have happened, and of the speeches which have been made in this town during the last few days, it is the most remarkable fact in Irish history that the unity of our cause has been maintained (Cheers.). And now I wish to say a word or two with regard to the candidature of Mr Lynch now withdrawn. I admire and I appreciate the spirit with which he entered into this candidature, and I equally admire the spirit and the feelings and the temper he has exhibited in withdrawing his candidature. Had I known a few days sooner of Mr Lynch's desire to represent this constituency I would have cheerfully yielded to that desire, and had I not, on the contrary, been expressly informed that he would not on any account consent to come forward for this constituency Mr Lynch would have been your chosen man, and to-morrow he would have been my comrade, as I hope that in the future he will be my comrade. (Cheers.) But Mr Lynch was not willing at the time when my duty required me to consider the recommendation I should make to the constituency - he was not willing to come forward, and i was obliged to look for some person outside the people of Galway to whom to give my recommendation, and in that search of all the names of the gentlemen who were suggested to me, of all the names which occurred to my own mind, I came to the conclusion, carefully and after full consideration, that the name of Captain O'Shea - (some groans) - was the proper name to suggest for your consideration. (Cheers.) After that conclusion was formed, and after my recommendation had been made, my conclusion was fixed. Mr Lynch came forward, but he has not retired, and the history of this contest is a closed book to my mind. (Cheers.) Let me now say a word as to the merits of the candidature of the man who will be your member to-morrow night. I wish to speak also of his demerits and the faults I have had to find with him. I shall be perfectly open in dealing with the question. Mr O'Shea was returned for the County of Clare in 1880, not as a member of my part - he was returned unpledged to me, and so far as I know he has both in letter and in spirit kept the pledges which he gave to the people of Clare in 1880. (Cheers.) Immediately after his return a meeting was held in the City Hall in Dublin of the newly-elected Irish members for the purpose of choosing a chairman. I was nominated and I was proposed as chairman and leader of the party. Mr William Shaw was also proposed. Twenty members of the party voted for Mr William Shaw, and twenty-two members voted for me. Mr O'Shea was one of the twenty-two members who voted for me, and against Mr Shaw. (Cheers.) If Mr O'Shea and one other member had voted for Mr Shaw and not for me I should not have been the chairman and leader of the Irish party. Mr Shaw would have been chairman and leader of the part; and many proud things which have since been done for Ireland; and her present proud position could not have been accomplished. I am examining Mr O'Shea's public conduct and public records step by step, and so far as I have gone I ask would it not have been very unfair for me if there are men in the present part who voted against me then, if Captain O'Shea were left out of the party who voted for me then? (Hear, hear.) But such an isolated act as that would not in itself have been sufficient to give him a claim on me apart from any other consideration. As far as I know his votes have been irreproachable. I have been obliged to condemn him publicly because during the last Parliament he refused to sit in opposition with the members of the Irish party. That is the only fault that I have been able to find with his public conduct. He refused to sit in opposition, but I considered that that was a fatal fault - a fatal blemish, and I repeatedly told him in the last Parliament that unless he could see his way to sit on our side of the House I should not recommend him to the constituency of Clare, and he was not elected, and was not returned to Parliament, although I supported him in Liverpool for a seat which we could not carry ourselves, and to which I considered he had the first claim. But since this election commenced Mr O'Shea has given me a promise that he will sit on our side of the House, and, therefore, my last objection to him has disappeared. Under these circumstances, should I allow him to be persecuted and kept out of Parliament? I know that his return cannot be any injury to the National cause and cannot be any injury to the Irish party. He was the best man I knew of at the time, and I recommended him. As I already told you, I did not know of Mr Lynch's claims, and, having recommended him, I was in my position bound not to recede one hair's breadth, not one jot - (hear, hear) - but to carry through  that recommendation to the bitter end, and to test whether the people of Galway and the people of Ireland had that confidence in me which I believe they have, and which I believe the result of this election will show they have. During the eleven years since my entering into public life I have never led the Irish people astray, never led them into any crooked path; I have never led the Irish party astray. When courage was required and was necessary for the interest of the Irish nation I have shown it - (cheers) - and when moderation was necessary, and when temperate judgment for the nation was necessary, I have had the courage to show it, and I shall never lead the party or the nation astray until we have gained for you the right to lead and govern yourselves. (Cheers.) Now, fellow-countrymen, there are several gentlemen here who desire to address you. I think I have said everything that it was necessary for me to say with regard to the candidature of Mr O'Shea. I need only add this - that you must not think that because Mr Lynch has retied it is not necessary for you to go to the poll to-morrow and vote. All of you who have votes must go and vote for Mr O'Shea, for otherwise the Tories might take advantage of the situation, might go and poll for Mr Lynch in order, if possible, to run him close to the poll for Mr O'Shea. This is not Mr Lynch's fault. Mr Lynch has acted honourably towards me and towards the party. His name cannot now be withdrawn from the paper. It must be on the ballot paper, and there the Tories have the opportunity of trying to play this "dirty trick." But you will defeat this "dirty trick," and you will give your vote, not for Lynch, but for O'Shea, for the purpose of showing that you have voted for me and for Ireland. (Cheers.) I should have desired to have addressed you also apart from this election upon the great question of the day, but I think that in view of the fact that Father Sheehy is her and will address you I shall not longer detain you. I will only add, in conclusion, my conviction that the day is very near at hand when we shall have gained for Ireland the right to make her own laws on Irish soil. (Cheers.) When that day comes I shall regard my mission as fulfilled. I have not entered on this great struggle with any motive of personal ambition; but it is my duty to stand by you till these measures are gained for you. I have come down to Galway to stand by you in your cause for any appearance of division in our party, in the weakening of my authority, would have been fatal to our cause; and that is the reason why I am here; and I confidently leave the result in your hands. After many a month you will look back to the proceeding days with satisfaction, for the results will have proved you have to-day struck a great and successful blow for Ireland. (Loud cheers.)</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>This evening in the hall of the Young Ireland Society, Mr O'Kelly, M.P., delivered a very able and instructive lecture on "The Soudan and the Mahdi." The hall was crowded. About half-past 8 o'clock Mr Parnell ... entered the hall, and was received with loud cheers, the whole audience standing up till he took his seat on the platform.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr Parnell, who was received with loud applause, seconded it, and said he had listened with pleasure to the very interesting lecture which they had just heard. He spoke of the facility which Mr O'Kelly enjoyed in the country itself of studying its features and of informing himself of the character of those brave Arabs who fought for their independence. When the Soudan war commenced Mr O'Kelly penetrated as far as Dongloa, where he was stricken down, having suffered from hunger and thirst and fever, and where he was arrested by order of Clifford Lloyd. (Laughter and applause.) He knew Mr O'Kelly's sympathy with the Arabs. They recognised in him a lecturer of great power, a man of deeds rather than of words, a man of great talent, silent, but observant - a man who he wished would more often come to the front and add to the laurels he had won in Mexico, Cuba, and in the Soudan such forensic triumphs as he (Mr Parnell) knew he had the power of achieving. (Loud cheers.) Mr Parnell then referred to the fact that Mr Lynch was in the chair, a symbol fo their unity, and he expressed a hope that before long mr Lynch would be one of his colleagues, fighting by his side, not for years, but for some months in Parliament, till they came back to their own country to develop their own resources and to manage their own affairs. (Cheers.)</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
