<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Parliamentary Intelligence, The Times, Friday 9 April 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Parliamentary Intelligence</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-04-09">9 April 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00052"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">     
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url=""></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, who was received with Home Rule cheers, said, - I am glad to find that we have not been disappointed by the lobby rumours which have been circulated for some days past regard the right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs, and that he has after all, like a celebrated French general who defended Paris against the Germans, got his own plan (a laugh), and did not think the hour too late to give us the details of this important plan. But I noticed it is a somewhat significant, although it must have been to the right hon. gentleman a rather discouraging fact, that the unfolding of his plan elicited no enthusiasm of any kind from any section of the House. ("Hear, hear," and "No.") It was not until he had pointedly appealed to hon. members of the Conservative party that at last some small section of them gave him a cheer or two, and he did succeed in getting some faint applause from a few gentlemen upon these benches. The Conservative party has always been most remarkable for its wisdom. Being sometimes a small party, and very often in a minority, it is bound to be remarkable for its wisdom, and doubtless in its reception of the plan of the right hon. gentleman the member for Mid Lothian it had in its mind the declaration of the noble lord the member for Paddington, when he announced in a speech some two or three years since, "Concede nothing more to the Irish Nationalists, either in the direction of local self-government, county boards, or anything else." Of course the rank and file of the Conservative party under these circumstances could not have ventured to applaud the member for the Border Burghs. I may be told that the noble lord has improved since then. Some say he has been flirting with Home Rule and a separate Irish Parliament, the apparition which has caused so much consternation in the mind of the right hon. gentleman opposite, the member for the Hawick Burghs. I shall not express any opinion upon that point. (Laughter.) I do think, however, that the right hon. gentleman, in the comparison which he appeared to draw between the action of Lord Spencer remaining in the Cabinet and his own action in leaving it to Lord Spencer's disadvantage, scarcely stood upon very firm or satisfactory ground. (Cheers.) Englishmen love the man who fights his own corner out to the end; and Lord Spencer certainly did do that. (Cheers.) He went over to Ireland to fight a battle which was not his - to fight the battle of the Irish landlords, and he stuck to his post. (Home Rule cheers.) He faced every danger, every risk, both physical and otherwise; but the action of the right hon. gentleman opposite looks very like running away from his post. (Cries of "No," and cheers.) Although the right hon. gentleman attempted to explain to the House his reasons for leaving the Cabinet, he did not explain why he left his position of Chief Secretary. (Cries of "Oh," and Home Rule cheers.) Does the right hon. gentleman propose, in the event of his plan being carried out, to compete for the office of Chief Secretary? If he is unwilling to assume that office himself, is it very chivalrous of him to open such a tempting door to future aspirants? (Cheers.) He attempted to prove to the House what terrible things we should do in an Irish Parliament by making an allusion to the motion which I moved in the last Parliament in 1882. I do not desire to go back over old quarrels. It generally happens that those who are defeated dislike to recur to those distant and unhappy recollections; but I have nothing to retract in regard them. (Home Rule cheers.) The right hon. gentleman read that resolution to the house. I complained of the execution and imprisonment of innocent men. I believed then, as now, that innocent men were executed. (Home Rule cheers.) I never accused the right hon. gentleman or Lord Spencer of having believed the same thing - of having sanctioned the execution knowing that the men were innocent. But I can scarcely think that the right hon. gentleman is of the same opinion to-day. What about the case of Bryan Kilmartin, who was sentenced to penal servitude for life? (Cries of "Order," and cheers). Upon the case being brought forward by us, and supported by the noble lord the member for Paddington, if my memory serves me right, and one or two other Conservative members, Bryan Kilmartin was released during, I believe, the tenure of office of the right hon. gentleman. The right hon. gentleman taunts us about the language of the resolution to which I have referred, and about the language of the manifesto which was issued by my hon. friend the member for the Scotland Division of Liverpool. But if I consider that all these things took place, was I not right, at the very height of this reign of terror in Ireland, to state what I did publicly? I did not see how, with any sort of consideration for my public duty as regards questions of law and order in Ireland of which the right hon. gentleman has constituted himself the sole champion to-night, I could refrain from bringing these matters under the attention of the House.</p>
         <p>"That in the captain's but a choleric word
            "Which in the soldier is flat blasphemy."</p>
         <p>While the right hon. gentleman bases such weighty arguments on the resolution to which he refers and the expressions in the manifesto of my hon. friend, he passes over the language which has been used since then in Ireland by a very prominent member of the late Administration - a man who was specially charged with the maintenance of law and order in Ireland, no less a personage than the Attorney-General of the late Government. Speaking at a public meeting in that country, the late Attorney-General asserted that the blood of Giffen was on the head of Lord Spencer. (Hear, hear.) The right hon. gentleman has no censure for that language. He does not take that language as an example of the great risk of entrusting the care of the lives of the Irish people to a future Conservative Ministry under the plan he has formulated to-night. Surely no language that was ever used by any of my hon. friends exceeded in gravity the charge that I have just quoted. (Home Rule and Ministerial cheers.) Certainly the language used in the resolution and in the manifesto of my hon. friend was mildness in comparison. (Hear, hear.) Of course, if the question of the future relations of England and Ireland is to be discussed with the heat, I will not say ill-temper, shown by the right hon. gentleman, that will greatly increase the difficulty of discussion. But I hope his example will not be imitated. I do not wish to go into a justification of our action in the last Parliament, but I could do so if I wished. I could remind the House of the agents used by the right hon. gentleman in upholding law and order. I could remind him of the result of the trial in French's case (cheers), the Inspector of the Irish Constabulary, a man whom the right hon. gentleman did not shrink from defending in this House. I do not desire to go into these things, but I believe history will record that in every resolution which we moved with reference to the administration of the right hon. gentleman we were more than amply justified. The right hon. gentleman has spoke of assassination literature, and would lead the House to believe that American sympathy for the Irish cause is confined to the supporters of this assassination literature. He has spoken of Mr. Ford. All I can say with regard to him, is that he has been constantly denouncing myself and my policy during the last five years. The right hon. gentleman is right in saying that this assassination literature is no American literature, and if he has studied it attentively he will also see that it is not Irish literature either. If he were to study the literature of America now he would find that the sympthy [sic] with the just settlement of the claims of Ireland by the concession of a domestic Legislature is shared by all classes in that country (cheers), whether Irish or native-born Americans; and it is more especially the native-born Americans who welcome the efforts of the Prime Minister, in the belief that they will bring peace between England and Ireland, and more especially between Irish-Americans and England. It is a remarkable fact that the great meetings which are now being held in every State in America are mainly summoned and organized by native-born Americans and by the editors and conductors of the purely American newspapers; and we regard the fact that during the last five or six months we have succeeded in entirely gaining the sympathy of the two great American political parties, the Democratic and the Republican, as an omen of great hope for the future of our cause. The right hon. gentleman in speaking about the Land Purchase Bill turned to the Radical members sitting below him in order to catch a cheer or two in his denunciation of the proposal to give money to Irish landlords. Now, Sir, I do not propose to go into the merits of this question, but regarding that matter just as I regard the other matter I will only say that it is not out of the mouth of the right hon. gentleman that such unkind words should proceed, because he himself brought in a Bill in the last Parliament as a member of the Government for buying out Irish landlords. (Home Rule cheers and laughter.) If that Bill had succeeded in passing - and unfortunately it was added to the long list of failures (laughter) - and if it had been successful, which was a still more doubtful prospect, it would have necessitated an additional payment of a very large sum of money for the purpose of buying out the Irish landlords - the very thing he denounced to-night with so much eloquence, in order if he possibly could to throw some discredit on the present scheme. Perhaps I might say, in leaving the right hon. gentleman, as regards his picture of the horrible consequences which will result to Ireland and to England if any such proposal as that suggested in the Bill under discussion were adopted - the consequences of physical force, of rebellion, and of separation - I believe so far from anything of the kind happening that your guarantee of a peaceful solution between the two countries will be enormously increased. (Home Rule cheers.) Why do I say that they will be enormously increased? Whey will be increased for several reasons. Why is there trouble in Ireland now; why do the people talk about separation; why does my hon. friend the member for Tyrone write what the right hon. gentleman considers violent passages in United Ireland? It is because the people are desperate and have nothing to lose, but give them a Constitution and they will be proportionately careful not to lose that. Every violent speech, every criminal action, will be so many nails driven into the coffin of their Constitution. You will have every guarantee you possess now. These cannot be weakened. The forces of the Crown will act just as freely and effectively as they do know. Even the control of the constabulary is to be withheld from us until their character has been altered, because they are an armed force. Although it has been impossible or very difficult for England to govern Ireland without 15,000 armed policemen, we are expected to govern Ireland without any policemen at all. (Laughter.) Certainly, no additional strength can be added to the physical force argument; and you will have those guarantees of peace and contentment which have always accompanied, in the experience which we have had, the concessions of those measures to the colonies and to the countries of Europe. You will have these as your surest and best guarantees in addition to those you possess at present. (Home Rule cheers.) I will now pass on to the measure from the consideration of which my attention was withdrawn by the speech of the right hon. gentleman. I desire to speak very briefly. It is difficult to express a definite and positive expression of opinion until I have seen the measure placed completely before us. Still, however, I think it is right that I should say something about the merits of the Bill as they have been expressed to us by the Prime Minister. (Hear, hear.) Allow me to say that I think it will prove a happy and fortunate thing both for Ireland and England that there was one man living, one English statesman living, with the great power and the extraordinary ability of the right hon. gentleman, to lend his voice on behalf of poor, helpless Ireland on this question. (Home Rule cheers.) He had devoted his great mind, his extraordinary energy, to the unravelling of this question, and to the construction of this Bill. It seemed to many people that the task might prove too large, too terrible, even for him. I believe it will not be so. (Home Rule cheers.) But whatever may be the fate of the Bill, the cause of Ireland, the cause of Irish autonomy, will enormously gain by the genius of the right hon. gentleman. (Hear, hear.) He has drafted this Bill; he has explained it to the House in a speech of extraordinary eloquence. To Ireland, I suppose - to none of the sons of Ireland - at any time has there ever been given the genius and talent of the right hon. gentleman - certainly nothing approaching to it in these days. I thank, therefore, the right hon. gentleman for the energy and the time he has devoted to this matter, and I believe sincerely in my heart that the effect of it will be that the people of England will recognize as the result of what he has done no less than the people of Ireland, that he has been to them a national benefactor. (Cheers.) But there are undoubtedly great faults and blots in the measure. The right hon. gentleman has had to meet very hostile criticism, and a very extraordinary state of affairs. He has seen his officers leaving his side one by one, and drawing their swords, as the right hon. member for the Border Burghs did to-night, against him. (Hear, hear). And he has had, I suppose, to shape his measure to meet the tremendous opposition which has been invoked. But there are several points which it will be our duty when the measure reaches its Committee stage to oppose very strongly, and to press for their serious modification and amendment. The question of the has been touched upon. In giving up the customs we should practically give to you the whole control of six-eighths or three-fourths of the revenues of Ireland. It would be absolutely as much within your power as it is now, both as regards the original assessment of the taxes and the receiving of the money. The right hon. gentleman has explained to us that if we were to insist on separate custom-houses, England, by collecting the duties on whisky and tobacco in her own custom-houses, gives £1,400,000 a year. This, of course, is a very serious consideration, and it may be very fairly balanced against the cession of the control of the customs and excise. But at the same time, if the right hon. gentleman the Prime Minister is to take credit for giving us that £1,400,000 as a consequence of the retention of the custom-houses and the collection of the revenue within the Imperial authority, I do not think he is also entitled to claim credit for it a second time, and make us pay out of the £1,400,000 a million for the Irish Constabulary, over whom we are not to have any sort of control at all, at least at present. Then there is the question of the contribution to the Imperial expenditure. I cannot admit - I say it with great deference - either the justice or the liberality of the standard of comparison which he has taken. It appears to be the amount of property which comes under assessment regarding the payment of legacy and sucession [sic] duties. That is the most unfavourable standard for us that he could have chosen. Of course, I understand that he was anxious to make the best bargain he could for England, and to secure as large a contribution for the Imperial Treasury as possible; but he should also remember that Ireland is a very poor country, and that with such a small balance as he showed on the budget of £400,000 a year, it will be impossible for floating loans. Irish landlords now can borrow money for the improvement of their estates; Irish tenants can borrow money for improving their farms; local bodies can borrow money for sanitary purposes within their jurisdiction. All these are very important matters. But we shall have to surrender all these under the scheme of the right hon. gentleman (hear, hear), and we shall be left with a Budget which only exceeds the annual balance by about £400,000 a year, and a budget arrived at on an estimate which necessitates that the consumption of spirits, not only in Ireland, but also in England, should continue at its present rate, and, of course, that the duty should be kept as it is now. Probably one of the first things that will happen in Ireland under an Irish Legislature will be the imposition of restrictions in regard to the sale of strong drink on Sundays as well as on other days, and certainly we must anticipate, and I should hope we can anticipate, a considerable reduction in the amount of the revenue derived from those duties. It is therefore scarcely fair, I think, to press us too closely, or to insist on driving too hard a bargain in this matter. If the sum is agreed upon of course we must pay it; we will pay it (hear, hear); but it would be most unfortunate if the right hon. gentleman selected such a standard of comparison as would lead him to adopt the proportion of one-fifteenth. In that case only would there be any possibility of the danger which the right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs has conjured up as to the repudiation of the Imperial debt, an attempt which, if made, would be entirely unsuccessful, because you have the collection of the customs and the excise absolutely in your own hands. When you are proposing a great settlement which can only succeed if freely accepted by public opinion in Ireland, is it worth while for a rich country like England on the question of £1,000,000, one way or the other to drive too hard a bargain? I do not want to go into the question to-night, but after reading the article by Mr. Giffen, which has attracted so much attention, and a communication in The Times of this morning from a gentleman who evidently knows what he is writing about, I think that it is clear that one-twentieth is a far better standard of the relative share of the two countries than that most unfortunate standard of one-fifteenth which the right hon. gentleman has adopted. We could show several standards much more favourable to us, based upon the things consumed in Ireland, and which will show that Ireland is a very much poorer country in comparison with England than is expressed by the proportion which the right hon. gentleman has selected. I have every confidence that when the time comes when this Bill is in Committee, and when we put forward our case, the conscience, not only of the House of Commons but of the right hon. gentleman the Prime Minister will be touched in regard to this matter, and that he will see that his zeal for making a good bargain for his own country has led him into doing an unintentional injustice to Ireland in this question of the contribution towards the Imperial expenditure. I think, also, that the question of the Royal Irish Constabulary has been left in a most unsatisfactory condition. I think that it is most unfair to ask us to pay for a force, or a large proportion of it, over which we have no control whatever. This, however, is also a matter upon which we shall have more light when we see the Bill of the right hon. gentleman. There is another important point to which I wish to allude - namely, with regard to vote by order. As explained by the right hon. gentleman, the first order elected by a fancy franchise is given the right of hanging up any Bill for three years. I understood the words of the right hon. gentleman to be these - "Three years or until a dissolution, whichever is the longer." I think that that would indicate three years as the minimum [italics] of time during which they could hang up a Bill; and if a dissolution did not take place before three years the Bill would be hung up for a still longer period. I should be glad if I were mistaken on this point; it is possible that I may be; but in any case, whatever the period might be, it would be absolutely within the power of the first order, in which from the nature of the case the popular party in Ireland could not obtain many representatives, to hang up any measure they pleased, and so to bring the proceedings of the Legislature to a deadlock. I am one of those who have always insisted that a due proportion of representation should be given to the Protestant minority in Ireland, and anything also which would tend to prevent rash, hasty, ill-considered, or revolutionary legislation I cordially welcome; but as far as the measure leads to obstruction more or less permanent to legislation and the means of bringing about a deadlock on the part of a body of members who cannot be said to be representative, I think that it ought to be modified so as to render such delay as that absolutely impossible. (Hear, hear.) As regards the measure itself, the Prime Minister has truly said that it ought not to proceed unless it is cheerfully welcomed, not only by the Irish members, but by the Irish people. I quite agree in that proposition, and I am convinced that if our views are fairly met the result of this Bill will be to agreeably disappoint the right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs and all those who think with him, that it will be cheerfully accepted by the Irish people as a solution of the long-standing dispute between the two countries, and that it will lead to the prosperity and peace of Ireland and the satisfaction of England. (Cheers.)</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
