<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Untitled, The Derby Daily Telegraph, Thursday 11 February 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Untitled</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="" level="j">The Derby Daily Telegraph</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-02-11">11 February 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7010684">Derby, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00050"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">    
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/bl/0000327/18860211/001/0002"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>The election for Galway borough is taking place to-day, but Mr. Parnell has made his authority paramount amongst the Nationalists and his nominee will be returned. The revolt was only temporary, and the rebellious could not withstand Mr. Parnell's iron will and determination, Captain O'Shea will consequently be returned, even though the electors themselves had set their hearts upon Mr. Lynch. The Nationalist leader took the opportunity yesterday of publicly explaining why he had resolved to push the Captain's claims to this "bitter end." In the first place the accepted candidate voted for Mr. Parnell when he was chosen leader of the party by a narrow majority of 2 votes over Mr. Shaw in 1880. A number of other reasons were given, but that already mentioned appeared to be the chief. The whole tenor of the defence of his course of action amounted to an admission by Mr. Parnell, that personal friendship was the prevailing motive for selecting Captain O'Shea over the other candidate. We need not point out how remarkable it was that Mr. Parnell should have understood that Mr. Lynch did not intend to stand, whereas everybody else knew that he was de facto [italics] the accepted candidate until the new nominee appeared on the scene. It was indeed a very lame defence, and the fact that it should have been implicitly accepted proves that Mr. Parnell has reached the position for which he has so persistently striven and become the absolute autocrat of his party. He has foisted upon Galway a man of admittedly inferior deserts from the Nationalist point of view than the one the people would have chosen for themselves. In the course of his semi-apologetic statement the Irish dictator was drawn to speak of his past services, and he did so with rather an unaccustomed absence of modesty. The people were asked to believe that he alone was responsible for all the recent legislation for the amelioration of the condition of Ireland. "He knew that the people of Galway would obey him, and that Ireland would stand by him. When during the eleven long years since he had entered Irish politics did he advise them wrongly? When since he accepted the leadership did he lead them astray? When did he lead them on a crooked path? He believed he showed courage when courage was required, and he showed, too, that he could be moderate when moderation was necessary." We should imagine that Mr. Healy, Mr. Sexton, Mr. McCarthy, Mr. Sullivan, and even Mr. Biggar feel that some share of the credit is theirs. Mr. Parnell's proud boast that he never made a mistake was ostensibly applied to the future, as well as the past. He repeated to the men of Galway yesterday, the promise he has made in many places during the past few months - to obtain an Independent Parliament. The man who has never experienced a failure, is naturally emboldened to prophecy, but even in the history of Mr. Parnell, a time may come of disappointed hopes and projects. Only a very sanguine nature could hope for the full realization of the scheme which Mr. Parnell has before him.</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
