<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Ireland, Mr. Parnell and his Constituents, The Daily News, Thursday 22 January 1885</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Ireland, Mr. Parnell and his Constituents</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="181031558" level="j">The Daily News</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1885-01-22">22 January 1885</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00073"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">    
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/bl/0000051/18850122/030/0006"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>He was greeted with vociferous cheering, and said:- Mr. Mayor and Ladies and Gentlemen, - The mayor has kindly claimed for me your indulgence, and, indeed, last night when I set out upon the journey which he has described to you I felt a sinking at my heart, lest when I should reach Dublin I should find myself unable to go any further, or to keep my engagement with you this evening. But when I approached Ireland I found myself getting better and better - (cheers, and cries of "Bravo") - and when I landed - (interruption at the rear of the building and cries of "Turn 'em out") - when I reached Dublin and came near your beautiful city of Cork, the change became increasedly [sic] marked. (Cheers.) So that when I reached your city I felt myself quite restored and strong as if nothing had ever been the matter with me. (Cheers, and a voice: "God keep you so long.") But at the same time, I do intend to claim your indulgence this evening, and to make my remarks very much shorter and fewer than they would have been under other circumstances. ("Hear, hear," and applause.) The previous speaker, Mr. Mahony, has reminded you and me that it wants a month or two of five years since the constituency of Cork honoured me by making me its representative. (Cheers, and a voice: "You are worthy of it;" another voice: "And you killed Whiggery." (Cheers.) Mr. Parnell: My victory was a very remarkable one. (Hear, hear.) Coming as I did amongst you, and representing the privileges which I did represent, it was extraordinary that in the limited constituency of the city at that time and with the ideas that then prevailed amongst that constituency, you should have selected a politician such as me. (Laughter and applause.) Your member, your late respected member, Joseph Ronayne - (cheers) - had often told me that it would be impossible for Cork to return two Nationalists, and my return was the first occasion on which two members of my way of thinking sat for and represented your city. (A voice: The knew you were the right sort, sir.) Mr. Parnell - But great as was the advance marked with my return by a very narrow majority, it was as nothing to the change which has since taken place. (Hear, hear.) Altogether leaving aside the great extension of the constituency which the Franchise Act has made, you have since shown in the election of my able colleague Mr. Deasy - (cheers) - that it is no trouble for you to elect any number of Nationalists - (applause) and the present constituency of Cork under the Franchise Act will leave you in a position free from care so far as the choice of your representatives goes. I do not suppose that Cork will ever again be contested by the oligarchy in this city. At that election in 1880 I laid certain principles before you, and you accepted them. (Applause, and cries of "We do.") I said, and I pledged myself, that I should form one of an independent Irish party to act in opposition to every English Government which refused to concede the just rights of Ireland - (loud applause) - and the longer the time which has gone by since, the more I am convinced that that is the true policy to pursue so far as Parliamentary policy is concerned, and that it will be impossible for either or both of the English parties to contend for any long time against a determined band of Irishmen acting honestly upon these principles and back by the Irish people. (Cheers.) But we have not alone had that object in view. We have always been very careful not to fetter or control the people in any way; not to prevent them from doing anything by their own strength which it is possible for them to do. Sometimes perhaps in our anxiety in this direction we have asked them to do what is beyond their strength; but I hold that it is better even to encourage you to do what is beyond your strength, even should you fail sometimes in the attempt, than to teach you to be subservient and unreliant [sic]. (Applause.) You have been encouraged to organize yourselves, to depend upon the rectitude of your cause for your justification, and to depend upon the determination which has helped Irishmen through many centuries to retain the name of Ireland, and to retain the nationhood of Ireland. (Applause.) Nobody can point to any single action of ours in the House of Commons or out of it which was not based upon the knowledge that behind us existed a strong and brave people, that without the help of the people our exertions would be nothing, and that with that help and with their confidence we should be, as I believe we shall prove to be in the near future, invincible and unconquerable. (Great applause.) The electors who will be swamped - (laughter) - in the great mass of Irishmen now admitted to the rights of the Constitution so far as they existed in this country were, on the whole, faithful to their trust. Indeed, it was not until we showed by a good many proofs that we could do without an enlargement of the franchise, and that with the old restricted suffrage we could do all that was necessary in the way of Parliamentary operations, that the opposition to the admission of the masses of the Irish people to the franchise disappeared. (Applause.) But I look forward to the future with a light heart. I am convinced that the five or six hundred thousand Irishmen who within a year must vote for the man of their choice will be as true to Ireland, and even truer to Ireland than those who have gone before them, and that we may safely trust to them the exercise of the great and important privilege, unequalled in its greatness and magnitude in the history of any nation, which will shortly be placed upon them. I am convinced that when the reckoning up comes, after the general election of 1886; that we in Ireland shall have cause to congratulate ourselves in the possession of a strong party, which will bear down all opposition, and which, aided by the organization of our country behind us, will enable us to gain for our country those rights which were stolen from us. (Cheers.) We shall struggle, as we have been struggling, for the great and important interests of the Irish tenant farmer; we shall ask that his industry shall not be fettered by rent; we shall ask also from the farmer in return that he shall do what in him lies to encourage the struggling manufactures of Ireland, and that he shall not think it too great a sacrifice to be called upon, when he wants anything, when he has to purchase anything, to consider how he may get it of Irish material and manufacture - (hear, hear) - even supposing he has to pay a little more for it. (Cheers.) I am sorry if the agricultural population has shown itself somewhat deficient in its sense of its duty in this respect up to the present time, but I feel convinced that the matter has only to be put before them to secure the opening up of the most important markets in this country for those manufactures which have always existed, and for those which have been reopened anew as a consequence of the recent exhibitions - the great exhibition in Dublin and the other equally great one in Cork - which have been recently held. (Cheers.) We shall also endeavour to secure for the labourer some recognition and some right in the land of his country. (Applause.) We don't care whether it be the prejudices of the farmer or of the landlord that stand in his way. (Hear, hear.) We consider that whatever class tries to obstruct the labourer in the possession of those fair and just rights to which he is entitled, that class should be put down and coerced, if you will, into doing justice to the labourer. We have shown we desire to benefit the labourer by the passing of the Labourers Act, which, if maimed and mutilated by many of its provisions, undoubtedly will secure for the labouring classes a portion of what we have been striving to secure for them. Well, gentlemen, I go back from the consideration of these questions to the land question, in which the labourers' question is also involved, and the manufacturers' question. Every Irish politician must be forcibly driven to the consideration of the great question of national self-government for Ireland. (Cheers.) I do not know how this great question will be eventually settled. I do not know whether England will be wise in time and concede to constitutional arguments and methods the restitution of that which was stolen from us towards the close of the last century. (Cheers.) It is given to none of us to forecast the future, and just as it is impossible for us to say in what way or by what means the national question may be settled, in what way full justice may be done to Ireland, so it is impossible for us to say to what extent that justice shall be done. We cannot ask for less than the restitution of Grattan's Parliament - (loud cheers) - with its important privileges, and wide and far-reaching constitution. We cannot under the British Constitution ask for more than the restitution of Grattan's Parliament. (Renewed cheers.) But no man has the right to fix the boundary to the march of a nation. (Great cheering.) No man has a right to say to his country, "Thus far shalt thou go, and no further," and we have never attempted to fix the ne plus ultra to the progress of Ireland's nationhood, and we never shall. (Cheers.) But, gentlemen, while we leave those things to time, circumstances, and the future we must, each one of us resolve in our own hearts that we shall at all times do everything which lies within us to obtain for Ireland the fullest measure of her rights. (Applause.) In this way we shall avoid difficulties and contentions amongst each other. In this way we shall not give up anything which the future may put in favour of our country, and while we struggle to-day for that which may seem possible for us with our combination we must struggle for it with the proud consciousness that we shall not do anything to hinder or prevent better men who may come after us from gaining better things than those for which we now contend. (Prolonged applause.)</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
