<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The Galway Election, Enthusiastic Demonstrations, Speeches of Mr Parnell, M.P., The Freeman's Journal, Thursday 11 February 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The Galway Election, Enthusiastic Demonstrations, Speeches of Mr Parnell, M.P.</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="315698503" level="j">The Freeman's Journal</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">5-6</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-02-11">11 February 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7001306">Dublin, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00049, speech_00050, speech_00051"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">  
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://archive-irishnewsarchive-com.ezp.lib.cam.ac.uk/Olive/APA/INA.Edu/Default.aspx#panel=document"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell said - People of Castelgar, I am very much obliged to you for assembling in such numbers at such short notice to meet me here to-day. I am glad to be able to announce to you that the dispute with reference to the representation of Galway has been settled by the self-sacrifice of Mr. Lynch and his friends cheers, who have retired in favour of the candidate Captain O'Shea, recommended by me to the constituency (cheers). I will take this opportunity of telling you that if I had known that Mr. Lynch was coming forward for the representation of Galway I should have cheerfully accepted him (hear, hear), because I believe him to be in every respect -</p>
         <p>A Voice - An honest man.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - As my friend says, I believe him to be an honest man, and a gentleman suited in every way to represent with honesty and ability the people of Galway. In the duty which devolved upon me as the leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party, and of the nation (cheers) to advise the people of Galway with regard to the selection of their candidate it became necessary for me to inquire some ten days ago as to whether there was any local candidate in existence who desired to offer himself to the constituency, and I was informed on authority by Mr. O'Connor that the only local candidate, Mr. Lynch, would not offer himself, that he had expressly declined to come forward for the town of Galway, and that he did not desire and could not be induced under any circumstances to offer himself to the constituency. It therefore became necessary for me to look around for some outside person not connected with the town, and the best candidate that I could find was Captain O'Shea (hear, hear). I therefore took upon myself the responsibility of recommending him to the constituency.</p>
         <p>A Voice - You are welcome.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - Unfortunately, owing to a misunderstanding, Mr. Lynch was induced to offer himself in opposition to Mr. O'Shea, the gentleman recommended by myself. Of course, as you will have seen a crisis of some gravity, difficulty, and danger then arose; but, as I have just told you, that crisis has happily been terminated by the patriotic withdrawal of Mr Lynch, and I am her to-day to say a few words to you in favour of Mr. O'Shea, to give you some information as to his abilities as a candidate, and to show that you may without fear and with full confidence go to the poll tomorrow and record your votes in favour of O'Shea (cheers). Although Mr. Lynch has withdrawn it will still be necessary for everyone of you, all the voters in this district, to go and vote all the same because Mr. Lynch's name will still be on the ballot paper, and it is possible, I believe it is more than that, it is probable that the Tories will go and vote for Lynch, to a man to try and return him against O'Shea, in the event of the people of Galway not coming forward in sufficient numbers to support O'Shea. Such a result would not be Mr. Lynch's fault, because he has done everything that an honourable man could be called upon to do to withdraw from his candidature, and advise all his friends to support O'Shea. It will be your duty to follow his example, and go to the poll and put a cross opposite the name of O'Shea. With regard to Mr. O'Shea's merits as a candidate. He represented the county Clare in the last Parliament. He was returned for the county of Clare in 1880. I did not then know him when he came forward that time. He was returned for the county of Clare without any recommendation; in fact he was not at that time any candidate, but, notwithstanding this fact, immediately after his return in 1880 he came up to Dublin and attended the meeting of the Irish Parliamentary Party which was held in City Hall, when the famous division took place as to whether I or Mr. William Shaw should be leader of the Irish Parliamentary Party, and he voted in my favour as leader of the party at that crisis in Irish history (hear, hear). My leadership was only carried by a majority of two votes, and it is right for me to remember that service which O'Shea then rendered to the cause of Ireland as well as to myself personally (cheers). If he and one other gentleman had voted against me on that occasion I should have been deprived of the leadership, and many great things which have been done for Ireland from that day to this could never have been done. There are men in the Irish Party of to-day - more than one man - who voted against me on that occasion, and if more than one man who voted against me is in the party to-day, why should O'Shea not be in it, who voted in my favour? I will now proceed further. I have had one fault to find with Mr. O'Shea's public action. I have not concealed my views from him. I have repeatedly told him that I could not support him at the general election that has just concluded for the representation of any Irish constituency, unless that fault were amended, and I did not support him, I declined to support him for Galway until he had given me a promise that that fault should not be laid to his charge for the future. The only fault that I have been able to find against him in regard to his Parliamentary action during the last Parliament was that he constantly refused to sit on the same side of the house with us in opposition. But he has given me a promise - I guarantee to you that he will keep this promise - that for the future he will sit in opposition with the Irish Party; therefore my last objection to him as a candidate has disappeared, and not only my last objection, but the last possible objection that could be raised against him by any man as a candidate has disappeared, and you may now freely accept him with every confidence that he has fulfilled all the conditions which are required as preliminaries from the other members of the Irish Party, and that he will act in the same way as they will act (cheers). I have done my duty to the country and to the party in this matter (cheers). I have never led the country astray (loud cheers). For eleven years I have worked for you and I have fought for you, beginning with only one other man by my side, two of us against 650. We have held the flag of Ireland high up by night and by day, and we have gradually recruited our strength, until now we are a solid wedge-like body of eighty six members, whom we have the power to drive into the heart of the English parties (cheers), and to split them to pieces, to grind them to powder if they refuse to concede the just rights of Ireland (cheers). I have never led Ireland wrong. I have always led her straight, and I have always led the party straight (cheers). I am not leading them crooked to-day, and I am confident, and the magnificent declaration of confidence in yesterday's Freeman [italics] supplemented to-day by the adhesion of 70 members of the Irish Party, gathered by telegrams from all parts of the country shows that I retain the confidence of my colleagues (cheers) unabated and untouched.</p>
         <p>A Voice - And of the country.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - I believe that the result of the Galway election will prove in no small fashion, in no weak manner, that I retain the confidence of the constituency of Galway and of the people of Ireland.</p>
         <p>A Voice - You are worthy of it.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - And you will find, fellow countrymen, that on to-morrow when you will vote for O'Shea, when you will return him at the head of the poll, that you will have done a service as great, probably, as will every have been done by any Irish constituency for Ireland. I do not wish to detain you. I have to attend several other meetings to-day, and the time is short. I will ask you to go to work amongst your friends and your neighbours and tell them what I have said to you, and ask them to trust me, and to believe that the cause of Ireland is safe in my hands and that in a very short time I shall bring back to you an Irish Parliament to College green (Cheers), where you will be masters of your own destinies and of the destinies of our country (cheers). Three cheers for O'Shea (cheers).</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell, M.P., who was loudly cheered said - Fellow-countrymen, I feel very proud and very happy in being able to address so magnificent and vast a meeting of the people of Galway, but the circumstances under which this meeting has been called give me greater encouragement and greater hope than any that I ever felt since I first entered public life (applause). The circumstances of the present contest have been well calculated to try your devotion and your spirit of union (hear, hear), but it is a remarkable fact that you have stood the test (hear) - it is a very remarkable fact. I do not care to go into what has taken place during the last few days in your town but I say that under these circumstances, in the face of events that have happened, and of speeches which have been made, in those circumstances during the last few days it is perhaps the most remarkable fact in Irish history that the unity of our cause has been maintained (cheers).</p>
         <p>A voice - And will (renewed cheers).</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - And now I wish to say a word or two with regard to the candidature (hear, hear), and I equally admire the spirit, and the feeling and the temper he has exhibited in withdrawing his candidature. Had I known a few days sooner of Mr. Lynch's desire to represent his constituency, I would have cheerfully yielded to that desire (hear, hear). Had I not on the contrary been expressly informed that Mr. Lynch would on no account consent to come forward for this constituency, Mr. Lynch would have been my chosen man, and to-morrow he would have been my comrade, as I hope that in future he will be my comrade (hear, hear). But Mr. Lynch was not willing, and when my duty required me to consider the recommendation that I should make to the constituency he was not at the time willing to come forward, and I was obliged to look for somebody outside the people of Galway to give my recommendation to and in that search, after a careful and full and fair examination of all the names of the gentlemen who were suggested to me, of all the names of those which occurred to my own mind, I came to the conclusion carefully and after full consideration that the name of Captain O'Shea was the proper name for me to suggest for your consideration (hear, hear). After that conclusion was formed - after my recommendation has been made - Mr. Lynch came forward. He has now retired, and the history of those days is a closed book for my mind. Let me now say a word as to the merits of your candidate - of the man who will be your member to-morrow night (hear, hear). I shall speak also of his demerits and of the fault which I have had to find with him. I shall be perfectly open in my dealing and in my representation of this question to you. Mr. O'Shea was returned for the county Clare in 1880, not as a member of my party - so far as I know he has fully both in the letter and the spirit kept the pledges which he gave to the people of Clare in 1880 (hear, hear). Immediately after his return a meeting was held in the City Hall in Dublin - a meeting of the newly appointed Irish members - for the purpose of choosing a chairman. I was proposed as chairman and leader of the party (applause). Mr. William Shaw was also proposed as chairman and leader of the party (groans). Twenty members of the party voted for William Shaw and twenty-two members of the party voted for me (cheers).</p>
         <p>A Voice - You are worthy of it.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - Mr. O'Shea was one of the twenty-two members who voted for me against Shaw (cheers). If he had voted against me and one other member who voted for me had voted against me, I would not be the chairman and leader. Shaw would have been leader, and many things that have been done for Ireland and her present position I fear would not have been attained. Some members of the present party voted against me on that occasion. I am examining Mr. O'Shea's public conduct and record step by step, and so far as I have done so I ask you would it not have been very unfair of me if there are men in the present party who voted against me then, and who are now members of the party - would it not have been unfair of me to have kept back O'Shea since he voted for me then? (hear, hear). But such an isolated act as that would not have given him any claim apart from other considerations. Mr. O'Shea's votes have been irreproachable. Although he has never given a vote to my knowledge with which I could find any fault, I have been obliged to condemn him to himself and publicly, because during the last Parliament he refused to sit in opposition with the Irish Party (hear, hear). That is the only fault that I have been ever able to find with his public conduct - the refusal to sit in opposition. But I considered that that was a vital fault, a vital blemish, and I repeatedly told him during the last Parliament that unless he could see his way to promise to sit on our side of the house I could not in the new Parliament recommend him to the constituency of Clare at the general election, and he was not returned to Parliament although I supported him in a constituency in Liverpool, which we could not carry for ourselves, and to which I considered he was entitled to have the first claim, so far as I could decide the matter. But since the general election Mr. O'Shea has given me a promise that he will sit in opposition on our side of the house (hear, hear), and my last objection to him as a candidate has disappeared. Well, now, under these circumstances, was I to allow him to be persecuted and kept out of Parliament? (No, no.) I know that his return cannot be any public injury - cannot be any injury or damage to the National cause; I know that his return cannot be any injury to the Irish party. He was the best man I knew of at the time that I recommended him. I have told you that I did not know then of Mr. Lynch's claims, and having recommended him in my position I was bound not to recede on hair's breadth (loud cheers), one jot, but carry through that recommendation to the bitter end to test whether the people of Galway and the people of Ireland had that confidence in me which I believe they have (cheers), and which the result of this election will show that they have renewed (cheers). I have bever led during election long years since my entry into public life, I have never led the Irish people astray (cheers). I have never led them into any crooked path (no, no). I have never led the Irish Party astray (cheers). When courage was required, when it was necessary for the interests of the nation I have shown it (cheers), and when moderation was required, when moderation was necessary and temperate judgment for the interests of the nation I had courage to show it (renewed cheers), and I never will lead the party or the nation astray (cheers) until we have gained for you the right to lead and to govern yourselves (cheers). Now, countrymen, there are several gentlemen who desire to address you. I think I have said everything that is necessary for me to say with regard to the candidature of Mr. O'Shea. I will only add this word - that you must not think because Mr. Lynch has retired it is unnecessary for you to come and vote to-morrow. All who have votes must come and record their votes for O'Shea (cheers), otherwise the Tories, who have been desirous of taking advantage of the situation, may poll for Lynch in order if possible to run him close to the poll of O'Shea. This is not Mr. Lynch's fault. Mr. Lynch has acted honourably and fairly towards me, and towards the party - it is not his fault if the Conservatives vote for him to-morrow, his name cannot be withdrawn from the poll now, it must appear on the ballot paper, and therefore the Tories have the opportunity to try and play the dirty trick (groans). But you will defeat this dirty trick by giving such a vote in favour of O'Shea as will show that you have voted for me, and for principle, and for Ireland.</p>
         <p>A Voice - Parnell forever (renewed cheers).</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - I would have desired to address you also apart from this election upon the great question of the day, but I think that in view of the fact that Father Sheehy is her (cheers), who will address you some further words I ought not to detain you longer. I will only add, in conclusion, my conviction that the day is very nearly at hand when we shall have gained for Ireland the right to make her own laws upon Irish soil (cheers). When that day comes I shall regard my mission as fulfilled. I have not entered into this great struggle out of any motives of personal ambition, but it is my duty to stand by you until these great measures are completed and gained for you (cheers). I have come down to Galway to stand by you and your course, because I believe that any division in our party, any weakening of my authority at this moment, would have been fatal to that cause. That is why I am here, and I leave confidently the result in your hands, and I feel assured that before many months are gone by you will look back to the proceedings of this day and to your vote to-morrow with the satisfaction that results have proved that you have struck a great and successful blow for Ireland (loud cheers).</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell, on coming forward to speak, was received by the crowded audience with an extraordinary demonstration of enthusiasm, rivalling in warmth and spontaneity the most enthusiastic welcomes that Mr. Parnell has ever received. the entire audience stood up and, waving their hats, cheered loudly for some time.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell said he had never before heard Mr. Kelly lecture, and had seldom heard him speak. Mr. O'Kelly kept his talents unobtrusive in the background. He wished Mr. O'Kelly would come more to the front and would add to those deeds of courage which he had done in the field in Mexico, in Cuba, and in the Soudan those forensic triumphs which he was perfectly certain it would be in his power to gain to an enormous extent. He was glad that they were all united to-night (cheers), and that the symbol of their unity was signalised by the presence of Mr Lynch in the chair (cheers). As he had said before on several occasions in this town, he trusted before long to welcome Mr. Lynch as a valued colleague into the ranks of the Irish party to fight by his side, he hoped not for many years or many months, in the English House of Commons; and when they returned to Ireland to take part in that work of development of the resources of Ireland and the building up of the nation, which all so ardently longed to engage in, Mr. Lynch would be with them.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
