<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The Home Rule Debate, The Freeman's Journal, Tuesday 8 June 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The Home Rule Debate</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="315698503" level="j">The Freeman's Journal</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">5-6</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-06-08">8 June 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00053"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04"> 
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/BL/0000056/18860608/017/0006?browse=true"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, whose rising was received with prolonged Home Rule cheers, said - If I intervene in the contest of giants which has been proceeding so many days in this house in reference to this great question, it is not because I suppose that the intervention is specially suited to the moment, and I certainly should not under ordinary circumstances have felt any self-confidence whatever in following so able and eloquent a member of this house as the right hon gentleman the member for the Eastern Division of Edinburgh. But "thrice is he armed who hath his quarrel just" (loud Irish cheers), and even a man so inferior from every point of view as myself to the right hon gentleman may hope upon this occasion not to be so much behind as usual. Sir, without intending to offer any disrespect to the right hon. gentleman, I could not help thinking when listening to his speech that in all the lost causes which I have seen him attempt to defend (Home Rule and some Ministerial cheers) during many years past, he was never so little effective as when contending against the bill which we hope to see read a second time to-night (Home Rule cheers). Sir, the right hon gentleman has sought, I think very unfairly, to cast a lurid light upon the situation by an allusion to those unhappy outrages which have been occurring in Kerry (hear, hear, from the Home Rulers). I join the right hon gentleman in the expression of contempt for those cowardly and disgraceful practices (Home Rule cheers). I join him to the fullest extent. But, sir, neither do I say because evictions have been more numerous in Kerry than in all the rest of Munster added together (hear, hear from the Home Rulers) during months past, that that fact is an excuse for these outrages, or is any excuse whatever for such occurrences, although it might supply us with the cause for them. But when I denounce outrages, I denounce them, sir, in all parts of Ireland (Home Rule cheers), whether they occur in Ulster or in Kerry. The right hon gentleman himself is certainly free from reproach in respect of this matter. He has not joined the noble lord the member for South Paddington (Home Rule cheers), and the right hon gentleman the member for West Birmingham (loud Home Rule cheers) in the use of reckless language with reference to the affairs of a country which is not their country (renewed Home Rule cheers) - an interference for which they had not the paltry excuse that it was any business of theirs, or that they really felt any interest in it (hear, hear). My colleagues, some of them, have been reproached in times past, because they had not been very careful in looking into what might be the effect of their language. The doctrine of indirect responsibility has been employed against many of them to the extent of imprisonment (hear, hear). But if the doctrine of indirect responsibility had been employed against the noble lord the member for South Paddington and the right hon gentleman the member for West Birmingham, the former might have pleaded for an excuse that as he, believes in nobody and in nothing except himself (laughter), so he could not have expected any great importance to be attached to his declarations (hear, hear); while the right hon gentleman the member for West Birmingham might have said - and said very truly - that he was absolutely ignorant of all the circumstances of Ireland, his celebrated projected visit to that country last autumn not having come off (laughter), and that consequently he really did not know what would come of his language. However, sir, we have the result now in one murder which has already been committed in Belfast ("Hear, hear" from the Home Rulers), and I trust that in future right hon gentlemen will remember that the importance and the gravity of occurrences which may follow in Ulster - and these occurrences cannot go further at the outside than outrage and assassination - will depend very much upon what they say and upon the amount of importance that they give to the doings of Ulstermen in the minds of these people themselves (hear, hear). Certainly, sir, I do condemn these occurrences in Kerry , and the right hon gentleman very properly said they must be put a stop to. Well, so say we all (loud Home Rule cheers). The right hon gentleman wants to put a stop to them by resorting to the old methods of coercion which he and his friends have been using for the last eighty-six years, but we say with the Prime Minister, "try the effect of self-government" (Home Rule cheers), and if Kerrymen then resort to outrage they will very soon find that the rest of Ireland will soon put a stop to these outrages (Home Rule cheers). Before I leave the terrible occurrences in Belfast I wish to give an explanation, because, as usual, the English newspapers have for their own purposes misrepresented what took place. I was very much pained on reading that it was alleged the disturbance arose out of an expression used by a Catholic workman to a Protestant workman, that "in a short time none of his religious persuasion would be allowed to earn a crust of bread in Ireland." That does not represent the correct state of facts as they are reported in the local newspapers. What actually took place, according to these reports, was a Catholic overseer of the works found fault with the way in which another workman, an Orangeman, I think - at all events a Protestant, was executing the digging out of a drain, and he said to him "this is a nice way in which you are digging out this drain." The Orangeman said in reply to his overseer "what does a Papist know about digging drains?" (Laughter), and the overseer, irritated, I will not say justly, because it would be absurd to be irritated by such an expression, said in reply "you will never earn a crust at these works again," meaning he should dismiss him (hear, hear). "That is all right - that is all I want," replied the man, and he took up his shovel and left the works. I believe as he was leaving he was assaulted by one or more of the other workmen (some Opposition laughter). It is so difficult to know what is true with regard to any Irish matter (laughter). It is of great importance that the house should understand that this remark had no a general but had only an individual application (hear, hear). At the same time, I am not to be taken as justifying the occurrence on the part of those employed in the yard in the slightest degree. The right hon gentleman the member for East Edinburgh spoke about the sovereignty of Parliament. Upon this point I entirely accept and agree with the definitions given by the hon and learned gentleman the member for one of the divisions of Aberdeen (Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs). We have always perceived, since the introduction of this bill, the difference between a co-ordinate Parliament and a subordinate Parliament. We have recognised that the legislature which the right hon gentleman the Prime Minister proposes to constitute is a subordinate parliament (hear, hear) - that it is not like Grattan's Parliament, which was coequal (hear, hear, from Mr. Gladstone), arising out of the same constitution given to the Irish people by the Crown, just in the same way, though not by the same means, as Parliamentary institutions were given to Great Britain by the Sovereign. We understand this perfectly well, and we should undoubtedly have preferred - as I stated in speeches which have been quoted against me as showing that I could not accept this proposed settlement as final - I should have preferred the restitution of Grattan's Parliament. It would have been more in accordance with the sentiments of the Irish people, and sentiment goes a long way in dealing with a people like the Irish. But at the same time, in reference to the argument used against us that I am precluded from accepting this solution as final because I have claimed a restitution of Grattan's Parliament, I would say that I consider there are practical advantages in a statutory body limited and subordinate to this Imperial Parliament, as it undoubtedly would be, which will render it much more useful and advantageous to the Irish people than Grattan's Parliament would be, Grattan's Parliament had many disadvantages. In the first place it had a House of Lords (Home Rule and Radical cheers). We get rid of the House of Lords under the constitution of the right hon gentleman. It is true that in its place there is to be a "first order," a very salutary provision, although I do not agree with the extent of time the first order is allowed to hang up a bill or with some of the qualifications (hear, hear). These are subordinate matters (a laugh). But I say the "first order" is a very salutary provision which will tend to prevent rash legislation and immoderate action on the part of the new body, and I would rather see a bill hung up for ten years by a body such as the "first order" than hung up for twenty-hour hours by the superior Parliament (Home Rule cheers). I venture to express that opinion regarding the effect and the irritation which constant meddling and overseeing as suggested by the right hon gentleman the member for West Birmingham, on the part of this Imperial Parliament would have on the minds of the people of Ireland (hear, hear). It would be most mischievous and dangerous, and sure to prevent such a settlement. But when we are all assembled in one chamber different sections of Irishmen thrashing out a subject, those causes and those effects which have always come into operation under similar circumstances will be also produced in Ireland, and discussion may be relied upon to bring about the settlement of controverted points. Of course we, too, have controverted subjects. And the result of those two orders working together in the same chamber will be that great questions will be settled on the basis of compromise, and more or less to the satisfaction of both parties. We, therefore, understand perfectly well that this Parliament has the ultimate supremacy and sovereignty. I have spoken of the detail of the House of Lords in Grattan's Parliament; another very important matter in Grattan's Parliament was the defect alluded to by the right hon gentleman the member for East Edinburgh - that the Executive was divorced from the legislative body. Fox, I think, said there could be no perfect system of government in which the executive and legislative bodies are not joined together. I agree with that statement, and I think one of the most valuable parts of this bill is that by which the Prime Minister throws responsibility on the legislature to maintain that order in Ireland without which no society can exist (hear, hear). I understand the supremacy of the Imperial Parliament to mean this. It is effective, as has been pointed out, in the event of the Irish body exceeding its powers, but it might, under certain circumstances, be more effective. I can illustrate this by saying that in accepting this bill I think we come under an honourable obligation not to abuse our powers, and we pledge ourselves (some derisive Opposition cheers and Home Rule counter cheers) not to abuse those powers, and to devote our energies and any ability or influence we may have with our people to prevent them abusing those powers, but if this abuse should take place the Imperial Parliament is here in its full plenitude of power ready to intervene, but ready to intervene only in the case grave and urgent necessity (Home Rule and Ministerial cheers). Believe me this is far the best way you can deal with this question. You will have the power of force. Of course we know when abuses are committed and injustice is perpetrated force is the real power. But you will have also the power of this Imperial Parliament untouched and unimpaired just as if this bill had never been enacted. We recognise this, as I have said, and I say again. I said on the first reading, immediately after I heard the statement of the Prime Minister, and I say now, that I accept this bill as a final settlement of our National question, and I believe the Irish people will accept it (Home Rule cheers). Of course you may not believe my words in the connection have been signally justified by the result (Irish cheers). We have had this measure accepted in the sense I have indicated by the leaders of every section of National opinion in Ireland and also outside Ireland - in the United States of America, with the vengeance of the Irish population of which some speakers against this bill are so fond of threatening us (Irish laughter and cheers). We have not had a single syllable - a single voice - against this bill by any Irishman (Irish Tory cries of "Oh, oh") by any Irishman of Nationalist opinion. Of course there are sections amongst Irish Nationalists just as there are sections in the Great Conservative party (laughter), but so far as it was possible for a nation to accept a measure cheerfully, freely, gratefully, and without reserve, I say that the Irish people have shown that they accepted this measure (loud Home Rule cheers). Even the terrible Irish World [italics], which has not been on my side for the last five or six years, says:-</p>
         <p>The Irish race at home and abroad have signified their willingness to accept the terms proposed by Mr Gladstone (cheers). If a coercion bill be now passed by Parliament it will be equivalent to a declaration of war on the part of England.</p>
         <p>(Tory ironical cheers). We do not agree with Mr. Patrick Ford in his conclusion. During the last five or six years we thoroughly differ from him, and he has returned the compliment by using every opportunity to condemn us, so that the honours are pretty easy (cheers and laughter). But so far as the Irish people could accept this bill they have accepted it without any reserve whatever as one that will be a final settlement of this great question (Irish and Liberal cheers). Now, sir, I will leave the question of the sovereignty of Parliament, and I will go to another point which has been touched upon by the hon gentleman the member for Edinburgh (Mr. Goschen). He has fairly told us of his fears with regard to abuses on the part of the Irish priesthood in reference to the question of education. The right hon. gentleman certainly has not followed the example of other illustrious persons (laughter) by indulging in extravagant language on the Protestant and Catholic question (hear, hear, from the Irish members), and I am quite sure that his apprehension is genuine so far as it goes, by the does not desire to fan the flames of religious bigotry amongst us (hear, hear). He has spoken very fairly, and I wish to say that, perhaps, as a Protestant, if I had not abundant experience of the feeling in Ireland I might have shared these feelings myself. Certainly I have no such fears (cheers), but it is rather remarkable that this question of education is the only matter the right hon gentleman has any fears about in dealing with the question of Protestant and Catholic in Ireland. It is rather remarkable that when the right hon gentleman the member for Birmingham (Mr. Chamberlain) proposed to give us a central Council in Dublin he proposed that it should have exclusive control over education without any reservation whatever with regard to Ulster Protestants or anybody else (cheers). I believe in that scheme also there was to be a first and second order (hear, hear). Sir, it is very hard to please everybody (hear and laughter), and while we please the right hon member for West Birmingham in regard to accepting the education scheme which the Prime Minister proposes to establish, we regret that we are unfortunate enough to run foul of the right hon member for East Edinburgh (hear, hear). But I do assure the right hon gentleman that we shall settle this question of education very well amongst ourselves (Irish cheers), and there are very many liberal nationalists - I call them liberal nationalists because I take the phrase in reference to this question of education - there are many liberal Nationalists that do not share those views of the Roman Catholic Church on the question of the control of education, and who are very much influenced in their desire to see Ulster remain a part of the Irish legislative body, and sharing the responsible duties of governing Ireland by the feeling that they have with regard to this question of education; and I am sure that with Ulster in the Irish legislature, and with her representatives coming there as they are here, there would not be the slightest risk, if there was indeed any such idea, on the part of the Catholic hierarchy and priesthood to use their power unfairly against the Protestants (loud Irish and Liberal cheers). But, as I said, we shall be able to settle this and other questions together very satisfactorily, and to the satisfaction of everybody concerned (cheers). There is one thing further I wish to say - that as things are going on in this house in reference to the education question there is no doubt that denominational education would be established in Ireland in a very few years. That is a point that is already conceded even by the right hon member for Birmingham. That right hon gentleman agrees that denominational education is the right thing for Ireland, and I am sure that we might say that if Parliament remains as it is, and that if Ireland remains as it is, we should find denominational education established in Ireland in a very few years (hear, hear). The right hon gentleman the member for Edinburgh spoke of the linen trade, and I think he was rather unfair to my hon friend the member for the Stephen's green division of Dublin (Mr. Gray). I have not had time to look at the series of letters on the question to which he refers, but the part of the letters that he quoted to prove that the articles went to show that the linen trade was the curse of Ulster was one passage out of many letters intended to prove that the linen trade had been the curse of Ulster, not directly but indirectly, because it enabled the landlords to extract rack rents from tenants on which the landlords otherwise would not have insisted (hear, hear), and I don’t think that in his argument the right hon gentleman was fair in seeking to carry the matter further than that - indeed he did not attempt to carry it further. He observed a similar reticence on the financial question in regard to which he made so much on his speech on the first reading. Sir, the speech of the right hon gentleman on the occasion produced a very great sensation in the house and in the country. It was understood that the right hon gentleman intended to show, and I believe the country understood him so, to intend that first Ulster was wealthier than any of the other three provinces, and secondly that the burden of the taxation would fall on Ulster, and that without Ulster it would be impossible to carry on the government of Ireland. The hon gentleman did not pursue this financial question very far to-day (Irish cheers), but it is perhaps not improper that we should direct a little more attention to it since this question of the wealth of Ulster has been made a sort of war cry by the loyal and Patriotic Union (cheers). In his first speech the right hon gentleman was not very fair in selecting schedule "D" of the income tax, that relating to trades and professions, as his standard and measure of the relative wealth of the four provinces (laughter). A fairer standard of relative wealth would have been the assessment for income tax on all the schedules, and also the rateable values of the property in the four provinces, and this would show that so far from Ulster being the wealthiest it was the third in relative amount of wealth (cheers). These assessments show conclusively and the right hon gentleman will not now deny that they show that Ulster comes third in point of relative wealth - that she comes after Leinster, after Munster, and that she is only superior to unfortunate Connaught (cheers). The assessment of income tax per head in Leinster is £10 6s 2d, for Munster £6 0s 7d, for Ulster £5 14s 5d, and for Connaught £5 13s 7d. The figures as to the relative values are the only fair tests, and they are Leinster, 9.92; Munster 5.78; Ulster, 5.49, or only a little more than half of Leinster; and Connaught, 3.53. If you take any other fair tests, similar results will be arrived at, and you will find that instead of being the first with regard to wealth Ulster comes a long way third (hear, hear). The right hon gentleman argued that there was a great disparity between the Protestants of the north-eastern counties and the Catholics of the western counties in point of relative wealth, but the right hon gentleman showed that disparity to be a great deal larger than actually exists by the system which he chose, and, of course, he was perfectly entitled to choose his own system of calculating the relative wealth of the different counties. Of course to a considerable extent there is a disproportion of wealth between the north-eastern and the other counties in Ulster, but the same disproportion exists all through Ireland (hear, hear). The eastern counties all through Ireland are richer than the counties in the west. If you draw a meridian line down through the whole country you will find that on the eastern side of that line there is comparative prosperity, and on the western side considerable poverty (hear, hear). The reason of this is obvious. In the first place in the west the country is rocky and barren, and in the second place its special trade is with England, and consequently all the great distributing centres and shipping are in the east, and men of business and men of wealth collect together and live on the eastern seaboard, and it is only natural therefore that the eastern portions of the provinces are richer than the western portions (laughter). Now, sir, we come to the question of the protection of the "loyal minority." I have incidentally dealt with this question in regard to the matter of education, but I would ask your permission, sir, to say a few more words upon it, as great attention has been bestowed upon the question. One would think that the Protestants of Ireland were going to be handed over to the tender mercies of a lot of Thugs and bandits.</p>
         <p>Major Saunderson - Hear, hear.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - The hon and gallant member for North Armagh cheers that statement. I only wish that I was as safe going to the North of Ireland as the hon and gallant member would be going to the South (Irish and Liberal cheers). What do these gentlemen mean by "protection of the loyal minority?" In the first place I would ask these gentlemen what "loyal minority" they mean. The right hon hon [sic] gentleman the member for East Edinburgh does not seem yet to have made up his mind as to what "loyal minority" he means. When asked he said he meant the same loyal Ulster as was referred to by the Prime Minister. Well I have examined the Prime Minister's reference to Ulster, and I find that he referred to the whole province. He did not select the little bit of the province in the eastern corner, because the Opposition had not discovered that point at the time, and consequently I will assume that he refers to the whole province when he asked the house for special protection for Ulster. He has not, however, told us how he will protect them. Let us, therefore, take the plans of other gentlemen to supply the deficiency. It is very confusing dealing with these plans. In order to make even an outline of a plan, or a patchwork of a plan, you have to set together the propositions of several members (laughter). You have to take a little bit of a plan from one, and a little bit of a plan from another, and a little bit of a plan from a third, in order to make one coherent whole (loud laughter), and even in face of all these efforts, the results are very unsatisfactory (cheers and laughter). The right hon gentleman the member for Birmingham, and I suppose the right hon gentleman the member for Edinburgh when the proper time comes would do the same, claimed for Ulster a separate legislature. Well, sir, you would not protect the Protestant minority in Ireland, even supposing you gave a separate legislature to Ulster, because there are outside the province 400,000 Protestants (cheers), who would still be without that protection. Therefore by taking away Ulster from them you would make the position of these 400,000 Protestants infinitely less secure (cheers). How would you protect the Protestants of Ulster? (Irish cheers). The Protestants according to the last census were in the proportion of 52 to 48 of the Catholics (hear, hear). We have now every reason to that the Protestant and Catholics in Ulster are about equal in number (hear, hear). At all events, however that may be, the Nationalists have succeeded in returning the majority of the Ulster members (loud Irish cheers), and consequently we have the Nationalists in the majority in ulster (renewed cheers). The main reason, apart from the increase of the Catholic forces, for this I believe to be that a large proportion of Protestant Nationalists voted in the closely divided constituencies in favour of Ireland, and returned Nationalist members (cheers). So that you see you would still have Nationalists to deal with in Ulster even supposing you had an Ulster Legislature (hear, hear, and cheers), and the first thing an Ulster Legislature would do would be to unite herself with the Dublin Parliament and the rest of Ireland (loud Irish and Liberal cheers). But, sir, driven away from the fiction of Protestant Ulster and the great majority, it was only recently discovered that there did not exist this Protestant Ulster (cheers). The opponents of the bill upon this point have been compelled to take refuge in the north-east corner of Ulster, consisting of three counties (cheers). Well, sir, there again comes in the difficulty that instead of protecting the majority of the Protestants of Ireland by constituting a Legislature in the north-east corner of Ulster, you would abandon the majority of the Protestants of Ireland to their fate or [sic] a Dublin Parliament (loud Irish and Liberal cheers). Seven-twelfths of the Protestants of Ireland live outside these three northern counties, and only five-twelfths of the Protestants live inside these three counties, so that whatever way you put it you must give up this idea of protecting either a body or a majority of the Protestants of Ireland by the establishment of a separate Legislature either in Ulster or in portions of Ulster (cheers). No, sir, we can not give up a single Irishman (cheers) - we want the energy, the patriotism, the talent, and works of every Irishman (cheers) to make this great experiment - to ensure that this great experiment shall be successful (hear, hear). The best form of government for a country I believe to be one that requires that that government shall be the resultant of what forces are in that country (hear, hear). We cannot give away to a second Legislature for a section of Ireland any portion of the talent or influence of the Irish Protestants (cheers). This class - the Protestant class - will form the most valuable element in the Irish Legislature of the future, constituting as they will a strong minority, and exercising, through the "first order," a moderating influence upon the making of the laws. We have heard of the danger of a first trial of untrained legislators in an Irish Parliament. I regard their presence as vitally necessary to the success of this trial (hear, hear). We want, sir, all creeds and all classes in Ireland. We cannot look upon a single Irishman as not belonging to us (cheers). However much we recognise their ability, we cannot admit that there is a single one of them too good to take part in this experiment (cheers.) We do not blame the small proportion of Protestants who feel any real fear. I admit that there is a small proportion who do (hear, hear.) We have been doing our best of late to remove this fear, and we shall continue to do so (cheers.) When this bill becomes an act we shall not cease to try to conciliate such Irishmen (cheers.) No, sir, there is no shame or disgrace in this fear - that shame and disgrace belong to right honourable gentlemen and noble lords belonging to English political parties, who, for selfish interests of those political parties, try to stir up the almost expired embers of religious bigotry (loud Irish and Liberal cheers). Ireland has never injured the right hon gentleman, the member for West Birmingham, and I do not know why he laid the strength of his powerful arm against her - why, like another Brennus - although, I hope, not with the same result - he has thrown his sword into the scale against Ireland? I do not think that either politically, or otherwise, she has attempted to injure him, and yet he and his kind seek to dash down this first cup of cold water that has been offered to our nation since the recall of Lord Fitzwilliam, as was said in those days, at the point of the dagger (hear, hear). This settlement, sir, I believe, will be a final settlement (hear, hear). I have been reproached - and it has been made an argument against the honesty of my declaration regarding the final character of the settlement - that in a speech at Wicklow I proclaimed a right to protect Irish manufactures. This bill gives no such right. Undoubtedly I did claim that right; but it was not when the Liberal Party was in power (laughter and cheers). That speech about protection at Wicklow was made at a time when we had every reason to know that the Conservative party, if they should be successful at the polls, would have offered to Ireland a statutory Legislature with the right to protect her own affairs (loud Irish and Ministerial cheers, in which Mr. Gladstone warmly joined), and that this would have been coupled with a settlement of the Irish land question upon a process of purchase on a larger scale than that now proposed by the Prime Minister (prolonged Irish and Ministerial cheers). I should never have thought, I never did think, and I do not think now, of claiming a right of protection from the Liberal party (cheers). I never expected it (Liberal cheers). Therefore I recognise this settlement as final - a settlement without protection. There is another argument stronger still. The Prime Minister has shown us when he introduced this bill that without fiscal unity we should lose £1,400,000 a-year. That will still go to us in consequence of this unity and the absence of protection, and it is a very good quid pro quo [italics] for the loss of protection (hear, hear). The question of the retention of the Irish members is one which I will only touch upon very slightly. I may say with regard to this matter that I have always kept my mind thoroughly open upon it (hear, hear). It is not a vital question. I have seen difficulties in it, and difficulties that are rather from your point of view than from ours (Irish cheers). I think that when considered in committee it will present a difficulty which will be a growing one for Liberal members (hear, hear). I do not desire to prejudge this question. I admit a desire and a strong sentiment in the matter. When, however, I consider how many times my colleagues and myself have been forcibly ejected (laughter), and how often the necessity of suspending, and if not entirely abrogating the representation of Ireland in this house has been eagerly canvassed by the London press as the necessary solution of the question, perhaps, sir, I may not consider under the present circumstances that this desire on the part of the Liberal members is a very reasonable one. I acknowledge, however, that it is an honest one. When the Prime Minister introduces his plan we can examine it. It will require a little time for consideration. When the Prime Minister has produced his plan, without binding myself beforehand, I shall candidly examine it with the desire to see in it elements which shall not endanger its final acceptance (hear, hear). I shall deal with the proposals from that point of view. To the permanency of the settlement and the success of it my colleagues and I have pledged our political future (cheers). But I confess, sir, that if I had regard to the spirit with which the right hon gentleman the member for West Birmingham has dealt with this question, I should have been hopelessly alienated from the plan. He has dealt with it in order to cast upon us an apparent stigma of inferiority in order he may have an excuse for constant meddling in our affairs, checking and thwarting us keeping us, under his thumb (hear, hear). That is not a state of things which the Irish people will submit to (cheers). We should not agree to his claims in this respect - they would be fatal to the durability of the settlement. Now, sir, what does it all come to? It comes to two alternatives when everything has been said and done - the alternatives of coercion, which Lord Salisbury has put before the country (no, no, from the Tories, and loud Irish and Ministerial cheers), and the alternative offered by the Prime Minister as a solution, carrying with it a lasting settlement and a treaty of peace (loud cheers). If you reject this bill, Lord Salisbury was right in what he said as to coercion (no, no), and with respect to the cries of "no" by hon gentlemen, I beg to say that you will have to resort to coercion (hear, hear). That is not a threat on my part. I would do much to prevent the necessity of a resort to coercion, but I see that it will be inevitable. The best intentioned Radical sitting on these benches, and who thinks that he never will be a party to coercion in Ireland, will be seen walking into the coercion lobby for drastic coercion, or, at the very outside, pitifully abstaining. We have gone through it all before, and know the sort of Ireland that there has been for the past five years. We know that they have had coercion during those five years of a very severe and stringent character, and it will require severer and more drastic coercion now. You will require everything you have had during these five years - I do not say it to inflame passion or awaken bitter memories - you have had during these five years suspension of the Habeas Corpus Act, you have had one thousand of your fellow-subjects held in prison without specific charge, many of them for a long period of time, and some of them for very many months without trial, without your placing them on trial, and I think of all these thousand persons arrested under the coercion of the late Mr. Forster scarcely one dozen were put on their trial for any offence (hear, hear). You have had an Arms Act, you have had the suspension of trial by jury. During these last five years you have authorised your police to enter the domiciles of your fellow-subjects in Ireland at any hour of the day or night, and to search every part of these domiciles - even the beds of the women - without warrant. You have fined the innocent for offences committed by the guilty; you have taken power to expel aliens from the country; you have revived the Curfew law and the blood-money of the Norman conquerors; you have gagged the Press, suppressed newspapers, manufactured new crimes and offences, and imposed fresh penalties. All this you have done, and much more, in the past five years - all this, and more, you will have to do again. The provision in the bill for terminating the representation of the Irish members has been very vehemently objected to, and the right hon gentleman the member for the Border Burghs has said there is no half-way house between separation and the maintenance of law and order in Ireland by the Imperial authority. Well, sir, I say with just as much belief and just as much experience as the right hon gentleman, that in my judgment there is no half-way house between the concession of legislative autonomy to Ireland and the disenfranchisement of the country and her government as a Crown colony (Irish cheers). But, sir, I refuse to believe that those evil days must come. I am convinced that there are sufficient number of wise and just men in this house to cause it to disregard the appeals made to passion and to pocket, and to choose the better way of the Prime Minister - a way of peace and good-will amongst nations - and that when the numbers in the division lobby have been told tonight it will also be told, for the admiration of all future generations, that England and her Parliament in this nineteenth-century was wise enough, brave enough, and generous enough to end this strife of centuries and give peace, prosperity, and happiness to suffering Ireland (loud and prolonged Irish and Liberal cheers.)</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
