<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Second Reading. [Adjourned Debate.], Hansard's Parliamentary Debates, Monday 7 June 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Second Reading. [Adjourned Debate.]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="81159818807513812830" level="m">Hansard's Parliamentary Debates</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-06-07">7 June 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00053"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>hansard report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">  
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/commons/1886/jun/07/second-reading-adjourned-debate#S3V0306P0_18860607_HOC_133"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>If, Mr. Speaker, I intervene in the contest of giants which has been proceeding for so many days in this House in reference to this great question, it is not because I suppose that that intervention is specially suitable to the moment; and I certainly should not, under ordinary circumstances, have felt any self-confidence whatever in following so able and eloquent a Member of this House as the right hon. Gentleman the Member for the Eastern Division of Edinburgh. But "Thrice is he armed who hath his quarrel just;" and even a man so inferior from every point of view to the right hon. Gentleman as I am may hope upon this occasion not to be so much behind him as usual. Sir, without intending to offer any disrespect to the right hon. Gentleman, I must say that I could not help thinking, when listening to his speech, that in all the lost causes which I have seen him attempting to defend during many years past he was never so little effective as when contending against the Bill which we hope to see read a second time to-night. The right hon. Gentleman has sought—I think very unfairly—to cast a lurid light upon the situation by an allusion to those unhappy outrages which have occurred in Kerry. I join the right hon. Gentleman in expressing my contempt for these cowardly and disgraceful practices. I join him in that respect to the fullest extent. Neither do I say that because for months past evictions have been more numerous in Kerry than in all the rest of Munster taken together—neither do I say that that constitutes any excuse for these outrages, although it may supply us with a reason for them; but when I denounce outrages I denounce them in all parts of Ireland, whether they occur in Ulster or in Kerry. The right hon. Gentleman himself is certainly free from reproach in this matter. He has not joined the noble Lord the Member for South Paddington (Lord Randolph Churchill) and the right hon. Gentleman the Member for West Birmingham (Mr. J. Chamberlain) in the use of reckless language with reference to the affairs of a country which is not their country, for the use of which language they had not even the paltry excuse that the subject was any business of theirs, or that they really feel any interest in it. My Colleagues have been reproached, some of them, in times past because they have not been very careful to look into what might be the effect of their language, and the doctrine of indirect responsibility has been employed against many of them to the length of imprisonment. But if the doctrine of indirect responsibility had been employed against the noble Lord and the right hon. Gentleman the Member for West Birmingham, the former of them might, perhaps, have pleaded as an excuse that as he himself believes in nothing and in nobody except himself, so he could not expect any great importance to be attached to his declarations; while the right hon. Gentleman the Member for West Birmingham might have said, and very truly, that he was absolutely ignorant of all the circumstances of Ireland, his celebrated projected visit to that country last autumn not having come off, and that consequently he really did not know what would be the probable result of his language. However, Sir, we have the result now in one murder which has already been committed in Belfast. I trust that in future right hon. Gentlemen will remember that the importance and gravity of the occurrences which may follow in Ulster—and these occurrences cannot well go further than outrage and assassination—will depend very much upon what they say and upon the meaning which their words may convey to the minds of Ulster men. But certainly I do condemn these outrages in Kerry; and the right hon. Gentleman says very rightly that they must be put a stop to. Well, so say we all; but the right hon. Gentleman would try to put a stop to them by resorting to the old bad method of coercion, which he and his Friends have been using for the last 86 years, while we say with the Prime Minister—"Try the effect of self-government;" and if Kerry men then resort to outrages they will very soon find that the rest of Ireland will put a stop to them. With reference to the terrible occurrence in Belfast, I wish to give an explanation, because, as usual, the English newspapers have perverted for their own purposes what actually took place. I was very much pained at reading that it was alleged that the disturbance arose out of an expression addressed by a Catholic workman to a Protestant fellow-workman, to the effect that in a short time none of his religious persuasion would be allowed to earn a crust of bread in Ireland. Now, that does not represent the circumstances of the occurrence as they are reported in the local newspapers. What really took place was this. The Catholic overseer of the works found fault with the way in which an Orangeman—I think he was an Orange workman; at all events, he was a Protestant workman—was executing the digging out of a drain. The overseer said to the workman—"That is a nice way to dig this drain," and the Orangeman replied—the overseer happened to be a Catholic—"What does a Papist know about digging drains?" The overseer being irritated—I will not say justly irritated, because it was absurd of him to be irritated by such a remark—said, in reply, "You will never earn a crust in these works again," meaning that the workman would be dismissed. "That is all right; that is all I want," said the Orangeman, and he took up his shovel and left the works, and I believe that while leaving he was assaulted by one or more of the Catholic workmen. It is necessary to point out—so difficult is it to know here what is true with regard to any Irish matter—it is very important that the House should understand that the overseer's remark had not a general but an individual application. At the same time, I am not to be taken as justifying in the slightest degree the conduct of the Catholics employed in the yard. Now, Sir, the right hon. Member for East Edinburgh (Mr. Goschen) spoke about the sovereignty of Parliament. I entirely agree upon this point. I entirely accept the definitions given by the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Bryce) the other day. We have always known since the introduction of this Bill the difference between a co-ordinate and a subordinate Parliament,, and we have recognized that the Legislature which the Prime Minister proposes to constitute is a subordinate Parliament—that it is not the same as Grattan's Parliament, which was coequal with the Imperial Parliament, arising out of the same Constitution given to the Irish people by the Crown, just in the same way, though not by the same means, as Parliamentary Institutions were given to Great Britain by the Sovereign. We understand this perfectly well. Undoubtedly I should have preferred—as I stated in speeches which have been quoted against me as showing that I could not accept this proposed settlement as final—I should have preferred the restitution of Grattan's Parliament; it would have been more in accordance with the sentiments of the Irish people, whose sentiments in such matters it is most important to regard. But with reference to the argument that has been used against us, that I am precluded from accepting this solution as a final solution because I have claimed the restitution of Grattan's Parliament, I would beg to say that I consider there are practical advantages connected with the proposed statutory Body, limited and subordinate to this Imperial Parliament as it undoubtedly will be, which will render it much more useful and advantageous to the Irish people than was Grattan's Parliament, and that the Statutory Body which the right hon. Gentleman proposes to constitute is much more likely to be a final settlement than Grattan's Parliament. That Parliament had many disadvantages. In the first place it had a House of Lords. Well, we get rid of the House of Lords by the Constitution of the right hon. Gentleman. It is true that in its place is put the First Order; a very salutary provision, although I do not agree entirely as to the extent of time for which the First Order is allowed to hang up a Bill, or as to some of the qualifications for it. But these are subordinate matters. I say, then, that the First Order is a very salutary provision, one that will tend to prevent rash legislation and intemperate action; and as to the power of the First Order to hang up a Bill, I would rather see a measure hung up for 10 years by such a Body than hung up for only 24 hours by this Imperial Parliament. I venture to express that opinion, having regard to the irritation which such constant action by the Imperial Parliament, such constant meddling and overthrowing on the part of this Imperial Parliament, as is suggested by the right hon. Member for West Birmingham, would have on the minds of the people of Ireland. That would be most mischievous and dangerous, and sure to prevent the settlement being regarded as final. But when we are all assembled together in one Chamber, different sections of Irishmen threshing out different subjects, those causes and effects which have always come into operation in similar circumstances will be reproduced in Ireland also, and discussion will be relied upon for bringing about a settlement of disputed questions, which we, of course, have, like other people, and the result of these two Orders working together will be that those questions will be decided on a basis of compromise more or less satisfactory to both parties. We feel, therefore, that under this Bill this Imperial Parliament will have the ultimate supremacy and the ultimate sovereignty. I have already said that under this Bill the House of Lords of Grattan's Parliament will not be revived; but there is another great difference between Grattan's Parliament and the Legislature to be established by this Bill—namely, that in Grattan's Parliament the Executive was divorced from the Legislative Body, whereas the two Bodies will be united under this Bill. I think it was Fox who said that there could be no perfect system of government in which the Executive and the Legislative Bodies were not joined together. In that observation I quite agree, and I think that the most useful part of the Bill is that in which the Prime Minister throws the responsibility upon the new Legislature of maintaining that order in Ireland without which no State and no society can exist. I understand the supremacy of the Imperial Parliament to be this—that they can interfere in the event of the powers which are conferred by this Bill being abused under certain circumstances. But the Nationalists in accepting this Bill go, as I think, under an honourable understanding not to abuse those powers; and we pledge ourselves in that respect for the Irish people, as far as we can pledge ourselves, not to abuse those powers, and to devote our energies and our influence which we may have with the Irish people to prevent those powers from being abused. But, if those powers should be abused, the Imperial Parliament will have at its command the force which it reserves to itself, and it will be ready to intervene, but only in the case of grave necessity arising. I believe that this is by far the best mode in which we can hope to settle this question. You will have the real power of force in your hands, and you ought to have it and if abuses are committed and injustice be perpetrated you will always be able to use that force to put a stop to them. You will have the power and the supremacy of Parliament untouched and unimpaired, just as though this Bill had never been brought forward. We fully recognize this to be the effect of the Bill. I now repeat what I have already said on the first reading of the measure, immediately after I heard the statement of the Prime Minister that we look upon the provisions of the Bill as a final settlement of this question, and that I believe that the Irish people have accepted it as such a settlement. [Cheers and ironical cheers.] Of course you may not believe me, but I can say no more. I think my words upon that occasion have been singularly justified by the result. We have had this measure accepted in the sense I have indicated by all the leaders of every section of National opinion both in Ireland and outside Ireland. It has been so accepted in the United States of America, and by he Irish population in that country with whose vengeance some hon. Members are so fond of threatening us. Not a single dissentient voice has been raised against this Bill by any Irishman—not by any Irishman holding National opinions—and I need scarcely remind the House that there are sections among Irish Nationalists just as much as there are even among the great Conservative Party. I say that as far as it is possible for a nation to accept a measure cheerfully, freely, gladly, and without reservation as a final settlement, I say that the Irish people have shown that they have accepted this measure in that sense. Even the terrible Irish World, which has not been upon my side for the last five or six years, says— The Irish race at home and abroad have signified a willingness to accept the terms of peace offered by Mr. Gladstone. And it goes on to say that— If a Coercion Bill were now passed by Parliament, it will be equivalent to a declaration of war on the part of England. I need scarcely say that we have not agreed with Mr. Patrick Ford during the last five or six years. We strongly condemn his proposals, and he returns the compliment by not agreeing with us, so that the honours are pretty easy; but I take his testimony upon this point—that as far as the Irish people at home and in America can accept this Bill they have done so without any reservation Whatever in a final sense. I will now leave this question of the supremacy of the Imperial Parliament, and I will turn to one that was strongly dwelt upon by the right hon. Gentleman the Member for East Edinburgh—I mean the influence which he fears the Irish priesthood will seek to exercise upon the future education of the Irish people. The right hon. Gentleman certainly has not followed the example of other illustrious persons by indulging in extravagant language on the Protestant and Catholic question, and I may say at once that I am quite sure that the right hon. Gentleman's apprehensions upon this subject are genuine, so far as they go, and that at the same time he has no desire to fan the flame of religious discord. On the whole, I think that the right hon. Gentleman has spoken very fairly in reference to this part of the question; and I will not say that, perhaps as a Protestant had I not had,  as I have had, abundant experience of Ireland, I might not have been inclined to share his fears myself. Certainly, I have no such fears; but it is rather remarkable that this question of education is the only matter the right hon. Gentleman has any fears about in dealing with the question of Protestant and Catholic in Ireland. There is, however, a further remarkable fact that in reference to this branch of the question the right hon. Gentleman the Member for West Birmingham has actually proposed to give the entire control of Irish education to a Central Council sitting in Dublin, without any reservation whatever as regards Ulster or the Irish Protestant population. I believe in that scheme, also, there was to be a First and Second Order. Sir, it is very hard to please everybody, and while we please the right hon. Member for West Birmingham by agreeing to give the control of Irish education to a Legislative Body which will include the Representatives of the Protestants of Ulster, we find that we are unfortunately running foul of the right hon. Member for East Edinburgh. I can, however, assure the latter right hon. Gentleman that we Irishmen shall be able to settle this question of Irish education very well among ourselves. There are many Liberal Nationalists in Ireland—I call them Liberal Nationalists, because I take the phrase in reference to this question of education—there are many Liberal Nationalists who do not altogether share the views of the Roman Catholic Church upon the subject of education, and they are anxious that Ulster should remain an integral part of Ireland in order that they may share the responsibility of Government and may influence that Government by the feelings which they have with regard to this question of education. You may depend upon it that in an Irish Legislature Ulster, with such Representatives as she now has in the Imperial Parliament, would be able to successfully resist the realization of any idea which the Roman Catholic hierarchy might entertain with regard to obtaining an undue control of Irish education. But I repeat that we shall be able to settle this question and others very satisfactorily to all the parties concerned among ourselves. I may, however, remind the House that things are going on in this House with reference o denominational education which would undoubtedly result in denominational education being conceded to Ireland within a very few years without any effective control over it being given to the Ulster Protestants. Mention has been made by the right hon. Gentleman the Member for East Edinburgh (Mr. Goschen) of the linen trade of Ireland, and some correspondence on the subject has been read. I think, however, the right hon. Gentleman was rather unfair to my hon. Friend the Member for Dublin (Mr. Gray). I have not had the advantage of reading the correspondence; but the part of it which the right Gentleman quoted to prove that the linen trade was the curse of Ulster was one passage out of many letters intended to prove that the linen trade of Ireland had been a curse to Ulster, as it had been the means, not perhaps directly, but indirectly, of enabling the peasantry to pay the rack rents of the landlords, who otherwise could not have obtained them. I do not think that the right hon. Gentleman was fair in seeking to carry the matter further than that; indeed, there did not appear to be an inclination on the part of the right hon. Gentleman to carry it very far. I observe that there had been a similar reticence exercised with regard to the financial question, of which such a point was made upon the first reading of the Bill. The speech of the right hon. Gentleman upon the first reading of the Bill undoubtedly produced a great sensation in the House and in this country. The right hon. Gentleman, as I and others, and as I believe the country, understood him, argued on that occasion that Ulster was wealthier than either of the three other Provinces, and that consequently the burden of taxation would chiefly fall upon her, and that without Ulster, therefore, it would be impossible to carry on the Government of Ireland. The right hon. Gentleman did not press the financial question very far to-day; but it would not be improper, perhaps, if we were to direct a little more of our attention to it. For instance, the great wealth of Ulster has been taken up as the war cry of the Loyal and Patriotic Union. The right hon. Gentleman was not very fair in choosing the Income Tax, Schedule D, referring to trade and professions, as his standard and measure of the relative wealth of the four Provinces. The fair measure of their relative wealth is their assessment to the Income Tax under all the different Schedules, and also the value of the rateable property in Ireland; and these tests show conclusively that, so far from Ulster being the wealthiest of the four Provinces—and the right hon. Gentleman does not deny it now—Ulster comes third in point of relative wealth per head of the population. She comes after Leinster and Munster, and she is only superior to impoverished Connaught. The Income Tax for Leinster shows £10 6s. 9d. per head; Munster, £60s. 7d. per head; Ulster, £5 14s. 9d. per head; and Connaught, £3 13s. 7d. per head. These figures will give the relative wealth of the four Provinces as ascertained by these, the only fair tests, as 9.92 for Leinster, 5.78 for Munster, 5.49 for Ulster—or little more than half the relative wealth of Leinster—and 3.52 for Connaught. And if you take any other fair test the same results will be arrived at, and you will find that Ulster, instead of being first on the list as regards wealth per head, conies along way third. But the right hon. Gentleman also argued that there was a great disparity between the north-eastern or Protestant counties of Ulster and the Catholic counties in point of relative wealth. He chose not the fairest test, but the test that showed the best results for his argument, and he represented the disparity as a great deal larger than that which actually exists. But undoubtedly, to a considerable extent, there is this disproportion between the relative wealth of the north-eastern counties of Ulster and the other counties of the Province. But that same disproportion exists all through Ireland. The eastern counties are universally the richer counties all over Ireland. If you draw a meridian line down through the centre of the country you will find to the east of that line comparative prosperity and to the west of it considerable poverty. The reason of this is obvious. In the first place, the country becomes rocky and barren as you go west; and, in the second place, its chief trade is with England; and consequently the great distributing centres, the shipping ports and other places where men of business and wealth congregate and find their living, exist on the eastern sea-board. And it is only natural, not only as regards Ulster, but Munster and Leinster, that the eastern portions of the Province are richer than the rest. I come next to the question of the protection of the minority. I have incidentally dwelt on this point in respect to the matter of education; but I should like, with the permission of the House, to say a few words more about it, because it is one on which great attention has been bestowed. One would think from what we hear that the Protestants of Ireland were going to be handed over to the tender mercies of a set of Thugs and bandits. ["Hear, hear!"] The hon. and gallant Member for North Armagh (Major Saunderson) cheers that. I only wish that I was as safe in the North of Ireland when I go there as the hon. and gallant Member would be in the South. What do hon. Gentlemen mean by the protection of the loyal minority? In the first place, I ask them what they mean by the loyal minority. The right hon. Member for East Edinburgh (Mr. Goschen) does not seem to have made up his mind, even at this late stage of the discussion, as to what loyal Ulster he means. When asked the question, he said he meant the same loyal Ulster as was referred to by the Prime Minister in his speech; but he would not commit himself by telling us what signification he attributed to the Prime Minister's expression. Well, I have examined the Prime Minister's reference since then, and I find that he referred to the whole Province of Ulster. He did not select a little bit of the Province, because the Opposition had not discovered this point at that time; and consequently I suppose I may assume that the right hon. Member for East Edinburgh also referred to the whole Province of Ulster when he asked for special protection for it. He has not, however, told us how he would specially protect it. But we may go to other sources to supply that deficiency. It is one of the features of this debate that in order to make up the patchwork of a plan you have to go round to the Opposition speakers and select a bit from one and a bit from another and a bit from a third to frame something like a programme in opposition to the proposal of the Prime Minister, and even then the results are very unsatisfactory. But the right hon. Member for West Birmingham (Mr. Chamberlain) has claimed for Ulster—and I suppose that the 1179right hon. Member for East Edinburgh, when the proper time comes, will support him in that claim—a separate Legislature for the Province of Ulster. Well, Sir, you would not protect the loyal minority of Ireland even supposing that you gave a separate Legislature to the Province of Ulster, because there are outside the Province of Ulster over 400,000 Protestants who would still be without any protection so far as you propose to give them protection. You would make the position of these 400,000 Protestants, by taking away Ulster from them, infinitely less secure. But you would not even protect the Protestants in Ulster, because the Protestants, according to the last Census, were in the proportion of 52 to 48 Catholics; and we have every reason to believe that now the Protestants and Catholics in Ulster are about equal in number. At all events, however that may be, the Nationalists have succeeded in returning the majority of the Ulster Members, and consequently we have the Nationalists in a majority in Ulster. The main reason of the balance of forces I believe to be that a large proportion of the Protestant Nationalists voted in the closely divided constituencies of Ulster in favour of my hon. Colleagues. So that you would have the Nationalist will to deal with in Ulster, even if Ulster had a separate Legislature; and the very first thing that the Ulster Legislature would do would be to unite itself with the Dublin Parliament. Well, being driven away from the fiction of Protestant Ulster and the great majority of Protestants which until recently was alleged to exist in Ulster, the opponents of this Bill have been compelled to seek refuge in the north-east corner of Ulster, consisting of three counties. Here, again, comes in the difficulty that, instead of protecting the majority of the Protestants of Ireland by constituting a Legislature for the north-east corner of Ulster, you would abandon the majority of the Protestants of Ireland to their fate under a Dublin Parliament. Seven-twelfths of the Protestants of Ireland live outside these three counties in the north-east corner of Ulster, and the other five twelfths of the Protestants of Ireland live inside those counties. So that, whichever way you put it, you must give up the idea of protecting the Protestants either as a body or as a majority by the establishment of a separate Legislature, either in Ulster or in any portion of Ulster. No, Sir; we cannot give up a single Irishman. We want the energy, the patriotism, the talents, and the work of every Irishman to insure that this great experiment shall be a successful one. The best system of Government for a country I believe to be one which requires that that Government should be the resultant of all the forces within that country. We cannot give away to a second Legislature the talents and influence of any portion or section of the Irish people. The class of Protestants will form a most valuable element in the Irish Legislature of the future, constituting as they will a strong minority, and exercising through the First Order a moderating influence in making the laws. We have heard of the danger that will result from an untried and unpractised Legislature being established in Ireland. Now I regard variety as vitally necessary for the success of this trial. We want, Sir, all creeds and all classes in Ireland. We cannot consent to look upon a single Irishman as not belonging to us. And, however much we recognize the great abilities and the industry of the Irish Protestants—and we recognize them freely and fully—we cannot admit that there is a single one of them too good to take part in the Dublin Parliament. We do not blame the small proportion of the Protestants of Ireland who feel any real fear. I admit, Sir, that there is a small proportion of them who do feel this fear. We do not blame them; we have been doing our best to allay that fear, and we shall continue to do so. And finally, when this Bill becomes an Act, we shall not cease from the work of conciliating the fears of this small section of Irishmen. No, Sir. Theirs is not the shame and disgrace of this fear. That shame and disgrace belong to right hon. Gentlemen and noble Lords of English political Parties who, for selfish interests, have sought to rekindle the embers—the almost expiring embers—of religious bigotry. Ireland has never injured the right hon. Gentleman the Member for West Birmingham. I do not know why he should have added the strength of his powerful arm—why he should, like another Brennus—let us hope not with the same result—why he should have thrown his sword into the scale against Ireland. I am not aware that we have either personally or politically attempted to injure the right hon. Gentleman, yet he and his kind seek to dash this cup from the lips of the Irish people—the first cup of cold water that has been offered to our nation since the recall of Lord Fitzwilliam. This settlement, Sir, I believe will be a final settlement. I have been reproached—and it has been made an argument against the honesty of my declaration as to the final character of the settlement—that in a speech at Wicklow I claimed the right of protecting the Irish manufactures, and it is said that this Bill gives no such right. Well, undoubtedly I claimed that right. But it was not when a Liberal Government was in power. That speech about Protection at Wicklow was made at a time when we had every reason to know that the Conservative Party, if they should be successful at the polls, would have offered Ireland a Statutory Legislature with a right to protect her own industries, and that this would have been coupled with the settlement of the Irish Land Question on the basis of purchase on a larger scale than that now proposed by the Prime Minister. I never should have thought, I never did think, and I do not think now, of claiming Protection from the Liberal Party—I never expected it, and, therefore, I recognize the settlement as final without Protection. There is another and a stronger argument as well. In introducing this Bill the Prime Minister showed that unless we have fiscal unity there will be a loss of £1,400,000. I think, therefore, that, as a consequence of fiscal unity, £1,400,000 is a good quid pro quo for the loss of protection. The question of the retention of the Irish Members I shall only touch upon very slightly. I have always desired to keep my mind thoroughly open upon it, and not to make it a vital question. There are difficulties; but they are rather more from the English than the Irish point of view, and I think that when we come to consider the question in Committee that feeling will be a growing one on the part of Liberal Members. I admit the existence of a strong sentiment in favour of our retention—I will not say it is a reasonable sentiment, when I consider how many times my Colleagues and I have been forcibly ejected from this House, how often the necessity of suspending, if not entirely abrogating, representation on the part of Ireland has been eagerly canvassed by the London Press as the only necessary solution of it—perhaps I may not, under these circumstances, consider the desire on the part of Liberal Members as a very reasonable one. I admit that it is an honest one. All I can say is that when the Prime Minister has produced his plan—and I admit that it is a difficult question, and will require some little time for consideration—when the Prime Minister has produced his plan, without binding myself beforehand, I shall candidly examine it, with a desire not to see in it an element that will injure the permanency of the settlement. I shall chiefly deal with it with a view of seeing whether it will diminish the permanency of the settlement to the success of which my Colleagues and I have pledged our political future. But I confess, Sir, that if I had regard to the spirit with which the right hon. Gentleman the Member for West Birmingham has dealt with this question, I should have been hopelessly alienated from the plan of retaining the Irish Members. He has dealt with it in a way to attach an apparent stigma of inferiority to us, and in order that he may have the excuse for constantly meddling in our affairs, checking us, thwarting us, and keeping us under his thumb. The Irish people will never submit to that. We could not agree to his scheme, for that would be fatal to the finality and durability of the scheme. Now, Sir, what does it all come to? It comes to two alternatives when everything has been said and everything has been done. One alternative is the coercion which Lord Salisbury put before the country, and the other is the alternative offered by the Prime Minister, carrying with it the lasting settlement of a treaty of peace. If you reject this Bill, Lord Salisbury was quite right in what he said as to coercion. ["No, no!"] With great respect to the cries of "No!" by hon. Members above the Gangway, I beg to say you will have to resort to coercion. That is not a threat on my part—I would do much to prevent the necessity for resorting to coercion; but I say it will be inevitable, and the best-intentioned Radical who sits on those Benches, and who thinks that he "never, never will be a party to coercion," will be found very soon walking into the Division Lobby in favour of the strongest and most drastic Coercion Bill, or, at the very outside, pitifully abstaining. We have gone through it all before. During the last five years I know, Sir, there have been very severe and drastic Coercion Bills; but it will require an even severer and more drastic measure of coercion now. You will require all that you have had during the last five years, and more besides. What, Sir, has that coercion been? You have had, Sir, during those five years—I do not say this to inflame passion or awaken bitter memories—you have had during those five years the suspension of the Habeas Corpus Act; you have had a thousand of your Irish fellow-subjects held in prison without specific charge, many of them for long periods of time, some of them for 20 months, without trial and without any intention of placing them on trial—I think of all these thousand persons arrested under the Coercion Act of the late Mr. Forster scarcely a dozen were put on their trial; you have had the Arms Acts; you have had the suspension of trial by jury—all during the last five years. You have authorized jour police to enter the domicile of a citizen, of your fellow-subject in Ireland, at any hour of the day or night, and to search every part of this domicile, even the beds of the women, without warrant. You have fined the innocent for offences committed by the guilty; you have taken power to expel aliens from this country; you have revived the Curfew Law and the blood-money of your Norman conquerors; you have gagged the Press and seized and suppressed newspapers; you have manufactured now crimes and offences, and applied fresh penalties unknown to your laws for these crimes and offences. All this you have done for five years, and all this and much more you will have to do again. The provision in the Bill for terminating the representation of Irish Members has been very vehemently objected to, and the right hon. Gentleman the Member for the Border Burghs (Mr. Trevelyan) has said that there is no half-way house between separation and the maintenance of law and order in Ireland by Imperial authority. I say, with just as much sincerity of belief, and just as much experience as the right hon. Gentleman, that, in my judgment, there is no half-way house between the concession of legislative autonomy to Ireland and the disfranchisement of the country and her government as a Crown Colony. But, Sir, I refuse to believe that these evil days must come. I am convinced there are a sufficient number of wise and just Members in this House to cause it to disregard appeals made to passion and to pocket, and to choose the better way of the Prime Minister—the way of founding peace and goodwill among nations; and when the numbers in the Division Lobby come to be told, it will also be told, for the admiration of all future generations, that England and her Parliament, in this nineteenth century, was wise enough, brave enough, and generous enough to close the strife of centuries, and to give peace, prosperity, and happiness to suffering Ireland.</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
