<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Parnell Welcomed, Fall River Daily Herald, Thursday 15 January 1880</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Parnell Welcomed</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="" level="j">Fall River Daily Herald</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1880-01-15">15 January 1880</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7014164">Fall River, United States</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00086"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">  
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="18800115 Fall River Daily Herald Parnell Welcomed 002.tiff, 18800115 Fall River Daily Herald Parnell Welcomed 003.tiff, 18800115 Fall River Daily Herald Parnell Welcomed 004.tiff"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>I am happy to think that you have investigated the causes which have brought me to this city. It would be useless for me to say that I am not worthy of the reception you have given me to-night, because, of course, it is evident that you have given it to the cause I represent, the cause of a suffering and starving people. I shall, before proceeding to the main portion of my address, endeavor to explain that we have changed somewhat from the original object for which we came to this country. Originally we came to this country for the purpose of enlisting your sympathy and support solely in behalf of our political movements in Ireland; but the immensity of the famine, and the certainty that unless something is done very speedily, in six or seven of the large counties in the West of Ireland, thousands will perish of the most horrible of all deaths, famine; so we have changed in obedience to the dictates of humanity and ask you to assist us in endeavoring to remove the distress in Ireland. Now, the Irish land subject is a very complex question; and it would be impossible for me, or anybody else, to treat of it, of that whole question in a single speech. I have, since my arrival in this country, examined this question from all points of view; and we have placed before public opinion the object we have in view, which is, shortly, to obtain for the tillers of the soil the sunshine of day; in other words, we desire to abolish the feudal land system which prevails in Ireland. It is a remarkable fact that no other country in Europe, save where British rule extends, does the feudal system fully prevail. The system in Ireland originally was that of tribal. Under its regulations the chieftains of the tribes exercised a kind of sovereignty over the people, who owned the land. The people gave their services in the army and were prepared to defend the country, in return for the occupation of the land. The chiefs had no real ownership in the lands that were cultivated; they belonged to the tribes according to the general system. But when the English conquered Ireland, they brought this feudal land system; in other words they took away the whole of the land from the people, and they transferred it to the soldiers of fortune, and others who had come over from England from time to time to assist them in their conquest of the country. I may here observe that in doing this they laid the foundation of all the trouble that has been in Ireland ever since. After your civil war in this country you never thought of confiscating the land; such an idea never entered your minds. On the contrary you hastened to admit those with whom you had fought to the rights of citizenship. You did not place those whom you had conquered under difficulties from which they could not recover, nor did you curse them with a feudal land system. Recognizing, therefore, the feudal land system of Ireland as the cause of all the misery, we desire to abolish it and introduce some other system, more humane, more in accordance with justice and the pressing requirements of an industrious and oppressed people. We are not seeking to introduce anything remarkably new, for we have precedent for all we propose to do in changing that system which has been productive of so much injury. We desire to abolish this feudal system of land tenure. France abolished it by the revolution. Prussia abolished it by a system which I shall describe to you. The system adopted by the King of Prussia to enable tenants to hold land might be adopted to great advantage in Ireland. My object in coming amongst you is not to appeal to your passions; but to give you as much information as I can with regard to the complex system of land tenure in Ireland and to endeavor to remedy the evil. (Applause.) The system of land tenure in Prussia in 1811 was far better than the system in Ireland. The tenants in Prussia had triple rights in the soil. They had a system of tenant right which prevented intrusion intact, and rendered it impossible to interfere with the occupation of the land; but at the same time the system which gave the ownership to the classes which did not cultivate it, awakened the King of Prussia to devise, at the conclusion of the war, to make the tenants in Prussia owners of the land in order to promote the peace and prosperity, contentment and solidity of his Kingdom. The edict which the King of Prussia made, with the advice of his ministers, is such a remarkable document that I shall trespass upon your time, while I read the preamble to you:- "We, Frederick William, by the grace of God King of Prussia, having convinced ourselves by personal experience in our own domains, and by that of many lords of the manors, of the great advantages which have accrued, both to the lord and to the peasant by the transformation of peasant holdings into property, and the mutation of service and use into a fair indemnity, and having consulted in regard to this weighty matter experienced farmers and skillful [sic] persons of all kinds belonging to our province, and to all ranks of our subjects, ordain and decree as follows": amongst other things "that all tenants of hereditary holdings, whatever the size of the holding, shall by the present edict become the owner of the holdings after paying to the landlord the indemnity fixed by this edict." And lower down there is another clause which says "We desire that the landlords and tenants should, of themselves, come to terms of agreement and give them two years to do so. If within that time it is not done the State will undertake it." The work was not done in two years. The landlords and the tenants could not agree in the terms in which it should pass, consequently the state stepped in and proceeded to make the transfer this way. They established rent banks, in all the different localities. The laws for establishing banks provided the machinery for the wholesale redemption of the land, and which was transferred to the tenant. By this law and its instrumentality the state constituted itself a broker between landlord and tenant. A bank established in each district was empowered to advance to the landlord a rent debenture by payment from per cent interest, and the amount of the rent debenture advanced to each landlord was to be equal to 20 years' purchase; what the state considered to be a fair rent. The state undertook to vary the rent, and it said to the landlord, you will receive debenture or bonds amounting to 20 years purchase of this rent. These debentures will carry four per cent interest per annum until we redeem them. Now you will have observed that Prussia was bankrupt. They had just come out of a disastrous war, without revenue or resources of any kind. The state was not in a position to pay the landlord his money, simply because they had no money or any credit to borrow the requisite sum, consequently they offered to the landlord four per cent interest. The tenant, on the other hand, had to repay the government for undertaking this obligation, and this was the method by which it was paid. The tenant was obliged to pay into the hands of the district tax collector each month a twelfth part of the rent, calculated at five per cent of the capital sum issued in debentures and bonds to the landlord. At the end of 41 years the land became the property of the tenant without further charge. You will observe that the position was this: The landlords received debentures from the state in termination of their interest in the land. The state paid the landlords four per cent. per annum, and the tenant paid the state five per cent. for 41 years upon the capital amount of this debenture. In other words the state became the landlord. Now another principle has been adopted by the Legislature in England with regard to this question of enabling the tenants to become the owners, and we have been told that we were Communists, robbers, of the Irish landlords, and that we were not worth the attention of this country. I will explain to you the principle upon which the legislature of England has acted. Two acts of Parliament provide for this. One of these was the Irish Church Act of 1869. The other the Gladstone land act of 1870. The Irish Church, as it is commonly called, but rather the English Church Establishment in Ireland, was maintained by the rents of Church members, or tenants of land in Ireland. The State protected the life interest of these clergymen, by making an annual payment during their life, to take from the tenants, who had become tenants of the State, under the form called the Irish Church Temporalities bill, controlling property which was formerly managed by the Church. By the act of 1869 it was directed to sell all this land. It was not considered a desirable thing that this land should continue to be the landlord's or tenant's for an indefinite time or that they should be in the ordinary sense of the word, tenants at will. The purchasing price arranged to be paid for this land was to be in this manner:- three-fourths of it was to stand out for a period of 35 years at a low rate of interest. The principal was to be paid in installments [sic] during this period, the remaining quarter was to be paid down by the tenants in cash. Of the 5000 tenants, 3000 became the owners of their own farms, paying one fourth in cash the remained being allowed to stand a period of 30 or 35 years (I forget exactly) and payable by installments [sic]. Well that was one of the ways in which the English recognized the desirability that tenants should become owners of the land. That was done by Mr. Gladstone under a liberal government. (Great applause.) The other act was the land act of 1870 and John Bright, (loud and continued cheers) who is a firm believer in the principle that the land ought to be held by those who till it, introduced into that act what were called the Bright clauses. By these clauses the State was empowered to advance to tenants desirous of purchasing of estates coming into the market voluntarily, by the will of the landlords two-thirds of the purchase money, the tenant to find the remaining third himself. The repayment of the two-thirds to the State was spread over a period of 35 years in installments [sic] of five per cent. by the tenant to the state; and at the end of 35 years these payments were to cease, principal and interest being discharged by them. It is a remarkable fact that while the clauses of the Church Act which permitted tenants to purchase their holding succeeded in a remarkable manner, 3000 out of 5000 having purchased their holdings, the Bright clauses remained practically a dead letter. There is a reason for that. In the operation of the Bright clauses of the land act the landlords, who were selling land, obstructed their working with equal determination; and to such an extent did that proceed that these Bright clauses have remained almost inoperative during the nine years since the passing of that act. The reason for the inoperation [sic] of the Bright clauses, was that the landlords had refused to sell to the tenants, refused to break their estates up into small lots. They have preferred to sell to large buyers instead of small ones; the consequence has been, that up to the present time a large number, since 1870, have been unable to buy although willing to give more for farms than could be obtained from any other purchaser. The land in England and Ireland is handed down from generation to generation, so that it remains unbroken, and it is the desire of the owners to keep up the land system, which enables them to maintain superiority through owning the land. They have obstructed the tenants many times in their attempts to become owners. These are the principles which the legislature of Great Britain under a liberal government followed. I have already described the course in Prussia, and I ask you to say whether there is anything of communism in what I have said. There is another reason why landlords arrested the movement. The Irish land, as obtained, that is to say, the landlords interest in Irish land, has obtained a very fictitious value in recent years. During the last eight or ten years, owing to the great manufacturing prosperity in England, the prices of beef and butter, and other agricultural produce have advanced enormously. The landlords took all benefit of this advantage; and instead of sharing the advanced prices with their tenants have raised their rents. You will have some idea of that when I say that the land of Ireland is one the verge of 50 per cent over the valuation the government have put upon it for paying price. (Shame.) Of course one of the results of our movement is to break this high price down. The landlords made estimates, at the commencement of the agitation, as to the value of the land in Ireland. They value it at £250,000,000, 25 years purchase, at a rental of 50 per cent. over the valuation of the government. I would not value the landlords interest at more than 20 years purchase, upon the rental based upon the government valuation. In other words it would reduce their interest into market value by something like ninety millions of pounds sterling. Of course it is natural the landlords should make a great struggle , for owing to the land being put into the market in such large quantities, the people of Ireland get none of it. But here, again, I would call your attention to the distress which exists. I have pointed out the cause; accounts, as they continue to arrive, show that distress is increasing. Even at what should be the glad holiday of the many partial starvation has commenced, many in Ireland only taste meat once in a year, on Christmas days, and I regret to say that this Christmas that custom was observed more in the breach than in the observance. There were many thousands in Mayo who had no meat even on Christmas day, and many of them could not even obtain meal. We are charged with endeavoring to prevent the payment of rents. That is not true. In trying to faithfull represent the interests of the tenant farmers we bear in mind how they have been rack-rented and, in this time of terrible distress, we want that some of the burden shall fall upon the landlords who have raised rents beyond the capabilities of tenants to pay. Is there communism in that? (Loud applause.) We are perfectly willing in a case of this kind, if landlords have not raised the rents, that the fall in prices of agricultural produce should be fairly divided between the landlord and tenant. I should be exceedingly sorry to utter any words of injustice between the landlord and his tenant. I think we should strive to protect the interest of landlords who have let their lands at a fair rent, as we endeavor to protect the interest of the tenants who have to pay rack rents. Well, then, it is now come to the question as to how much the landlords shall get, whether they shall receive unfair rents in the presence of so much misery and suffering, whether the small minority shall extort while the people starve, or whether there shall be that even-handed justice to which legislation in other European countries has pointed in relation to the ownership of the land, and in the Church Temporalities Bill and Bright clauses of the land act in English Parliament. We feel that our efforts for the many are right. We want the people to be benefitted by wise legislation, to be rewarded for their labor. We do not want the people to be driven away. In short, everybody admits, except the landlords, and they are hard to convince, that they, the landlords, will have to go. (Long and continued cheers.) The only point to decide is how they are to be got rid of in a fair manner. That is the question, but we feel strong in the belief that they will have to go and the land come into the possession of those who till it. (Cheers.) The landlords admit that Ireland is in a peculiar state, both for themselves and the tenants. They are candid and they kindly say the tenants ought to emigrate. (Voice; send them to England.) (Another voice; send them out west.) If there was any choice and the people would receive them, we might give them Horace Greely's advice. It is, undoubtedly, a very great compliment to our people to be told by the newspapers of this country that they are very anxious to have them here. The American people say come over and we will give you land for nothing. This is a great comfort to our people at home, but I have not heard any such invitation from the landlords yet. (Cheers). On the contrary the New York Herald (hisses) although anxious to give the landlords every opportunity for fair play, does not invite them out here. I think the most forcible commentary that can be made upon the Irish land system is, that a class of men, educated and intelligent, should be placed in position and power, the Irish landlords have occupied for a period of seven centuries and not be able to find anything better than extradition, for the bone and sinew of Ireland. (Loud Applause.) Lord Dunraven is a fair sample of the landlord class. He addressed a long letter to the New York Herald in which he recommends his feeble plan of emigration as a cure, and he pitches into us Irish people for not being willing to go. He says there are two causes for the distress, the want of capital, continued increase of population and periodic times of famine. He thinks emigration is the panacea for all the troubles of Ireland. But, then, even though he is a lord, he may be mistaken. (Cheers.) His Lordship neglects to point out that the Irish people do not govern themselves, but are governed by the representatives of England, which the Irish people consider not only unfair, but look upon as a disgrace. Would emigration cure the evils? If emigration could have been any good to us in Ireland, we should have been the most prosperous nation on the face of the globe. There has been more emigration from Ireland than from any other European nation. Then he says we have given the Irish tenants very poor advice not to pay their debts. He calls it "A Patent Parnell Pill." He says, it is very deleterious in its consequences. The very last advice I gave before leaving Ireland to those present was to take all the money they had and pay their debts. (Cheers.) In nine cases out of ten the tenant has not made enough for his family to live upon. They tell the tenants to go and ask for an abatement for rent and the landlord refuses the abatement. To 650,000 people brought together we have given the advice that I have just told you, and yet this lord is not ashamed to come before the American people and tell them a palpable lie. He goes on to tell us, that the proceedings of the Parnellites are peculiar. We propose that the settlement of the land question should be adopted, which shall enable a tenant to hold his farm by paying rent to the government for a period of 35 years. We don't propose to pay Lord Dunraven all this. We hold that they should hold the land they till; and that no man should interfere with them in the efforts of their labor. He further reviewed Lord Dunraven's letter at length, and then went on to say that the history of Ireland has been one long continued struggle between the minority and the majority. The minority have ruled the majority, but the time is coming when the process should be reversed. The time has come when, if there has to be suffering, it should be borne by the minority, not by the majority. We proclaim the right to govern ourselves. We say that no government is constitutional, except a government by the majority of the people of a country; and that it is a systematic violation of that law which has led to all the trouble of Ireland. The minority have been settled down upon us and they have upheld their odious system. When the majority have decided one way, the minority have gone against it. It is time that this rule should cease; and that the same law which governs every civilized community should be had in Ireland. On this great principle the government must stand condemned. We think the time will come when the British government will be as anxious to settle the question as the Irish are themselves. Unless you act upon English public opinion by mere force, make it inconvenient for them to do injustice, we can never have a settlement. There is only one way, to show them that they must. (Here Mr. Parnell stamped his foot and there was great applause.) Other methods have been tried, various attempts have been made, to show John Bull that he must listen. Every attempt that has been made has been successful more or less, although the time might have fallen in different periods. Gladstone attempted, but not until a prison had been attacked at Clerkenwell, and the tragedy had occurred in Manchester. (Loud Cheers.) We are not recommending a resort to physical force, but in the troubles, as years roll along, it is impossible to say what may come if there is not some justice, some redress for the wrongs of Ireland. We want to feel that we have our sympathy and aid for the people of Ireland. We want to feel, as we go along in this agitation that you, in this land, sympathize in our endeavors. We have to thank our sympathizing countrymen for the aid they have rendered and which we feel will still be rendered. The people of the West of Ireland are in a fearful condition. They have had to endure a famine for three months; and we have advised the tenants to keep their rents and save them for food for their children. Had it not been for this the famine would have commenced three months earlier; and 100,000 of them have been kept from starvation through the abatement of rent. The famine instead of being confined to six or seven counties would have extended much farther. We have therefore succeeded in two things; in limiting the famine and postponing the date; but the time has come when further postponement is not possible. There is now no food left for 250,000 people of that country. We ask you, in view of the facts, to come to our assistance and help our people, until we can shame the government into a sense of its duty. I am sure that the people are very near starvation point. There is distress and destruction all over Ireland. In most of the Irish towns the laborers have only one meal a day, consisting of course Indian meal. In Omagh they have nothing left. The testimony of bishops, men of distinguished position, and gentlemen of all ranks and classes of society, of all political views, tell us of the extent of the famine, and ask you to come forward liberally with your sympathy and help in the removal of the causes. It is useless to give charity unless you take some steps to put down the tyranny. We think you ought to be proud of the opportunity given you to save a noble people. They are too [sic] many of you, kith and kindred, and their present wants and future comforts should be well considered. We wish to agitate in such a way that there may not arise the necessity for resort to force, to accomplish the purpose which Sarsfield enunciated on the field of Limerick. (Long and continued cheering.) I know, after a lapse of two or three centuries, we should take every opportunity afforded us for a settlement of this great question, that we should break down the barriers between class and class in Ireland, and Catholic of the South uniting with Protestant of the North, be united for one common purpose. (Immense cheering). It is possible to have the upper classes of Ireland taking their position as leaders of the people, as friends of the people. When that comes, and come it may, we shall partly have realized the dream of true Irishmen at all times during the history of the country, which may yet been redeemed; and you, in this country, may then look back with satisfaction to the part you have taken, and bless your fortune that you have lived unto to-day to assist us in the aim we have in view. Immense cheering which continued three or four minutes.</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
