<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Mr. Parnell in Plymouth, The Times, Monday 28 June 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Mr. Parnell in Plymouth</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-06-28">28 June 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00076"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">   
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url=""></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, on rising to speak, was received with loud cheers. He said, - Mr. Chairman, and men of Plymouth, I am indebted to our chairman, as he has told you - very much indebted - for the invitation which he extended to me to visit this portion of the counties of Cornwall and Devonshire, and it is a very great pleasure to me personally to have an opportunity of coming in contact with the stalwart population of the south-west of England. I have never been so far down in this direction before, although some of the earlier years of my life were spent at a school in the neighbouring county of Somerset and it is a curious fact that it was the school of Plymouth Brothers, so that any mischief that you may be disposed to admit to me (great laughter) as well as some good - some little good - (cheers) that some of you may be disposed to admit I have done in the course of my life (cheers) you must, in fairness, attribute it, or, at all events, a portion of it, to the very excellent teaching which I received in my earlier years - to which I shall always look back with the greatest reverence, affection, and respect - from my pastors and masters in the neighbouring county of Somerset. Your chairman has truly reminded you that this is a struggle of the democracies of the two countries - England and Ireland - and it is the first time that it was possible for them to come together. (Cheers.) And they have lost no time about it; and it is to the credit of the innate perception and good feeling of the people of England and Ireland that within a few months after they were enfranchised they have taken and shaken each other by the hand. (Loud and prolonged cheering.) No, Sir, the Anglo-Irish quarrel has not been a quarrel between the democracies of the two countries. The peoples of neither country have been responsible for it, and we have never, and I have never, thought to attribute to the democracy of England or Scotland any share in the blame for the misgovernment of Ireland. I recognize that the misgovernment has been the calculated engine of the privileged classes (loud cheers) against whom you have to struggle quite as much as we have, and by whom the misrepresentation with which it is sought to overwhelm our cause has been sedulously propagated for their own purposes. (Cheers.) No, the responsibility does not rest upon the democracy of England, but the responsibility will rest upon them if after full consideration and examination the democracy of England should reject the prayer of Ireland. (Cheers.) But I have no fear of such a result. It has been a fortunate and a happy thing for my country that this question has fallen into the hands of that great man, that greatest man, (cheers) in whom we recognize the ability and the willingness to settle this question. We believe that no other Englishman could have been potent enough to settle it. So I say it is a happy and a fortunate thing for Ireland that she has found such a champion. (Cheers.) In his older days - at a time when other men would have sought repose - his duty has been plainly pointed out to his conscience. He has disregarded the claims of, perhaps, failing health, and with an extraordinary vigour, mental as well as physical, which no other man could have equalled, he has thrown his whole heart into this last effort of his to do justice to Ireland and to settle for ever this long-standing quarrel between the two nations; and whether he succeeds or fails Ireland will always be grateful to him. (Cheers.) His words will have been left as a legacy for succeeding Englishmen and they can never die. (Cheers.) Having opened the way, even should he fail (loud cheers), for a man who has never failed in anything yet is not going to fail when he appeals to the newly-enfranchised masses of Great Britain (cheers) - he will, I say, in any case have pointed out the way for the English people. That way will be clear and made open, and our nation will be given that justice that it is Mr. Gladstone's desire she should have. (Cheers.) Now, fellow-countrymen (cheers), if this enormous and gigantic meeting can have patience with me, let me go into a few disputed details of this question. Let me touch first of all upon the land question. Now, the land question has interested us very much in Ireland, because it has been a case of life or death to our people. We have not had the manufacturing industries upon which you have fallen back in Great Britain for your support. But for these you would have had no nation. If you had been left to the tender mercies of the landlords in England you would not have had as much of a nation in England as we have in Ireland. (Cheers.) As I go through the country and see the vast distances which intervene between the habitations of the people I am tempted to say that the hand of the landlord has been as heavy upon the people of England as it has been upon the people of Ireland. (Cheers.) But you have had some other resources to fall back upon (interruptions and a voice, "Phoenix Park"), and you have not been drifting into deep sea as our people have been, and, consequently, the land question has not attracted so much attention or been so pressing and prinching [sic] in England as it has been in Ireland. But the land has been the only resource of the Irish people. They have been obliged to stick to the land, and when they have been driven off it they have died in the workhouse, they have perished in rotten emigrant ships, and the remainder of them have found that home beyond the Atlantic which was denied to them in their own country. Well, then, the land question is a great and pressing question in Ireland. You know that Mr. Gladstone sought to settle it by a Land Purchase Bill. This Bill would have extended very favourable terms to the Irish landlords. (A voice, "Too favourable.") I agree with my friend that the terms would have been too favourable. (Cheers.) But the Irish people, in return for the settlement of the national question, would have permitted them to go to work in the direction of the development of the resources of their own country, to open up their mines, to drain their swamps, to build their harbours, and to make railways when necessary. The Irish people would have been willing to have given the landlords much too favourable terms in order to be quit of them, and the only condition we had in our minds was this, that the landlords should not be given so much as would render it impossible for the tenants to pay the annual instalments, and so throw any loss upon the British taxpayer. (Cheers.) We did not consider that we were entitled to ask the working men of England to share or to contribute one farthing towards the expense of getting rid of the Irish landlords. (Cheers.) We were willing to do it ourselves, and we believe that by making sacrifices, and under Mr. Gladstone's Land Purchase Bill, not a penny of the cost would ever have fallen upon the British taxpayer. (Cheers.) Now that was the principle I kept in my mind in dealing with Mr. Gladstone's Land Purchase Bill. I admit it was too good a settlement for the landlords, but the landlords have saved any compunction of conscience on that score by being so idiotic as to reject it (laughter), and they will never hear anything more about that Bill. There are several ways of settling the Irish land question besides giving 15 or 20 years' purchase to the Irish landlords. I will tell you a way of settling it; I will tell you a much better way of settling it than by handing 50 or 100 millions of money to the Irish landlords. Let me carry you back for two or three years in Parliamentary history. You will remember that Mr. Gladstone passed a Land Act for Ireland, and that great results were expected from that Land Act. But two things happened - one of them before the Act was passed and another immediately afterwards - which prevented me and my friends from having any expectation whatever that the Land Act would settle the Irish question. And bear this in mind for a moment, because the thing is an argument in reference to the Home Rule Bill of Mr. Gladstone. It is said that the Irish have never been satisfied with any Bill that was passed for them, that they have never taken it as a final settlement, that they did not take the Land Act as a final settlement, and that they will not take the Home Rule Bill as a final settlement. I say in reply to that that the Nationalists of Ireland never accepted any Bill coming from the English Parliament as a final settlement of any question until this Bill was introduced, and that we come before you with clear consciences in that respect. We have never given you to suppose that we would take any measure that was brought forward as a final settlement of any question until this measure was brought forward; and at the time of the passing of the Land Act we expressly warned you that it could not settle the question. We did more than that. Many of us sealed our belief in our own words by suffering imprisonment. (Loud cheers.) Well what were these two things which happened at the time of the passing of the Land Act which deprived us of any confidence in that enactment? I will tell you shortly. There was a clause which was introduced by the Irish members into that Act which provided that no rent should be charged upon any improvement made by a tenant or his predecessors in title. That clause was passed by the House of Commons, but when the Bill containing it went to the House of Lords (laughter and groans), they said to themselves "It will never do to allow this clause to pass into law; it will be made a precedent with regard to English legislation, and we landlords in England - for of course the House of Lords is a House of landlords (cheers) - will by and by have the same measure meted out to us that the House of Commons has meted out to the Irish landlords." The House of Lords, acting upon this consideration, to a great extent emasculated that clause, though it was not destroyed entirely. It was sent back to the House of Commons, and the Government, very wisely, as I think, agreed to the amendment in a great portion. At all events, the clause by this amendment was to a large extent rendered valueless for the purpose of protecting the improvements of the Irish tenant. However, it was not entirely useless, there was a little good left in it, but even that was entirely taken out of it shortly afterwards by an interpretation put upon the clause by the majority of the Judges in the Supreme Court of Appeal in Dublin, and the result of that interpretation, combined with the previous mutilation of the measure in the House of Lords, was to render that important clause perfectly useless for its purpose, and to destroy the utility of the Act. Now if we, knowing this to be so, had failed to say so and to warn the English Government and the Irish people that the Act would fail, should we not have been dishonest and cowardly? ("Yes" and cheers.) Well the Act failed. I must tell you by way of remark in passing, that there was a very close division on the judgment in the Supreme Court of Appeal in Dublin, that it was only carried by a majority of one in a full bench of judges, and that it so happened that all the Tory judges voted on one side and all the Liberals, including the Lord Chancellor, on the other. But the Tory judges were in a majority and they carried the appeal against the Irish tenants and destroyed the Land Act. Now that is a short history of the Irish Land Act, and we had failed still to settle the Irish land question. I tell you this, that, speaking shortly, one way to settle the Irish Land question would be to reduce the statutory term of tenure from 15 years to five, and to restore the improvements clause of the Land Act to the state in which it was left by the House of Commons. These two terms taken together would reduce the present judicial rents by, at least, 20 or 30 per cent. from the standard fixed by the Court - a standard which the tenants are utterly unable to pay and live at the same time. It is a measure which would not hurt the pockets of the English taxpayers, but it is also a thing that the landlords would not like nearly so much as 50 or 100 millions of money. However, the Irish landlords have put this matter out of Court. In respect to their feelings or ideas being taken into consideration the matter is now gone before the democracy of the two countries and it will have to be decided by them (cheers); and the position of the Irish landlords will be something very like that which is depicted of the drowning crew in Virgil's line - </p>
         <p>"Rari nantes in gurgite vasto."</p>
         <p>When the ship had been shipwrecked a few of the mariners were seen swimming here and there, a few of them struggling in the vast whirlpool, and they were soon overwhelmed. So it will be by the Irish Landlords who allowed the sands in the hour glass to run down, and who rejected Mr. Gladstone's generous offer. (Cheers.) And now I think I have shown you that you need not be apprehensive as regards this question of the 50 or 100 millions which has been brought forward by Mr. Chamberlain (groans), and Mr. Trevelyan. (Groans.) Mr. Trevelyan has been one of the gentlemen who has joined with Mr. Chamberlain (cheers and groans) in protesting against this tax, as they call it, of 50 millions being placed upon the English working classes; but it is a remarkable fact that Mr. Trevelyan himself in the last Parliament, brought forward a Bill for the purpose of giving 18 or 20 millions - I am not certain of which ("Oh") - to the Irish landlords at the expense of the British taxpayer, and without any of the guarantees with which Mr. Gladstone has surrounded his proposal. But the question of giving money to the Irish landlords is out of the matter altogether and you may dismiss it from your minds. The point for you to come at is whether you will do as Mr. Gladstone wants you to do ("No," and "Yes") - whether you will give the right of self-government to Ireland, or whether you will not. (Cheers.) I believe that there will be every desire on the part of the Irish people to give them more than they ought to get, but it will be a settlement which cannot be so good as the settlement which was offered to them by Mr. Gladstone. I now come to the simple question of whether you will give to Ireland the right to manage her own domestic business. (Loud cheers.) I pointed out at Portsmouth last night that Imperial unity does not require or necessitate that there should be a union of Parliaments. I took for an example the case of your colonies, who are united and who wish to be united in your Empire, not because they have not a separate Legislatures [sic], not because they have got a representation in the Imperial Parliament, but because they have got no representation in the Imperial Parliament. (Hear, hear.) I pointed out that rebellion in Canada had been checked, and that a feeling of disloyalty on the part of the French Canadians had been changed into a feeling of loyalty by the concession of a constitution to them. (Cheers.) I pointed out that there are many examples of separate Legislatures with power over domestic business in the colonies within the British Empire, and that these separate Legislatures, so far from contributing to discontent, had prevented discontent and created loyalty. I pointed out the example of the great United States of America, where there are 38 separate Legislatures. I am remined by a friend on the platform that there is a 39th Legislature which is now being born at the present moment. Then you have in the United States of America 39 separate Legislatures with powers in excess, and largely in excess of those Mr. Gladstone proposes to give us in this Bill. (Cheers.) The people of each State of the American Union have the right of appointed their own Governor by universal suffrage. (Cheers.) We don't claim that right. We leave the Imperial Parliament the duty of appointing the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland. Each State of the American Union has the right of appointing the Judges of the State and paying them and dismissing them. We shall not be able to appoint any judges until at least half the present Judges - and they are all fairly young men - have either died or retired. There are just twice too many Judges in Ireland; for, notwithstanding what you have been told, the people are a very law-abiding people (cheers), and there is very little litigation there. We shall not, I say, have the power of appointing a single Judge until half of the present Judges have either retired or died. We shall never have the right of dismissing a Judge except with the consent of the Protestant minority in Ireland, represented by the first order. (Hear, hear.) As regards the militia, each state of the American Union has the right of levying and controlling the militia of the State, and of appointing the officers thereof. We have no control whatever over the militia; they would remain under the Imperial authority as at present. (Hear, hear.) And then there are as many other points of difference of detail in favour of State rights in America, which I should weary this great meeting by going into ("No, no"), but this large concession of power to the States in America does not interfere with federal union, which answers to the same thing as Imperial union in this country. On the contrary, it strengthens and consolidates it. (Hear, hear.) When the Southern States of America tried to leave the union the Northern States had the conscience, not only their own conscience, but the conscience of the civilized world in approval of their course in keeping them within the union; and it would be the same with you if, after you have conceded State rights would be in comparison with those enjoyed by the States of America, any demand were made to separate from England by force, you would have that moral influence and authority in compelling Ireland to remain within your Imperial union which you have not now got. (Loud cheers.) But you can never have this until you yield these concessions to Irish opinions. (Cheers.) (A voice.- What about Ulster. Cheers and counter cheers). Now, men of Plymouth, I have shown you the examples of your colonies. I will not trouble you by going over those presented in European countries where the relations were similar to those between England and Ireland, and where concessions of autonomy have settled the difficulty and strife between them. I have shown you the example presented by the United States of America, and I ask you who in the name of common sense prevents the English people from doing this small justice to Ireland. (Cheers.) You cannot - you a great and a rich people over 30 millions strong, with colonies attached to you and ready to help you at the signal - you cannot surely be afraid of little miserable Ireland with her five millions of people. (Loud cheers.) You cannot really fear that such a concession to Ireland can possibly endanger your empire. ("No, no.") Why to hear the talk that goes on one would think that Ireland was inhabited by a people equally numerous and equally rich with yourselves, instead of a people few in number, reduced to the last stage of depression, poverty, and misery by long-continued misgovernment. (Cheers.) Oh no! Sensible men do not really fear these things, and the people of this country when the issue has been explained to them will not believe in these fears or any of them. This battle is being waged against Ireland by a class of landlords. Their loyalty that they boast of is loyalty to their own pockets. (Loud cheers.) Have they not repeatedly threatened, not now for the first time, that if the Queen, Lords, and Commons of England pass a certain Act they will rebel against the Imperial authority? Is that loyalty? ("No, no.") Much fight there is in them. (Loud laughter and cheers.) I know these gentry well. (Laughter.) The talk about the Protestants of Ireland, of whom I am proud to be one. (Cheers.) The Protestants of Ireland despise this miserable gang who trade upon the name of religion; they despise them and appraise them at their full worth. They threatened to rebel when the Irish Church was disestablished. They threatened to rebel when the first Land Act of 1870 was passed, and now they threatened to rebel again. (Laughter.) All I can say is that 1,000 men of the Royal Irish Constabulary - (A soldier, "Or the Royal Irish Regiment" (cheers) - will be amply sufficient to cope with all the rebels that the Orangemen of the North of Ireland can produce. (Hisses.) They would be just taken like corner boys and street rowdies, and they would be locked up in the police barracks. (Cheers.) This is another of the alarms that are raised:- that the Protestant minority of Ireland will be injured. Well now, I wish to point out to you that this cry is not really raised by the Protestants of Ireland at all. It is raised by a few fanatical Orangemen in the North of Ireland. The Protestants of Ireland are not a bit afraid of either the Pope or the Papists. (Cheers.) The great majority of them - and I know them well - are pretty much indifferent upon this question. Of the two things they would probably rather have matters left as they are, but they have not any very strong feeling one way or the other. There is a small minority strongly in favour of the Bill, and there is another minority larger in numbers; but not much larger who represent the party of violent resistance. So you need not regard this talk at all about the fear of the Protestants of Ireland. We are not a bit afraid of the Roman Catholics. I do not know whether there are any Cornishmen here to-night or not. (Loud cries of "Yes.") I live and was born in a portion of the county of Wicklow, which is a mining county, and a good many Cornishmen have come over to that county within the last fifty years for the purpose of showing us how to work the mines. They have been captains and managers and so forth and we have been very glad to have them. They have been all Protestants principally Nonconformist Protestants. They have built their little churches over at Wicklow, where they worship God according to their own consciences. Wicklow is a Catholic county; nine-tenths of the people are Catholic. Many scores of these Cornishmen must have come and gone in Wicklow within the last 50 years, and I believe there is not one of them, if you appeal to them, who have lived among this Catholic population who would not tell you that his right to worship God according to his own religion has been as secure in Catholic Wicklow and as little assailed by the Catholics of that county as it would have been in Cornwall. (Loud cheers.) No Protestant Cornishman who has ever come to Wicklow has been asked what his religion was. They have been admired and respected as God-serving and pious men, as men attentive and conscientious in the discharge of their duty, and they have been looked up to universally by their Catholic neighbours as men of whom we would welcome among us many hundreds more besides. (Hear, hear.) Now I am an employer - I trust you will excuse me for alluding to a personal matter - but I am an employer of labour to some extent in the county of Wicklow. I have got some quarries there and I have a great many men employed. The majority of the men who work the quarries are Catholics, as is natural in a Catholic county; but we have many Orangemen from the North of Ireland working side by side with them, and we have Welshmen from Wales, but no single angry word has ever been given by any Catholic workman to either Orangeman or Welshman, or ever will be given. (Loud cheers.) But this expression of panic and of fear on the part of the Orangemen, for it does not come from any other of the Protestants, comes from a place and part of Ireland where the Protestants are in the great majority. It comes mainly from Belfast and the north-east corner of Ulster. (Hear.) But where the Protestants are few in number, where they are living all over Ireland scattered about among their Catholic fellow-countrymen, we do not hear any expressions of alarm or fear from them. All the expressions of alarm or fear from them. All the expressions of fear and of panic have been from the Orangemen of the North of Ireland, and it reminds me of nothing so much as the wolf complaining that the lamb was muddying the water. (Hear, hear.) The lamb pointed out to the wolf that it was drinking lower down the stream than the wolf, and could not possibly muddy the water that was being drunk by the wolf. But that was not sufficient for the wolf, and he turned on the lamb and rent it. And this is the attitude of this small minority of Protestants. But I thank God, as a Protestant, that it is a very small minority. (Cheers.) These men seek to get their foot upon the necks of the majority in Ireland. It is not fair play, and they know it well enough. (Hear, hear.) And if fair play were wanting on the part of the majority of Irishmen, then I say it would be just and right, if Irishmen so far forgot the honour of their country and the public opinion of the world as to revert to the bigoted sectarian oppressions of the middle ages, for Englishmen to step in and take away this great privilege which Irishmen would then be proved to have abused. Now, I turn from this question of protection for the minority with the remark that that protection for the minority with the remark that that protection is amply provided for under the provisions of the Bill, because not a single Act of Parliament can be passed without the consent of the first order, which will be under the control of the minority. If the first order refuses its consent that Act will be hung up for three years, and during that three years there would be ample opportunity given to the English people to decide whether that enactment was fair or unfair to the Irish minority, and if it were unfair to treat the matter accordingly. Now I have nearly come to the end of what I have to say to you. I recognize how very fatiguing it must be for a crowded meeting such as this is to stand on their feet all the time during my long address, and I shall finish up very quickly after I have made some reference to what is now known as the Carnarvon incident. (Laughter.) It is a very favourable device with politicians when they are accused of one thing to say, not that they did not do that thing, but that they did not do something else. (Hear.) And when I stated that I had reason to believe that the Tories if they had a majority at the polls would have given us a statutory Legislature, with a power of protecting Irish industries against the products of British factories, Sir Michael Hicks-Beach contradicted me by saying that the Cabinet had not agreed to do that. (Laughter.) Well, I never said that the Cabinet had agreed to do it. From the very nature of the case the Cabinet could not have agreed to do it, because the matter was not ripe for final judgment, and could not have become ripe until the result of the general election was known. But what I say is this. The leading man, who was responsible in the Cabinet for the government of Ireland - a man in the high position of Lord Lieutenant (hear) - asked me to meet him in London for the purpose of consulting with me, and learning my views and giving me his opinion with regard to a Constitution for Ireland. (Cheers.) Now, a Constitution for Ireland can only have meant a Parliamentary constitution, and it has not been denied and cannot be denied. Secondly, I say that during that interview I found that Lord Carnarvon (groans) - do not hiss or hoot him; he was the only gentleman in the late Cabinet - Lord Carnarvon agreed with me in the main lines on which a constitution for Ireland might be granted by the giving of the statutory Legislature. (Hear, hear.) Lord Carnarvon does not deny that. But what he denies is this. He says " I do not agree with Mr. Gladstone's Bill." Well, I never said that Lord Carnarvon agreed with Mr. Gladstone's Bill; but I said that he agreed with me at the beginning of last August regarding the lines upon which the Irish national question should be settled. (Cheers.) It is very likely that he does not agree with all the points in Mr. Gladstone's Bill. I do not agree with all the points in Mr. Gladstone's Bill. A great many people on one side and another do not agree with all the points in Mr. Gladstone's Bill. I agree with Mr. Gladstone's Bill in the main (cheers), and I know that if there had been a shorthand writer present at my conversation with Lord Carnarvon last August, he would have been found also to have agreed with Mr. Gladstone's Bill. (Cheers.) There are important points of difference very probably; but I do not wish to make any further disclosures. (Cries of "Go on," and cheers.) Very probably Lord Carnarvon in his constitution would like to keep the Irish members at Westminster in order to vote down Radical measures. (Laughter.) But there is another assertion that I have made which has not been attempted to be denied, and it is this. Lord Carnarvon has not denied my assertion that he urged these views on the Cabinet for six months, and that although the time for the Cabinet to take a final decision did not become ripe until after the result of the General Election was known, yet, notwithstanding, during the whole of those six months, Lord Carnarvon was not opposed in the Cabinet to any extent. And I make another assertion now which Lord Carnarvon will not deny either. If his views had been opposed in the Cabinet during those six months so as to make him believe that he could not have carried them, he would have resigned his office (loud cheers); and he never did resign office until the result of the General Election and our failure to give the Tories a majority swung the Cabinet round into opposition to his views. (Cheers.) Now, I think I may leave Lord Carnarvon with these two or three assertions after making a further statement. Lord Carnarvon has stated that he spoke to me unofficially. Well, he has been asked by Mr. Gladstone to give his version of what he said to me and of what he said to Lord Salisbury afterwards. This request has been made by Mr. Gladstone not once, but twice, and the British public are entitled to have an answer. (Cheers.) I have given my version of a portion of what took place at the interview. Let Lord Carnarvon give his. (Cheers.) He says that he spoke to me unofficially. I want to know how much of what I said to him he communicated to the Cabinet. Lord Carnarvon, as the result of that interview, and as the result of what passed between us, gave me earnest of his official capacity during the interview, and very good earnest too. He gave me five millions of money. (Cheers and groans.) I say he gave me earnest of his official capacity at that interview - (Interruption caused by a squad of youths singing "Rule Britannia," which was met with overwhelming cheers for Parnell.) Ah! these gentlemen are afraid of hearing the truth. (Loud cheers.) He gave me earnest of his official capacity, not for myself but for the Irish landlords, in the shape of five millions sterling money of the British taxpayers. And within a week after that interview at my request, made at that interview, and at my strong recommendation, he passed the Land Purchase Act - it would not otherwise have been passed - giving five millions of your money to the Irish landlords. (Cheers.) Was that an official act or not (loud cries of "Yes"), arising out of that interview? (Cheers.) Did he communicate anything about my recommendation to pass that Land Purchase Bill, and a larger Land Purchase Bill later on as a part of the national sentiment, to Lord Salisbury? (Cheers.) Now, I have made a few fresh revelations about Lord Carnarvon. Lord Randolph Churchill of course (great groaning) is a bird of another feather. Lord Carnarvon is a sensible man, and resigned his position when he found he could not carry out the expectations which he had held out to us. But Lord Randolph Churchill, although he was up to the hilt in the thing too, did not resign his office, and has only turned right-about-face. (Laughter.) He became a denouncer of the very policy for the relief of Ireland that he had a month before determined to carry out. And now, men of Plymouth, I have expressed my belief that this cause is safe in your hands. Am I to measure the strength of the opposition by the contemptible interruptions to which I have been subjected? (Hear, hear.) If that is all the Unionists of Plymouth can do I feel very confident about the result. (Loud cheers.) I believe that the great heart of the English people has been touched by this question in a way it has never been touched before, and that the genius of the illustrious Englishman who towers head and shoulders above all other living men (cheers), for who equal as a statesman and as a philanthropist we have to search the pages of history in vain (cheers), has shed a new light upon the blood-stained pages of Irish history. That light, strong as truth, bright as the sun will never fail until you have thoroughly read the words written on those pages, and when you have read that book you will come to the conclusion that neither landlord tyranny nor Orange bigotry shall continue to blind you to the suffering of the sister nation, or prevent you any longer from doing her that justice which she confidently asks from you. (Loud and continued cheering.)</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell, who was loudly cheered on rising to reply, said, - I thank you most heartily for the kindness and general good order with which you have listened to me, and I believe that this meeting will have good fruit and good result. (Cheers.) As I have already said, I leave this issue, which is simply one of truth and justice and nothing else (cheers), with confidence in your hands, that you will do justice to our nation as well as to your own great Empire. (Cheers.) I could have wished to have spent a longer time among so fine a people, but the claims of the great election contest that is now pressing around us draw me elsewhere. I trust, however, in happier and quieter times, when the Irish and English nations have learnt to understand each other and are bound together only by the terms of affection and respect (loud cheers), that I may have a further opportunity of making your acquaintance and of admiring some of the features of this beautiful county. (Cheers.) For myself, I can only say that it seemed when I came along in the train to-day almost as if I was going back to the days of my boyhood. I am pleased that I have had the opportunity of coming among you. I am pleased, glad, and grateful that I have been able to state, however imperfectly, what the Irish cause is, and however great may have been the deficiencies in my speech, and they undoubtedly exist to a large extent ("No, no"), do not remember them against me, and above all do not permit them to weigh against my countrymen. (Cheers.)</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
