<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Speech by Mr. Parnell, The Liverpool Echo, Thursday 11 February 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Speech by Mr. Parnell</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="" level="j">The Liverpool Echo</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">4</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-02-11">11 February 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7010597">Liverpool, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00050"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">    
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/bl/0000271/18860211/086/0004"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Speaking at Galway yesterday, Mr. Parnell said:- But since this election commenced Mr. O'Shea has given me a promise that he will sit on our side of the house, and therefore my last objection to him has disappeared (cheers). Under these circumstances should I allow him to be persecuted and kept out of Parliament? I know that his return cannot be any injury to the Irish party. He was the best man that I knew of at the time that I recommended him. As I have already told you, I did not know of Mr. Lynch's claims, and having recommended him, I was in my position bound not to recede one hair's breadth - not one jot (hear, hear) - but to carry through the recommendation to the bitter end, and to test whether the people of Galway and the people of Ireland had the confidence in me which I believe they have, and which I believe the result of this election will show - that during the eleven years since my entering into public life I have never led the Irish people astray, never led them into any crooked path. I have never led the Irish people astray. When courage was required and was necessary for the interests of the Irish nation I have shown it (hear, hear) and when moderation was necessary, and when temperate judgment for the nation was necessary, I have had the courage to show it, and shall never lead the party or the nation astray until we have gained for you the right to lead and govern yourselves (cheers). Now, fellow-countrymen, there are several gentlemen here who desire to address you. I think I have said everything that it was necessary for me to say with regard to the candidature of Mr. O'Shea. I need only add this, that you must not think that because Mr. Lynch has retired it is not necessary for you to go to the poll to-morrow and vote. All of you who have votes must go and vote for Mr. O'Shea, for otherwise the Tories might take advantage of the situation, might go and poll for Mr. Lynch, in order, if possible, to run him close to the poll for Mr. O'Shea. This is not Mr. Lynch's fault. Mr. Lynch has acted honourably towards me and towards the party. His name cannot now be withdrawn from the paper. It must be on the ballot, and, therefore, the Tories have the opportunity of trying to play this "dirty trick." But you will defeat this "dirty trick," and you will give your vote, not for Lynch, but for O'Shea, for the purpose of showing that you have voted for me and for Ireland (cheers). I should have desired to have addressed you also, apart from this election upon the great question of the day, but I think that, in view of the fact that Father Sheehy is here and will address you, I shall not longer detain you. I will only add in conclusion my conviction that the day is very near at hand when we shall have gained for Ireland the right to make her own laws on Irish soil. When that day comes I shall regard my mission as fulfilled. I have not entered on this great struggle with any motives of personal ambition but it is my duty to stand by you till these measures are gained for you. I have come down to Galway to stand by you in your cause, for any appearance of division in our party, of the weakening of my authority, would have been fatal to the cause, and that is the reason why I am here, and I confidently leave the result in your hands. After many a month you will look back to the proceedings of this day with satisfaction for the results which have proved that you have to-day struck a great and successful blow for Ireland (loud applause).</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
