<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The Split Among Nationalists, An Arrangement Made, The Northern Whig, Thursday 11 February 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The Split Among Nationalists, An Arrangement Made</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="27159818562313810880" level="j">The Northern Whig</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">8</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-02-11">11 February 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7012112">Belfast, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00050"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">  
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/BL/0000434/18860211/114/0008?browse=true"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, in addressing a meeting from the steps of the Galway Railway Hotel this evening, said the circumstances under which the meeting had been called gave him greater encouragement than anything he had felt since he first entered public life, for the circumstances had been well calculated to try their spirit of devotion and union. He admired the spirit with which Mr. Lynch had entered the contest, and he also admired the spirit in which he had withdrawn. As to Captain O'Shea, as far as he knew, his votes had been irreproachable. The last objection to him had been removed, and was he to allow him to be persecuted? Having recommended Captain O'Shea, he was bound to carry out his recommendation to the bitter end, and to test the people of Galway and of Ireland whether they had that confidence in him which he believed they had. During the eleven years since he had entered public life he had never led the Irish people or the Irish party astray. When courage was required in the interests of the nation he had shown it. (Cheers.) When moderation was necessary he had courage to show it. Let the people of Galway show, by returning O'Shea, that they had voted for him (Parnell) and Ireland. Mr. Parnell also said he would not enter on general public questions; he would only add his conviction that the day was near at hand when they should have gained for Ireland the right to make her own laws on Irish soil. When that day comes he would regard his mission as fulfilled. He had not entered on this great struggle with any motives of personal ambition, but it was his duty to stand by the people until these measures are gained. Any appearance of division or weakening of his authority would have a fatal effect on the cause. Months hence they would look back with satisfaction to the results of this election, for they would prove that they had struck a great and successful blow for Ireland.</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
