<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The O'Connell Centenary Committee, The Freeman's Journal, Wednesday 24 November 1875</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The O'Connell Centenary Committee</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="315698503" level="j">The Freeman's Journal</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1875-11-24">24 November 1875</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7001306">Dublin, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00028"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">      
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://archive.irishnewsarchive.com/Olive/APA/INA.Edu/Default.aspx#panel=document"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell said he had come to that meeting anxious to carry out those principles of harmony which the reverend gentleman had recommended (hear, hear). They found themselves at the very outset, he regretted to say, enveloped in difficulty by the conduct of the hon. secretary, who, in reading the minutes of the last meeting, had abstracted from the Freeman's Journal the very accurate report which had appeared in that paper of the proceedings after the Lord Mayor had left the chair (hear, hear.) It was alleged by Mr. Dwyer that Professor Kavanagh was right in doing so, because those proceedings were conducted by members who, in Mr. Kavanagh's opinion, were not members of this committee. His lordship had lately assigned two [indecipherable] against the validity of his (Mr. Parnell's) election to the chair on the last day of meeting, and which he was sure his lordship would on reflection admit to be entirely unfounded. The first objection urged against him was that he had not subscribed to the funds of the association.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell said it was true he had not been a contributor to the funds of the committee, and for reasons which, for the sake of harmony, he should prefer not to specify. He should, however, say that he was prepared to defend his conduct in that respect before any public body in Ireland (hear, hear). But although he did not subscribe to the funds of the committee he did subscribe to the other funds connected with the movement (hear, hear). He subscribed to the expenses incurred, and necessarily incurred, in worthily carrying the celebration to a success (hear, hear). He had subscribed to the funds of the two public bodies of his constituents in Meath to assist them in taking part in the procession (hear, hear).</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell (resuming) said that in addition to those he had subscribed to a public body in Dublin also, with the view of aiding them in more worthily contributing to the success of the procession.</p>
         <p>Chairman - Name them, if you have no objection.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell said he had not the least objection to name them. He had subscribed to the bakers of Meath and the Drogheda band to assist them in forming part of the procession, and the Amnesty Association. And he submitted that a good deal of the success and credit of the procession was owing to the contingents which came in from the outlying parts of the country to swell it and add to its imposing appearance (hear, hear). Every man was his own governor, ruling and controlling himself that day (hear, hear). He (Mr. Parnell) could not believe that the Lord Mayor really desired to rule out and not to be recognised the thousands which had been subscribed in various ways that never reached the hands of the Central Committee, or appeared on their list, towards the main object of celebrating the memory of O'Connell (hear, hear). Would it be said that those men, who had come in most cases at great personal expense and inconvenience from remote parts of the country, away from their business, to attend the procession, had not contributed to the celebration? He considered those men had done their duty in taking part in the procession, and he considered he had done his duty in assisting them to discharge theirs as far as his means allowed him (hear, hear). With regard to the seccod objection, that a circular was sent him by the committee, requesting his co-operation, on the condition of being added to the list of honorary members, he had never received such a circular. He had before stated that he had not received that circular.</p>
         <p>Mr. Keegan - I saw the circular directed to Mr. Parnell's Wicklow address; it was a few days subsequent to the resolution of Mr T.D. Sullivan.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - A circular informing me that, as a member of Parliament, if I co-operated with the committee, I should be an honorary member of the committee?</p>
         <p>Mr. Keegan - Yes.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - Well, I was not a member of Parliament for a month after (laughter).</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - I leave it to the meeting to consider what sort of recollection Mr. Keegan must have of the matter (laughter). He said it was a few days after the resolution being passed which directed these circulars being sent to members of Parliament. I attach no importance to the recollection of Mr. Keegan in the matter. I entirely deny your lordship's right to alter the constitution of this committee as it was defined at the National Conference (hear, hear). You have no more right to alter it than has the President of the United States or the Queen of England, or any other potentate, to alter the constitution of the country over which he or she presides (hear, hear). Your lordship did not act upon the principle on which this committee is and should be governed - namely, by the voice of the majority - when you left the chair on the last occasion, and refused to put Mr. A. M. Sullivan's motion as being unworthy of your lordship's dignity, (hear, hear). You then deprived the meeting of your support, and left us to get along as best we could. It would be well, I think, if you had put that resolution and taken the sense of the meeting on it, without raising the question of the status of members of that committee for the first time (hear, hear). We have here a duty to discharge, not alone to ourselves but to those in the country who confided this money to our care as trustees. To ourselves and our own reputations we owe it that this money should be expended only for the purposes originally intended and in a legal manner (hear). But if it be applied to any purpose against the wish and approval of the majority it will not be spent either legally or in accordance with the wishes of the country (hear, hear). I would ask some gentlemen who have not taken a prominent part in this dispute to try and suggest some mode in which we may arrive at a peaceable and satisfactory settlement (hear, hear). I should like to settle the matter finally to-day; but how are we to do so when our position and votes are questioned?</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
