<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Relief of Distress (Ireland) Act (1880) Amendment Bill - [Bill 205.], Hansard's Parliamentary Debates, Saturday 3 July 1880</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Relief of Distress (Ireland) Act (1880) Amendment Bill - [Bill 205.]</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="81159818807513812830" level="m">Hansard's Parliamentary Debates</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1880-07-03">3 July 1880</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00065"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>hansard report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">     
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/commons/1880/jul/03/relief-of-distress-ireland-act-1880#S3V0253P0_18800703_HOC_428"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that in the absence of the right hon. Gentleman the Member for the County Carlow (Mr. Gray), he had to ask for permission to move the Amendment of which the right hon. Gentleman had given Notice. The Amendment related to the advances made by Parliament for the purpose of enabling Boards of Guardians in certain districts of Ireland to lend or advance seed in the shape of the potato seed, and for other crops, to such persons as should require them. By the Act under which these advances were authorized, it was provided that the loans should be repaid by the Boards of Guardians to the Treasury at the end of next year. But, in order to effect that re-payment, it had been necessary for the Boards of Guardians to collect the first instalment of the advance from the tenants. This was done, in many cases, before the growth of the crop to produce which the seed had been lent had been got in. It was very commonly the case, with regard to potatoes, to allow them to remain in the ground until a late period, because it was found that they ate the better for being left in the ground; also that they were less liable to disease afterwards. There was some talk in Ireland during the late Election of asking the Government to remit the whole of the amount advanced for seed; but the leaders of public opinion, upon re-considering the matter, had thought that if they could obtain for the tenants the postponement of the re-payment of the first instalment for another year, they would be thus in a position to pay the amount to the Treasury. The loans had been described as having been of enormous assistance to all classes in Ireland, and it had been felt by the tenants that they ought to endeavour to do their very best to repay the loans as soon as it was possible to be done. The seed purchased for the purpose of making these loans was purchased at a very high rate indeed. He might state that the rates were 112 per cent over the market price previously asked. The rise in the price of the seed was in consequence of the passage of that Act. The great demand for fresh seed caused an increase in the price. Consequently, Boards of Guardians had to buy seed at a price at which potatoes never reached before in Ireland. So, from every point of view, the charge was an exceedingly heavy one upon tenant farmers, and it would be impossible for them to meet it at the present time. The Guardians admitted that if the advance were collected at the present time, the result would be that the feelings of the people would be set against the re-payment of the loan altogether. The people desired to pay it; but if pressed by the Guardians for re-payment before their crops were brought in, public opinion in Ireland would be more or less set against the re-payment altogether. At present, the desire was to look upon this as a just debt, and to avoid any unnecessary hardship in the collection of the money. They, therefore, thought that the Amendment of the right hon. Gentleman the Lord Mayor of Dublin was a fair and proper one. They asked the assent of the Government to the proposal that the landlords should not be asked to repay their loans for two years; but they now asked that the same period should be extended to the tenants. The tenants were willing to pay half of the advance, if postponed for a year, and the remaining half at the end of the year. He begged to move—</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that they did not propose to take money out of the Public Funds. The money had been already taken out of the Public Funds, and the Amendment dealt only with the question of the postponement of re-payment. With all submission to the Chair, he thought it was quite competent to move the Amendment. He would also point out that the Bill already dealt with grants from the Public Funds. By Clause 5, the Commissioners of Public Works were authorized to make advances of certain amounts of public money.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he did not consider the proposition of the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland was quite so satisfactory as some of his hon. Friends seemed to think. But, in the absence of his right hon. Friend the Lord Mayor of Dublin (Mr. Gray), who had placed this Amendment on the Paper, and who took a great interest in the question, he could not take upon himself the responsibility of rejecting the compromise, more especially as he was assured that they could not continue the discussion upon this question by reason of the Rules of the House; but he would suggest to the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland, that he should take the power in his proposed new clause for the Local Government Board to postpone the repayment of a portion, or the whole, of the instalments in any Union that the Local Government Board might think proper, because it was exceedingly probable that there would be a great many Unions where it was difficult for a portion of the tenant farmers to pay this year, and yet the remaining portion of the farmers might be able to pay. At the same time, he thought it would probably have been better if he could allow the whole of the charge to be postponed for a year. The Committee would recollect that that was the intention of the Legislature on the passing of the Act of Parliament. The intention of the Legislature was evidently that the farmer should pay in the next 12 months. That was shown by the way the Act of Parliament referred to the Boards of Guardians; but by a rule necessarily adopted by the Local Government Board, in order that the Boards of Guardians should pay next year, it became necessary that the tenants should pay this year, so that the intention of the Legislature was clear that the tenants should not be called upon to pay this year. He thought that where the payment could not be made without undue harshness or pressure upon those who had contracted the debt, then the re-payment was a matter which could not fairly be insisted upon. Of course, they had been charged with the desire to repudiate their debts; but he believed that no people were more willing than the people of Ireland to carry out their just contracts—contracts entered into according to the conditions under which contracts were usually entered into in civilized countries. He had seen no disposition on the part of the Poor Law Unions in Ireland to repudiate their just debts. He should ask permission to withdraw the Amendment.</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, the Amendment which he was about to move—namely, to insert, in page 1, after the word "Act," inline 15— And whereas it is desirable to enable the Commissioners of Public Works, on the recommendation of the Local Government Board, to advance moneys by way of grant to the Boards of Guardians in scheduled Unions, subject to the restrictions and conditions hereinafter set forth, must be taken in connection with the next Amendment standing in his name— namely, the addition to this clause of the following words:— The Commissioners of the Public Works in Ireland may from time to time, on the recommendation of the Local Government Board, grant to any Board of Guardians of a scheduled Union, out of the said sum of one million five hundred thousand pounds, such moneys as the Local Government Board may deem necessary, having regard to the financial condition of such Union, to aid in giving out-door relief to such Union: Provided, That the entire sum to be so granted shall not exceed one hundred thousand pounds. That Amendment had been framed in view of the suggestion made by the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland the other morning, when they were discussing the second reading of the Relief of Distress Bill (No. 2). The right hon. Gentleman then suggested that the adjournment of that Bill should be agreed to, with the view of introducing an Amendment to carry out the effect of the modifications which he (Mr. Parnell) had agreed to make in his Bill. The Bill, as it originally stood, provided that the grant of £200,000 should be given to a Commission which was indicated in the Bill; but, in the discussion upon the second reading, the Chief Secretary for Ireland seemed so very much averse to taking the matter out of the hands of the Poor Law Board, that it was suggested that the Local Government Board should be intrusted with the distribution of the proposed grant. Now, he (Mr. Parnell) thought if power was given to the Local Government Board to grant money to certain Unions, it would facilitate enormously the setting in motion of the machinery of the Poor Law in reference to outdoor relief. Speed being of the utmost importance at that moment, he thought that if the right hon. Gentleman attempted to drive the Poor Law Boards in Ireland into the distribution of outdoor relief, it was most desirable that he should have willing instead of unwilling horses to drive. It stood to reason that if the Unions knew they had in the clause the means of obtaining grants in aid of out-door relief, they would be much more willing than they were at present to set their machinery in motion. There was an example in point in the Poor Law Act, which provided that medical stores and attendance should be paid by grant; and their experience of the working of the Act showed that the amount of medical comforts and attendance had been increased by the fact that only half of the cost was charged on the rates, while the rest was paid by the means of grants. Now, at that moment, the people of Ireland were getting weaker and weaker, and were becoming more liable to the fever— spotted typhus fever—which had broken out in Galway. The right hon. Gentleman seemed rather to take comfort to himself that this fever had not originated since he had commenced his system of out-door relief; but, at all events, it had originated since the right hon. Gentleman assumed the reins of government in Ireland. He (Mr. Parnell) had no wish to throw the responsibility for this upon him, because, no doubt, it had come as one of the heritages created by the ineffectual attempts of the late Government to deal with the distress. The people of Ireland had been living on meal supplied by charitable contributions; those contributions had fallen off, and in a few weeks the strain of relieving the people would be thrown upon the system which the Chief Secretary for Ireland was putting into operation. But the few Poor Law Boards administering relief had been doing so in an inefficient manner, and with the most careful regard to the pockets of the ratepayers; and already the Chief Secretary for Ireland had had to nominate paid Commissioners in their stead. The Committee possessed little information as to these official Guardians, and it might, he believed, be assumed that it was not easy to get men capable of dealing at short notice with the emergency which existed in Ireland. Any inducement, therefore, which the Legislature could give the Poor Law Unions to co-operate in the system of relief, would be of the utmost importance. He would, therefore, suggest that, in the event of his Amendment being agreed to, the Local Government Board should announce to such Unions as they thought proper, where any emergency existed, that they would give one-half, one-third, or one-fourth of the amount paid for out-door relief. The Unions would then have a direct stimulus to administer relief, because, if they refused, they could be forced to do so, and if they threw obstructions in the way of the Local Government Board, they could be punished by withholding from them the proposed grants in aid. He had a right to say that the unanimous opinion of the Irish Members was entitled to consideration; and when he moved the second reading of his Bill, hon. Member after hon. Member had risen and urged its acceptance by the Government. The Irish Members had in every way met the wishes of the Government, and they had agreed to leave the distribution of the money in the hands of the Poor Law Boards, although they were convinced that there existed an emergency with which it was impossible to cope, even by means of those Boards. He, therefore, urged upon the right hon. Gentleman the necessity of accepting his Amendment. The money was to come out of the Irish Church Fund, and would therefore lay no burden on the Imperial Exchequer. It was the money of the Irish people. Already £1,500,000 had been given out of the Irish Church Fund to the Commissioners of Works; and he believed that this grant, which he now proposed, would be instrumental, during the six weeks which intervened between that time and the harvest, in preventing much sickness and in saving a good many lives. The Special Commissioner of The Freeman's Journal reported that fever was raging in Swinford Union; a total of 21 people had been removed to the workhouse suffering with fever. Some doubt had been cast upon the opinion that it was famine fever; but, if it was not famine fever, it was fever caused by distress, and by want of food, as well as by the want of change of diet. Again, if it was not famine fever, it was because there had not been the same extremity of distress and actual famine in Ireland as there had been in 1846–7; but it was more virulent and more catching, and was likely to spread over a large area, if some machinery could not be had to provide better food and clothing for the people than they had during the last six months. He had information that the allowance of Indian meal to each person per day was about 32 ounces, and this, it would be seen, was not so good as the allowance in the prisons in this country, where they gave soup and potatoes twice a-day. Under these circumstances, he urged upon the Government the necessity of making further provision for the relief of the people of Ireland. But, unless some relief were given to the bankrupt Poor Law Boards, it would be impossible to make any change in the scale of diet which they were obliged to adopt With the object, therefore, of preventing further sickness and loss of life in Ireland, he begged to move the insertion of the Amendment of which he had given Notice, such Amendment to be taken, as he proposed, in connection with the next Amendment standing in his name.</p>
         <p>Amendment proposed, In page 1, line 15, after "Act," to insert "And whereas it is desirable to enable the Commissioner of Public Works, on the recommendation of the Local Government Board, to advance moneys, by way of grant, to Boards of Guardians in scheduled Unions, subject to the restrictions and conditions here in after set forth."—(Mr. Parnell.)</p>
         <p>Question proposed, "That those words be there inserted."</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that he thought his hon. Friend (Mr. Synan) was under a wrong impression. He would see that the Amendment in the name of the hon. Member for Roscommon (Dr. Commins) was not of an alternative character for that which stood in his name. The Amendment of the hon. Member for Roscommon was one throwing an additional sum of £750,000 upon the Consolidated Fund, whereas that in the name of the hon. Member (Mr. Synan) was one reducing the rate of interest to 1 per cent.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that the right hon. Gentleman the Member for the county of Carlow (Mr. Gray) not having risen to move his Amendment, and no Amendment having been before the Committee subsequently, he submitted that his hon. Friend (Mr. Synan) was entitled to move that which stood in his name.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that the statement that had been made previously that the distress in Ireland had not been relieved from the Imperial Exchequer was strictly accurate, notwithstanding the exception mentioned by the hon. Member. But it should be remembered that the Seed Potatoes Act, although it would be of great use in the coming winter, had not yet been of any assistance in relieving actual distress. It was true, therefore, that the distress in Ireland up to the present had not been relieved to any extent by the Government whatever. He demurred altogether to the statement of the noble Lord the Secretary to the Treasury (Lord Frederick Cavendish) that the last Parliament had sanctioned this expenditure. The last Parliament did not sanction this expenditure. What it did sanction was an expenditure of £750,000. He contended that they were perfectly justified in asking the present Parliament to re-consider the matter. They were not asking this Parliament to re-consider the question of this expenditure; but they said that if they were bound to ratify the act of the previous Government, this ratification ought to be given at the expense of the Imperial Exchequer. But they ought not to put their hands into the unfortunate, and not very full, pockets of the Irish. What were the facts of this case? So far from the last Parliament having sanctioned the expenditure of the Government, it was exactly the reverse. By an Act of last Session £750,000 was granted for the purpose of making loans to landlords and sundry county authorities. This Bill was passed to ratify the proceedings and orders of the British Government, who found that, so far from the Irish Government having undertaken to advance £750,000, when the Treasury Minute, under which the Notice in The Dublin Gazette was published, only sanctioned the advance of £250,000. The Treasury Minute, after describing the purposes for which the Government were willing to advance the money, went on to say that the Government had. decided to recommend the Commissioners of Public Works in Ireland upon the responsibility of the Government to make an advance not exceeding the total sum of £250,000. He thought it should be distinctly understood that, in accordance with these directions by the Treasury, a Notice was issued by the Commissioners of Public Works in The Dublin Gazette of the 3rd January, 1880, distinctly stating that loans not exceeding£250,000 would be granted on certain conditions. The landlords borrowing money were, therefore, distinctly informed that the loan would not amount to more than£250,000. The Government, however, came forward in the last Session and granted an additional sum of £500,000 to the landlords, making a total amount of money authorized of £750,000. There was not the slightest necessity for the further advance, as was shown by the Return moved by the right hon. Gentleman the Member for North Devon (Sir Stafford Northcote). That Return showed that up to the 10th of April, 1880, only £354,520 had been sanctioned and ordered to be advanced to the landlords. On the 7th of May, when the present Government came into Office,  it was absolutely impossible that the further sum now asked for could in the meantime have been sanctioned conditionally. He confessed he could not understand upon what ground they were now told, in the course of this discussion, that the Government was morally bound to increase the amount. Originally, the Notice issued by the Government to the landlords distinctly stated that the amount of loan would be limited to £250,000, and that amount was subsequently increased to £750,000. But up to the 10th of April, the amount of loan sanctioned was only £354,520. He could see no excuse for the present Government asking that these loans might be sanctioned. The amount sanctioned by the Act of the last Session was only £750,000, and he could see no reason that they were morally or legally bound, or in any sense bound, to increase that amount. He wished now to make an explanation upon another point. The Government had given them the difference of this money, £200,000, and had taken power, by accepting the Amendment which he introduced later on, to apply a certain sum for the purpose of out-door relief. He thought it was only fair to them to pay interest and principal for such useful purposes out of the Church Surplus Fund. So far as the money at present advanced was concerned, not more than £60,000 had reached the hands of the distressed people, and he could not, therefore, regard the Act as one for the purpose of relieving Irish distress; but by the acceptance of his Amendment the Government had changed the situation, and he should be willing to accept such sums as the Government might advance to the Poor Law Board from the operation of the Amendment proposed by his hon. Friend (Mr. Synan). He was sure that his hon. Friend would be willing to agree to that Amendment. He wished to point out to the noble Lord the Secretary to the Treasury that the Government were dealing in a most shabby way with Ireland with respect to this distress. Up to the present time the Government had not given a single penny from the Imperial Exchequer for the relief of distress in Ireland. The Government of the Dominion of Canada had given £20,000, and the late Chief Secretary for Ireland (Mr. J. Lowther) was not ashamed to accept that amount and apply it to the relief of distress, although he refused to recommend his own Government to apply a single penny for the same purpose. The Legislature of Canada, one of the States of the American Union, and charitable persons throughout the entire world had subscribed sums for the relief of Irish distress amounting to £300,000, while the rich Government of England had refused to put its hands into its pockets for one single sixpence for the same purpose. He could not but think that the continual perseverance of the Government in that niggardly policy was a discredit to the Government of the country, and he trusted that his hon. Friend would press his Amendment to a division.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he had never hinted that the Government had no power to mate these loans; but he contended that there was no boon in making them. He quite agreed with what had fallen from the right hon. and learned Gentleman the Member for the University of Dublin (Mr. Gibson). It was quite true that under the 9th section of the late Act the Commissioners had the power to make advances to the extent of £750,000, instead of £250,000, the sum promised in the Circulars of the Treasury. But his contention was that it was not a boon to issue grants to landowners, other than those granted or sanctioned by the Board of Works up to the 19th April, 1880. According to the Return moved for by the late Chancellor of the Exchequer the Member for North Devon (Sir Stafford Northcote), the amount of loans sanctioned to landowners in Ireland was £354,520. He (Mr. Parnell) contended that it was that sanction that was referred to in the portion of the 9th section quoted by the right hon. and learned Gentleman the Member for the University of Dublin, when he intimated that all contracts, express or implied, which had been fully entered into between the Commissioners and any person, or the sanitary authority, respecting any such loans, should be valid and effectual. He would admit that if the Board of Works had entered into contracts up to the time when the late Government left Office to the extent of £1,250,000, the landowners would be, undoubtedly, legally entitled thereto; but, according to the Return of the Board of Works, they had only entered into such contracts to the extent of £354,520; therefore, the present Government could not shield itself if any excess beyond that sum was entered into. He wanted to know what the present Government did under these circumstances? There had been no Return on the subject and no information, although inquiry had been made, and the matter had been frequently alluded to in the discussion on that Bill. There had, he repeated, been no information whatever as to the amount of loans sanctioned by the present Government to landowners. When they came into Office, they had information in their possession to the effect that £354,520 had been sanctioned; but that was not £250,000. He should like to know how much had been sanctioned by the present Government, and the reasons why they sanctioned any additional sum to that they were entitled to do. The Government had often expressed their disapproval of those large grants, and they had thrown the blame of making such grants of public money, for purposes entirely useless, he must say, on their Predecessors. But the late Government, he contended, was only responsible for the sum of £354,520, sanctioned up to the date when they left Office. They must necessarily exonerate them from any further responsibility, and such responsibility must undoubtedly fall on the present Government.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, what he had meant was that the present Government disapproved of the low rate of interest on the loans to landowners, and had expressed a belief that they were useless for the purpose of relieving the present distress.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he did not think the time spent in discussing this question had been thrown away, because to Irish Members it was a very important matter whether £15,000 should be taken out of the Irish Church Fund or not. The Fund in question was the only one they had in Ireland for any purposes. But this sum of £15,000 would be an annual loss to the Fund for purposes which the Irish Members entirely disapproved from the first. It meant, also, a loss to the Fund for purposes carried against their will by a majority of English and Scotch Members. Surely, under these circumstances, when English and Scotch Members insisted upon applying money to purposes disapproved by the Irish Members, they should pay for it out of their own pockets, and not insist upon the Irish people paying for it. If Irish Members could have had their way they would not have devoted one penny of the Irish Church Fund in the way proposed by the Chief Secretary for Ireland. They had introduced certain Amendments indicating the way in which they desired the money to be spent; and so far as the right hon. Gentleman was willing to apply the money in the direction they wished, they were perfectly willing that the interest should be thrown upon the Irish Church Fund. But they objected that money applied against their will, and in accordance with the will of English and Scotch Members, should be paid for out of that Fund.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he could not entirely agree with the advice of the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland that the Committee should hurry through his Bill for the reasons stated by him. They had seen how much mischief had been done in the last Parliament by the hurried legislation which had taken place with reference to the relief of Irish distress. The various points now raised had been dictated by the experience gained since that time. It was rather unsatisfactory to be told by the Chief Secretary for Ireland that unless the Bill were passed through Committee that evening he did not know when he could again bring it forward, and that, in consequence, a number of benefits would be lost to Ireland. But there was nothing to prevent the right hon. Gentleman agreeing to the loans to Boards of Guardians; and so far as the Fishery Piers and Harbours were concerned the amount of £45,000 was a very insignificant sum, and one which ought to have been considered outside this Bill. He had himself urged upon the Chief Secretary for Ireland the desirability of such non-contentious matters being dealt with in a separate measure. The right hon. Gentleman, however, had not thought proper to agree to that suggestion. For his own part, he was unwilling to surrender his right of discussion for the purpose of getting the £45,000. He would further point out that the Amendment had been down on the Paper for a fortnight; and it was somewhat unsatisfactory that one of the Law Officers of the Crown, the right hon. and learned Attorney General for Ireland, who, he (Mr. Parnell) thought was not over - burdened with work, had not considered it and given the Committee the result of his consideration. The right hon. and learned Gentleman had told the Committee of the Act of 1862, and that under it bonds had been entered into. But did he know to what extent the £1,500,000 proposed to be lent by this Bill had been dealt with in those bonds? Again, did he know the terms adopted by the Board of Works under the powers of the Act of 1862, if they limited the works to one, two, or three years? Of course, information upon these subjects was exceedingly valuable, and was very much desired by the Committee for their guidance. Seeing that the Amendment had been on the Paper for a fortnight, it must have been evident to the right hon. and learned Gentleman that a discussion would be raised as to the terms of the bonds which had been entered into. He could not help thinking that the right hon. and learned Gentleman ought to know what terms had been agreed upon. If the Committee were supplied with that information, he could not see why they should not proceed to deal with the subject at once. However, in the absence of that information, he did not think it desirable to postpone the question until Report; because, as it was difficult to obtain from Government reasons why they were honourably bound with reference to this sum of £750,000, they might on Report be unable to furnish reasons why they were honourably bound not to accept the terms of the Amendment. He thought the Committee was entitled to some further information, and would suggest either that the Amendment should be accepted at once, power of alteration being reserved to the Government, or that the clause should be withdrawn; and as it was obvious that the stage of the new clause could not be reached that night, it might be brought in as a new clause a few days later, or whenever the Government wished to take the Bill again in Committee, He preferred that course to postponement until Report, which simply meant a foregone conclusion.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he should like to ask the right hon. and learned Gentleman the Attorney General for Ireland (Mr. Law) whether he could then give them the information for which he asked a short time since? First, as to the number of bonds entered into between the landlords and the Board of Works under the previous Act of 1862. Secondly, the amount of money covered by those bonds. Thirdly, the term of years covered by each class of bonds— for he had understood that there were different terms for the different classes of bonds. If the right hon. and learned Gentleman could give him an answer at the next Sitting it would do quite as well.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, there was a Return published under date the 18th March, in which it was stated that the amount sanctioned up to the 19th April was £354,520. That was just before the present Government came into Office, and he did not see why the Government should have gone on sanctioning fresh loans, believing, as they did, that this application of money was not all that it might have been. Now, it appeared to him that the Act of last Session distinctly referred to the Notice of the 12th January, issued by the Commissioners of Public Works, the obvious inference from which was that the Government were not bound to sanction loans to a greater extent than £250,000 until the Act of last Session was passed. It was admitted that the previous Government had not sanctioned loans to a greater extent than £400,000or£500,000. What the present Government wanted was a sanction for their conduct with reference to this matter in continuing to sanction expenditure. They said they were morally bound to expend this sum of £1,500,000. It seemed that there was no control whatever over the proceedings of the Irish Government, and that when anything was done, all that was necessary was for the Chief Secretary for Ireland to say that he felt himself bound in some way or other; and that was all the satisfaction that could be had with reference to the applications for this money. If his hon. Friend (Mr. Biggar) went to a division, he should vote for his Amendment. It was a monstrous thing to place a charge upon the Irish Church Fund which was not applied to the relief of distress in Ireland.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he wished to take, in the best part, the advice of his hon. Friend opposite (Mr. Fay); but he must reply to him, in equally good part, that he intended to occupy as much time in moving the Amendments in his name as he should think necessary. His hon. Friend appeared not to make sufficient allowance for the circumstances of hon. Members from Ireland, who had from the commencement of the Session taken much trouble with the Bill and had imported into it valuable Amendments. He could not imagine how any sensible person could stand up for the proposition of the Government contained in this clause. But to show the absurdity. The right hon. and learned Gentleman the Attorney General for Ireland (Mr. Law) had pointed out that the Government were morally bound to lend money to those landlords who had applied up to the 29th February last. Now, he would ask the noble Lord the Secretary to the Treasury (Lord Frederick Cavendish), who had endorsed that proposition, and the Chief Secretary for Ireland also, whether, if £20,000,000 had been applied—for an amount which the Church Surplus Fund could not guarantee—they would have come forward under this moral obligation, which they so much commended, and carried a Bill through Parliament to grant that sum of money? He ventured to think that had they attempted to introduce a measure dealing with English money as they were now dealing with Irish funds, their tenure of Office would have been very brief. The Government were certainly not legally bound to continue in the disastrous and useless course of their Predecessors.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he should like to ask the Committee to be allowed to amend the proposed Amendment by adding a few words thereto. He proposed to insert the words—"Under the authority of 'The Belief of Distress (Ireland) Act, 1880,'"at the end of the Amendment.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he was one of those who thought those two clauses were so utterly worthless that they could not possibly be made any better, and he doubted very much whether they could be so amended as to carry out his hon. and gallant Friend's (Major Nolan's) views. If the ratepayers, through their representatives, wished to charge themselves for the construction of county works, he (Mr. Parnell) had no objection; but the proposition contained in those clauses was entirely different. It was, that anon-representative body called the associated cesspayers, who were chosen by the Grand Jury and who would be confined to the magistracy of the county, should be entitled to saddle vast sums of money upon the ratepayers, at an extraordinary presentment sessions convened by the Lord Lieutenant. All the checks provided by the Legislature and by the Orders of the House of Commons were dispensed with, and, consequently, there would be practically no guarantee to the ratepayers who might be affected. If they had a representative system of county government in Ireland, these clauses might be made workable and very valuable; but, in the absence of any representative system, he feared to trust the very large power that would be given. He observed that a great number of Amendments had been placed upon the Paper to open the floodgates still higher, and, in his humble opinion, they would make the clauses still more dangerous than they were already. But he thought the Committee were entitled to have some reason for the postponement of the clauses. They ought to know whether the right hon. Gentleman proposed to postpone them in order to consider the desirability of giving them up altogether, or whether he intended to stand by them. If the first reason was the true motive, and the effect of the proposal would only be to save the time of the Committee, he should certainly be in favour of going on with the other part of the Bill. But, with reference to the remarks of the hon. Member for Meath (Mr. Metge), who seemed to be in a state of intense excitement about the whole measure, and feared they might lose something very wonderful if they did not get it, he could only say that, so far as they had gone, they had not obtained any very important concessions. Perhaps they might obtain those concessions by-and-bye; but, in explanation of the misapprehension of the hon. Member for Meath with respect to the merits of this measure, he (Mr. Parnell) might be permitted to state that he had no recollection of the fact that the hon. Member had assisted in the numerous consultations which had been held for the purpose of practically improving the Bill, notwithstanding that the hon. Member represented that great evils would attend the stopping of so beneficial a measure. He (Mr. Parnell), for one, would very much like to ask the hon. Member for a fuller explanation of what his views really were.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he certainly did not say the concession was worthless. At any rate, he had no intention of going further than saying that it was not satisfactory.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he must confess he would like to find some way of carrying the Motion without going to a division. The right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland seemed to think that no one but himself was dinnerless; but he (Mr. Parnell) could assure the right hon. Gentleman that many of them had had nothing to eat since breakfast. He would not press that argument, because he thought all the Irish Members were very ready to vote fasting; in fact, Irishmen were generally understood to be able to fight without anything to eat, whilst Englishmen and Scotchmen always required to be well fed. But as regarded those two clauses, he really thought it would be a great waste of time going into them that night. As the right hon. Gentleman had said, the fishery piers and his own proposal of grants to Boards of Guardians were, in his opinion, the only important parts of the Bill.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he was quite aware that the right hon. Gentleman did not. He only gave it as his own opinion. Although he did not think it was a very wonderful concession to have the option of giving to the people of Ireland £200,000 of their own money, when they were going to give£l,500,000 of their own money to the landlords, still, of course, it was a concession, and he was happy to admit it. However, since the 3rd and 4th clauses—which he was really not clear that they ought to have come into any relief of distress Bill, and which would take an enormous deal of time to lick into shape—if, indeed, they could be licked into shape, which he very much doubted—since those clauses were to be postponed, he was, personally, perfectly willing to go on with the Bill for any reasonable time; and perhaps, under those circumstances, the hon. Member for Waterford (Mr. E. Power) would reconsider his Motion.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, it appeared from the remarks of the noble Lord (Lord Frederick Cavendish) that the Treasury would be threatened with bankruptcy in case that grant were increased to £45,000. That only showed to what desperate devices hon. Gentlemen might be driven in order to avoid any increase of expenditure. He did think that such a sum as £45,000 was a poor miserable sum considering what was required to be spent on the West Coast of Ireland. The Inspectors of Fisheries had recommended that some harbours should be built. They asked for that purpose for a Vote of £45,000, and £15,000 was to be given by Canada and Liverpool, making a total of £60,000, and that was all that could be obtained, in order that the fishermen might reap the magnificent harvest that Providence sent them. As a measure for the relief of distress it was equally miserable. He was sorry that the noble Lord the Secretary to the Treasury had not seen his way to be more generous in that matter. £45,000 was a poor contribution out of the Exchequer for the relief of distress. It was not what they might have expected from a great country, and he thought that they should have received a sum equal to the emergency—say £100,000. It would not ruin England to give a grant of that kind, and the advantage and benefit of it to the poor fishermen on the Western Coast of Ireland would render them perfectly satisfied. Upon studying the question he had become so convinced of the great necessity that existed for a larger sum of money to be expended that he had placed upon the Notice Paper, the previous night, a new clause, in order to enable the sum of £250,000 to be given for that purpose out of the Church Surplus Fund, and he hoped that when the time came for considering that clause the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland (Mr. Forster) would see his way to agree to it. He knew of no purpose to which the Church Surplus Fund could be better put than in national works of that kind, and thus to improve the industrial resources of the country, and increase the wage-earning power, and so relieve those who were then dependent upon relief Committees for their daily bread. He had merely referred incidentally to his own clause, which he hoped to introduce. Looking at the history of the distress in Ireland, he was afraid to think what the state of things would have been had it not been for the magnificent contributions they had received from the United States and far-off Australia. He trusted that the Government would not limit their contributions to the miserable grant of £45,000.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, what would be the effect of adopting the first Amendment and not the second one? It appeared to him, in that case, the work would be stopped, and not proceeded with.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL moved, in sub-section 2, after the word "money," to insert "under the provisions of this section."</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he wished to move the rejection of sub-section 3.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL would move to omit those words. It was not necessary to go over the arguments which had already been adduced in favour of placing upon the Consolidated Fund the difference between two rates of interest; but an important alteration had been made by the Amendment of the Chief Secretary. Under the Belief Bill of last Session the money borrowed by Boards of Guardians for the purposes of out-door relief was borrowed from the Exchequer. It was now proposed to be borrowed from the Irish Church Fund, and to that he objected. He wished to have it borrowed, as it was now, from the Imperial funds.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, there might have been a loss to the public funds, independent of the interest which, by the change, would now have to be borne by the Church Surplus Fund. It sometimes happened, and it might happen in this case, that some of the Boards of Guardians might not be able to repay the loans, and to that extent the Church Surplus Fund would be a loser instead of the Exchequer. To that extent, a difference had been caused by the adoption of the clause of the right hon. Gentleman. Under the Act of last Session, if any Board of Guardians became bankrupt, as they did in 1847–8, so as to be Tillable to repay the advances to the Treasury, the public funds would have been the loser; but now, under the alteration made by the right hon. Gentleman, the Church Surplus Fund would be the loser. He trusted the right hon. Gentleman would consider the advisability of inserting a new clause, by which the risk of that loss might be taken from that Fund. It was manifestly not fair to put it upon it, for it was not originally intended to do so. It was decided in the last Act that the money should be lent out of the Consolidated Fund; and, consequently, it should bear any loss that might possibly result from the non-payment of the Boards of Guardians. He (Mr. Parnell) thought it would be fair, under all the circumstances, to propose a new clause, which would prevent such loss being thrown upon the Church Surplus Fund.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL moved, after Clause 8, to insert the following Clauses:— The Commissioners of Public Works may, from time to time, out of the said sum of one million five hundred thousand pounds, payable to them by the Commissioners of Church Temporalities, apply any sums not exceeding in all the sum of two hundred and fifty thousand pounds for the purposes of the Fishery Piers Act, to be expended in the manner therein mentioned, but subject to the conditions and exceptions hereinafter mentioned. Upon the publication by the Commissioners in the 'Dublin Gazette' or otherwise, as they shall think fit, of a notice of their intention to undertake any work which may be executed under the Fishery Piers Act, such notice shall be instead of and shall have all the force and effect of the final notice mentioned in the sixteenth section of the Fishery Piers Act. Before publishing such notice, the Commissioners may, if they think fit, do any matter or thing, and shall have, and may if they think tit, exercise any right, power, or authority in connection with such work, which they might do or would have with reference to any of the proceedings preliminary to the publication of the final notice mentioned in the Fishery Piers Act if the work were undertaken in strict compliance with the said Act. The provisions contained in the following sections of the Fishery Piers Act (that is to say); section four, sub-section four, section five, and sections ten to fifteen, both included, relative to proceedings preliminary to the publication of such notice, shall not apply to any such work.</p>
         <p>(Power to undertake works.)</p>
         <p>"At any time notice after the publication by the Commissioners of Public Works of any such notice as is mentioned in this Act, the Commissioners may commence and proceed with the works proposed to be executed and to which such notice relates.</p>
         <p>"The Commissioners may, if they think fit, do any matter or thing, and shall have and may, if they think fit, exercise any right, power, or authority with reference to such work, which they might do or would have if the work were undertaken in strict compliance with the Fishery Piers Act, and all the enactments contained in that Act, save so far as they are modified by this Act, shall apply as nearly as may be with reference to any such work."</p>
         <p>(Management and maintenance of works when constructed.)</p>
         <p>"When such work has been constructed, all the provisions of the Fishery Piers Act and of the Act of the Session of Parliament held in the sixteenth and seventeenth years of the reign of Her present Majesty, chapter one hundred and thirty-six, as amended by any Act or Acts, shall apply to such work as if it was a pier constructed in strict compliance with the Fishery Piers Act."</p>
         <p>The hon. Member said, he trusted the Government would carry out the new clause he had placed upon the Paper last night. He regretted he was unable to give longer Notice; but he had intended to bring in a Bill in reference to the matter, and finally came to the conclusion it would be more convenient to propose a clause in connection with the Bill under discussion. The Committee was aware they had agreed to grant the sum of £45,000 out of the Imperial Exchequer in aid of the construction of fishery piers and harbours on the West Coast of Ireland. As many as 70 piers and harbours had been recommended by the Commissioners as urgently required; and in order really to develop the harbours and piers on the West and South Coasts of Ireland, it was necessary that they should have a very much larger grant. He asked, by these clauses, to allow them to have some of the Church Surplus Fund for that natural object. The hon. Member for the County Waterford (Mr. Blake), who was for many years Inspector of Fisheries in Ireland, and had fulfilled his duties in a most satisfactory manner, had assisted him (Mr. Parnell) in framing these clauses, and from his practical knowledge of the operation of the Fishery Piers Act of 1847, he assured him that they would work perfectly with that Act. They would enable the Board of Works in Ireland to undertake the construction of fishery piers and harbours, which they could undertake by the Act of 1847, without the necessity of any local contribution. The Act of 1847 allocated a grant of £50,000 for Fishery Piers and Harbours in the West. It provided that a contribution of one-fourth was necessary from local sources. That had usually been found by baronial grants; but, owing to the repugnance of the ratepayers to burden themselves more, it had been impossible to get these. He proposed to dispense with the necessity of a fourth, and the red tape required by the Act of 1847, and enable the Board of Works to undertake the construction of the fishery piers and harbours which were so much needed. He had every confidence in recommending the application of some of the Church Surplus Fund for this purpose. It would be most difficult to point out a work more urgently needed than the construction of these harbours. It was quite impossible to hope that they could be constructed without this system, for the West Coast of Ireland was far removed from civilization; it had no resident landlords, and the people were left in a sort of wild state to subsist in the best way they could, without anyone to look after their interests; and it would be of the greatest advantage to the teeming population if a grant such as he proposed were made to get on with some of the 70 piers and harbours which had been recommended by the Fishery Inspectors. Some of the piers and harbours constructed in 1847 had fallen out of repair and were now useless, so that very much was needed to develop the fisheries. He asked the Committee, with the utmost confidence, to agree to the second reading. The Irish Members, he believed were almost unanimous in its favour, and thought that no application of the money would be more advantageous to the country.</p>
         <p>New Clause (Mr. Parnell) brought up, and read a first time.</p>
         <p>Motion made, and Question proposed, "That the Clause be now read a second time."</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL thought there was some force in the objections which had been urged on the other side to grants being taken at such short notice, more especially as it would appear to raise the question of the allocating of the Church Surplus Funds, and their distribution among the industries of Ireland; but the proposition of the hon. Member for Lei-trim (Mr. Tottenham) did not fall under these objections. The amount which had been allocated by this Bill—one of the most useful the Bill contained next to that of £200,000 for assisting the Poor Law Unions in giving out-door relief—that for harbours and fishery piers was a very small one, and when that question was under discussion the Irish Members urged the desirability of increasing it. This was impressed on the Government; but the noble Lord the Secretary to the Treasury was unwilling, he said, in view of the Budget proposals, to recommend an increase. Taken with the Liverpool and the Canadian funds it would amount to £60,000. This was a very small thing for the assistance of the Fisheries of the West Coast. It would go a very little way, and he was afraid it would raise expectations among the fishermen which, in nine cases out of ten, would be doomed to disappointment. Now, if power were given to the Commissioners to take from the Church Surplus Fund £60,000 in addition to the £60,000 already granted for piers and harbours, it would make something of a little gift to the West Coast Fisheries. Although there was a great deal of force in the objection of the hon. Member for Limerick (Mr. Synan) that a considerable portion of this must go in materials, though not so much as he seemed to think, yet nothing he (Mr. Parnell) believed would do more to relieve the poverty and privations during the coming winter than affording such facilities to these fishing stations. In many instances they had no harbours, but only little boat slips. It would encourage the men to hold on and fight through the winter. He would ask the right hon. Gentleman to consider this. He did not know whether it was the intention to finish the Bill that night; but if not he would ask leave to withdraw his clause for the present, in order that it might be fully considered in the interval between then and the next Sitting of the Committee; that the right hon. Gentleman might consider whether or not he would give, say £60,000, so as to make something of a little gift to these little harbours of the West Coast. This would not trench much on the Church Surplus, and it would be something out of the £1,500,000, which he felt sure would do a great deal of good. The question had been thoroughly inquired into, the harbours were well known. The Board of Works would know perfectly well where the works were to be constructed, and he felt sure it would be an enormous assistance.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, yes: he proposed to withdraw his clauses in order to give the right hon. Gentleman a little time for consideration, for a very short Notice had been given of them.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL did not think the clause, as moved, would be found of a workable description. In order to set it in motion, some scheme would have to be provided. At all events, the outlines of the scheme would have to be embodied in a set of clauses, for it would be quite impossible to set in motion the clause as it stood. He had been thinking about the best means of meeting the object of the clause, and had intended, if it had not been so late in the season, if the urgency had not been so great, and if they had not had other concessions of a valuable character from the right hon. Gentleman, he had intended to move a set of clauses in the Bill which would have enabled the Committee, at all events, to discuss the subject properly. However, he did not wish to detain the Committee with the clauses he had proposed to move. He would have constituted the county surveyor to assist, in conjunction with the Poor Law Boards, in the machinery for carrying into effect the provisions of the clause. He would have proposed that power should be given to Boards of Guardians to make advances to occupiers of land, and that they should borrow money, to be so advanced on the security of the rates, and that the money should be recovered from occupiers in the shape of rates. Therefore, this money would be the first charge on their holdings. He would propose that the county surveyor should be appointed as the authority for checking the Poor Law Boards in their allocation of the advances. That would have given the county surveyor the veto, as regarded any work proposed. He had the clauses there; but he did not propose to read them, for he had abandoned all intention of moving them some time ago. But, in that way, a simple machinery would be provided for carrying into effect the object of the hon. Member for Waterford County (Mr. Villiers Stuart), the county surveyor acting as a check on the Poor Law Board, as to the work to be undertaken. But now, as the season had got so late, it would be useless for immediate relief; and as he was assured that, should the distress continue next winter, the Chief Secretary for Ireland intended to adopt sweeping measures to cope with it, then there would be an opportunity of raising the question again. He did not see the slightest practical use in persevering with the clause now.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, it might be left until the time came for dealing with the clause of the hon. Member for Limerick (Mr. Synan). That was the only other important clause on the Paper with the exception of the "Suspension of Ejectments" Clause in the name of the hon. Member for Cavan (Mr. Biggar), which he (Mr. Parnell) thought had better be left to be moved as an Amendment to the Government Land Bill. So far as he could see, the only important part of the Business remaining was the clause of his hon. Friend; but, of course, if a discussion was raised upon that, they ought not to go on that night.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, before coming to those clauses, there was an important point to be settled in reference to the Seeds Act. He believed the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland (Mr. W. E. Forster) undertook to bring up a new clause.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, there was also the hon. Member for Limerick's (Mr. Synan's) clause as to limitation of time, and his (Mr. Parnell's) own little matter about the £60,000. He supposed the right hon. Gentleman did not intend to finish the Committee that night; and, therefore, he would be content to allow the three questions he had named to remain until the Committee resumed. He, therefore, now moved to report Progress.</p>
         <p>Motion made, and Question proposed, "That the Chairman do report Progress, and ask leave to sit again."— (Mr. Parnell.)</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL inquired whether it would be possible to move any other clauses when the Committee resumed?</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, it was only 20 minutes past 12, and he thought they might go on with the Registration of Voters (Ireland) Bill, and take a step in that; and there was also the Municipal Franchise (Ireland) Bill. They were both opposed Orders; and if they had not an opportunity of taking them now, they might not be able to get them any other night.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
