<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The Government of Ireland, The Home-Rule Bill, The Standard, Friday 9 April 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The Government of Ireland, The Home-Rule Bill</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="182249744" level="j">The Standard</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-04-09">9 April 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00052"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">   
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url=""></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, who was received with enthusiastic cheers from the Irish benches, said:- Mr. Speaker, - I am glad to find that we have not been disappointed by the lobby rumours which have been circulated for some days past regarding the right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs, and that he is, after all, like the celebrated but unsuccessful French general who defended Paris from the Germans, and who had got his own plan (laughter); and that he did not think the hour too late at the close of his interesting, but not very fair, speech to give us the details of his important plan (laughter). But I notice it as somewhat significant, although it must have been a rather discouraging fact to the right hon. gentleman, that the gradual unfolding of his plan elicited no enthusiasm of any account from any section of the House (dissent from the Conservative benches), and that it was not until he had pointedly appealed to hon. members of the Conservative Party that at last some small section of them would give him a cheer or two, and that he did succeed in getting some faint applause from a few gentlemen around the Conservative gangway. The Conservative Party has always been most remarkable for its discipline; and, undoubtedly, in its reception of the plan of the Prime Minister, it had in its mind the declaration of the noble Lord (Lord R. Churchill) when he announced in a speech some two or three years ago, that they should concede nothing more to the Irish Nationalists, neither in the direction of local self-government, county boards, nor anything else (hear, hear). Of course, the rank and file of the Conservative Party, under these circumstances, could not have ventured to have applauded the right hon. gentleman the members for the Border Burghs and broken away from their allegiance to the noble Lord. I shall be told, perhaps, that the noble Lord has improved since those days (hear, hear). Some say that has caused so much consternation in the mind of the right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan). I know nothing about these things (laughter), and I shall not express any opinion upon them. But I do think that the right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan), in the attempted comparison which he appeared to draw between the action of Lord Spencer in remaining in the Cabinet and his own action in leaving it - to Lord Spencer's disadvantage - scarcely stood on very firm or satisfactory ground (Irish cheers). Englishmen love a man who fights his own corner out to the end, which Lord Spencer certainly did (cheers). He went over to Ireland to fight out a battle which was not his - to fight the battle of the Irish landlords - and he stuck to his post (cheers). He faced every danger, every risk, both physical and otherwise, but the right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan) did something very like running away from his post (some Liberal cries of "No, no"). although he attempted to explain to the House his reason for leaving the Cabinet, he did not try to explain to the House why he left his position as Chief Secretary (cheers). Does the right hon. gentleman propose, in the event of his plan being carried out, to compete for the office of Chief Secretary, and if he be not willing to resume that office himself, is it very chivalrous in him to open such a door for future aspirants? (hear, hear.) The right hon. gentleman attempted to prove to the house what terrible things we should do in our Irish Parliament by allusions to a Motion which I moved in 1883. Mr. Speaker, I do not desire to go back over old quarrels. It generally happens that those who are defeated like to recur to these distant and unhappy recollections, but I have nothing to retract (cheers). The right hon. gentleman read that Resolution to the House, which complained of the execution and imprisonment of innocent men. I believed then, as I believe now, that innocent men were executed (cheers). I never accused the right hon gentleman or Lord Spencer of having believed the same thing. I did not accuse them of having executed innocent men knowing they were innocent. But I can scarcely think that the right hon. gentleman thinks so to-day (hear). How about the case of Brian Kilmartin who was sentenced to penal servitude - for life, I believe - and who, on his case being brought forward, supported by the noble Lord (Lord R. Churchill) and by one or two other prominent Conservatives, was released during, I believe, the tenure of office of the right honourable gentleman himself? (Irish cheers.) The right hon. gentleman taunts us with the language of that Resolution, and with the language of the manifesto which was issued by my hon. friend the member for the Scotland Division of Liverpool. But if I considered that these things had taken place, was I not right, at the very height of this reign of terror which then existed in Ireland, in stating so publicly? (hear, hear.) I do not see how, with any sort of regard for my duty, not only to my constituents, but my public duty as regards the question of law and order in Ireland, which the right hon. gentleman has constituted himself the sole champion of to-night - I do not see how I could have refrained from bringing this matter under the notice of the House. While the right hon. gentleman places such a weighty argument against us in regard to the Resolution to which he has referred and to the manifesto of my hon. friend, he passes over language which has been used since then in Ireland by a very prominent member of the late Administration (hear, hear) - a man who was specially charged with the maintenance of law in that country. I mean the late Attorney General for Ireland (Home-rule cheers), who asserted at a public meeting that "the blood of Giffen was on the head of Lord Spencer." The right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs has no censure for that language (cheers). Surely no language that was ever used by any of my hon. friends exceeded in gravity the charge contained in these words; and certainly the language used in the Resolution and in the manifesto of my hon. friend (Mr. T. P. O'Connor) was mildness itself in comparison (cheers). If this question is to be discussed in the temper - I will not say the ill feeling - shown by the right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs, it will undoubtedly not tend to decrease the irritation and ill-feeling between the two countries (hear, hear). But I hope the example of the right hon. gentleman will not be imitated (cheers). I do not wish to go into the justification of our action in the last Parliament. I could do so if I wished. I could remind the House of the agencies used by the right hon. member for the Border Burghs in the upholding of law and order in Ireland. I could remind him of the result of the trial of French's case - a director of the Royal Irish Constabulary, a man whom the right hon. gentleman did not shrink from defending in his place (Home-rule cheers). But I do not desire to go into these matters. I believe, however, that history will recall that in every Resolution we moved in reference to the administration in Ireland during his time of office we were more than amply justified by the terrible circumstances surrounding the country at that time (hear, hear). The right hon. gentleman has spoken of assassination literature, and of sympathy with Ireland in America. He has spoken of Mr. Ford as having conveyed that sympathy to this country, the fact being that Mr. Ford constantly denounced myself and my policy for several years (cheers). This assassination literature has not been American nor purely Irish, but there has been a sympathy in America for the just settlement of the claims of Ireland to the cession of domestic legislation, and that sympathy has been shared by all classes in that country, whether Irish or native-born (cheers). The right hon. gentleman took exception to the proposal to buy out the Irish landlords (cheers and laughter) - a measure which, if he had succeeded in passing, and it had been successful, would have involved the payment of a very large sum of money for the purpose. With regard to the picture the right hon. gentleman drew of the possible consequences that will result to Ireland and to England if any proposal such as that now suggested should be adopted, I can only say that I believe that, so far from anything of the kind happening, the guarantees for a peaceable solution of the difficulties between the two countries will be enormously increased. And why? For several reasons. Why is there trouble in Ireland now? Why do some talk of separation? Why does my hon. friend the member for Tyrone write in what the right hon. gentleman sometimes describes as violent passages in United Ireland [italics]? It is because the people are desperate, and have got nothing to lose (Home-rule cheers). But if they have a Constitution they will be proportionately careful not to lose it, and every violent speech and every criminal action will be so many nails in the coffin of that Constitution (cheers). You will have this in addition to every guarantee you have now for the preservation of peace and order in the country. But I now pass to the consideration of the Bill (hear, hear). It is difficult to express a definite and positive opinion with regard to a Bill before it is in print and I should like to reserve all positive expression of opinion with regard to this measure until I have seen it, which I suppose will be on Monday. But I think it right that I should say something about its merits as explained by the right hon. gentleman the member for Midlothian. I hope it will prove to be a happy and fortunate thing both for Ireland and for England that there was one man living - one English statesman found of the great power and extraordinary ability of the right hon. gentleman to lend his voice to poor helpless Ireland on this question (cheers) - to devote his great mind and extraordinary energy to the unravelling of this problem. It seems to many people that the task may prove too large (hear, hear), too terrible. I believe it will not be so (cheers). But whatever the fate of the Bill, the cause of Ireland, the cause of Irish autonomy will have gained enormously, in a way it would not otherwise have gained, by the genius of the right hon. gentleman (cheers). To Ireland, to none of the sons of Ireland at any time has there ever been given the genius and talent of the right hon. gentleman for the energy and time he has devoted to this measure, and I believe sincerely in my heart that the result of it will be that the people of England would recognise as the result of what he has done, no less than the people of Ireland, that he had been to them a national benefactor (cheers). But there are undoubtedly great faults and blots in the measure. He has had to meet very hostile criticism, and a very extraordinary state of affairs. He has seen his officers leaving his side one by one and drawing their swords upon him, as the member for the Border Burghs had done to-night (hear, hear), and he has had, I suppose, to shape his measure to meet the tremendous opposition which has been invoked against him. But there are several points which it will be our duty in Committee to oppose very strongly, and press for the serious modification and amendment of. The question of customs has been touched upon. In giving up the customs we would practically give up the control of three-fourths of the revenue of Ireland. The right hon. gentleman has explained to us that if we insist upon separate custom-houses England would deprive Ireland, by collecting duties on whiskey and tobacco, of customs amounting to 1,400,000/. per annum. This is a very serious consideration, and it may be fairly balanced against the concession of customs and excise. But at the same time, if the right hon. gentleman is to claim credit for giving us that 1,400,000/. as a consequence of the surrender of these customs and excise, I do not think he was also entitled to claim credit for it a second time a little later on, and to make us pay out of the 1,400,000/. a million a year for the Irish Constabulary, over whom we are to have no sort of control whatever. There is also the very grave question of the contribution to the Imperial Empire. I cannot admit either the justness or the liberality of the standard of comparison which the right hon. gentleman has taken. It appears to me that the amount of property which comes under assessment regarding the payment of legacy and succession duty is the most unfavourable standard which could have been chosen. It must be remembered that Ireland is a very poor country, and with such a small balance of 400,000/. a year on the Budget it would be absolutely impossible for Ireland to have any credit in the direction of floating loans. We are now able to borrow from the Treasury large sums of money for various purposes in Ireland. Irish landlords can borrow at a low rate of interest for the improvement of their estates; Irish tenants can borrow for the purpose of improving their farms; local authorities can borrow for sanitary purposes within their jurisdiction. All these are very important matters, but we shall have to surrender all these (Opposition cries of "Hear, hear"). Yes; we shall have to surrender all these under the scheme, and we shall be left with a Budget which only exceeded the annual balance by about 400,000/.  A year, and a Budget arrived at on an estimate which necessitates that the consumption of spirits, not only in Ireland, but also in England, should continue at its present high rate. Of course one of the first things that would happen in Ireland, in an Irish Legislature, would be a restriction regarding the sale of strong drink on Sundays and other days, and certainly we must anticipate, and I hope we can anticipate, a considerable reduction of the amount of revenue derived from these duties. Therefore it is scarcely fair to press us too closely, or to insist on driving too hard a bargain. If the sum is agreed upon, of course we must pay. We must pay it, and we will pay it (Home-rule cheers); but it would be most unfortunate if the election of such a standard as that which the right hon. gentleman has chosen should be the future poverty of the Irish Exchequer. I have every confidence that when the time comes in Committee the conscience of the Prime Minister will be touched on this matter, and that he will see that his zeal for making a good bargain for his own country on the question of the Imperial contribution has misled him into an attempt to do an unintentional act of injustice to Ireland. I think, also, that the question of the Royal Irish Constabulary has been left in a most unsatisfactory position. It is most unfair to ask us to pay for a force over which we have no control whatever. But this is a matter on which more light will be thrown when we have seen the Bill. Then there is another important matter in regard to voting by orders. This would give the first order, the 28 Peers and those elected by fancy franchises, the power of hanging up any measure for three years, or until a dissolution, and so bringing the whole proceedings of the Legislature to a deadlock. So far as the first order went in securing rash, hasty, or ill-considered legislation, I heartily welcomed it; but, so far as it goes or could be made to act as obstruction, more or less permanent, to legislation, and be a means of bringing about a deadlock on the part of a body of members who can scarcely be said to be representative, it ought to be seriously modified, so as to render such a delay as that impossible. As regarded the measure itself, the Prime Minister had truly said that it ought not to be proceeded with unless it were cheerfully welcomed, not only by the Irish members, but by the Irish people. For his own part, he was convinced that if the views of Irish members were fairly met in Committee regarding the defects to which he alluded, the results of the working of the measure would be to agreeably disappoint the right hon. member (Mr. Trevelyan) and all those who thought with him. The Bill would be cheerfully accepted by the Irish people and by their representatives as a solution of the long-standing dispute between the two countries, and it would lead to the prosperity and peace of Ireland, as well as to the satisfaction of England (Home-rule cheers).</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
