<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Mr. Parnell at Portsmouth, The Times, Saturday 26 June 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Mr. Parnell at Portsmouth</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-06-26">26 June 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00077"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">  
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url=""></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, who was received with loud and prolonged cheering, said, - I do not know whether at the commencement I ought not to render to you an apology for trespassing into the domain of English politics. It is, I believe, about the first time that I have had the honour of addressing a mainly English audience, and I have been induced to do so now because I rely greatly on the spirit of fairplay among the English masses (cheers), and because the issues for my country are so great and so vital at the present moment. The Irishman who remains silent when it might be possible to do something to help his country would be more unworthy than tongue could describe. Mr. Gladstone (cheers) was right when he said that this battle was the soldiers' battle. Is not this great meeting a verification of his words? It is the people's battle; it is the soldiers' battle; and upon the justice of the masses of the British people we rely. (Hear, hear.) I have in my career as a member of Parliament never willingly injured the cause of the English working men. (Cheers.) I have done something to show my sympathy for the masses of the people of this country. To take as an illustration. I will select for a moment the question of the abolition of flogging in the Army. (Hear, hear.) Seven or eight years ago it was my privilege to strike with English members a successful blow in favour of the abolition of flogging in the Army and the Navy. We were then met with the very same arguments as we are met with to-day, and from the same class of persons. It was said by the late Lord Beaconsfield (hisses) that the integrity of the British Empire would be endangered if flogging were abolished (laughter), and he called a great meeting at one of the Ministerial offices in London, a great meeting of his supporters both in the Lords and in the Commons, for the purpose of exhorting them to stand shoulder to shoulder in defence of the British Empire against the abolition of flogging in the Army. (Laughter.) Well, we abolished flogging in the Army and Navy, in spite of the Tories, and in spite of Lord Hartington and Lord Salisbury, all of whom were then leagued together as defenders of the lash (cheers); and we shall win this battle too. (Loud cheers.) I am here to-night for the purpose of endeavouring with my poor voice, which I am afraid hardly penetrates this great meeting, to brush away some of the clouds of prejudice that have been cast before your eyes to prevent you, if it were possible, from seeing the truth. Now, what is the settlement which Mr. Gladstone and his Government have offered us, which we have accepted as a final settlement (loud cheers), and which five-sixths of the Irish people in a few days hence at the poll will accept as a final settlement. You were told that not only the integrity of the Empire, but the supremacy of the Imperial Parliament would be endangered. I shall show you neither one nor the other will be harmed. The statutory Legislature which we have accepted is not, like Grattan's Parliament, a supreme, co-ordinate Parliament, but it is a subordinate one. (Hear, hear.) The Legislature that we have accepted will have only power to deal with exclusively Irish business. (Hear, hear.) Grattan's Parliament had power to deal with Imperial affairs, and it repeatedly exercised that power. It had power to object to foreign wars undertaken by Great Britain. It had separate powers to address the Crown against these wars. It had power to refuse supplies for the maintenance of the Army and Navy. The new Legislature will have none of these powers, but we shall have a more valuable power for our own interests, exclusively apart from Imperial affairs, which Grattan's had not. We shall have the power of appointing and controlling our own Executive Government (hear, hear), and no Legislature, no Parliament is worth a rush or can secure the respect of those whom it governs unless it has that power which it is proposed to be given to us under Mr. Gladstone's Bill. (Hear, hear.) I have shown you that in some respects the Irish settlement proposed by Mr. Gladstone does not give a Parliament with powers possessed by Grattan's Parliament, but, on the other hand, that as regards our own exclusively domestic business it gives larger powers, more important powers, more valuable powers for Ireland itself than Grattan's Parliament possessed. (Hear, hear.) Therefore we think that this settlement proposed by Mr. Gladstone will prove a more durable settlement than the restitution of Grattan's Parliament or the repeal of the Union would prove. (Cheers.) Now there is one point which it is very important, that you should bear in your minds and carry away with you, and that point is - that Imperial unity does not necessitate or require unity of Parliaments. (Cheers.) Will you carry away with you, and remember it, because it is the keystone of our whole proceedings. You have an example in your own Colonies. You have ever so many Colonial legislatures, and yet you have Imperial unity. There is no demand, no fear of separation from the Colonies, although each one of them has an independent Legislature, so far as their own business is concerned. Take again the example of the United States of America. There are 38 Legislatures in the United States, each of them with more power than it is proposed to give to the Irish Legislature (hear, hear); and yet there is no danger of the separation of one State from another, or of the separation of all of the States from the central Federal Government, which corresponds to the Imperial authority in this country (hear, hear); and you would have if you gave us this settlement, and if separation were ever attempted in Ireland - as it was attempted by some of the States of the American Union some years ago - you would have that moral power to put down that separation which the people of America possessed and used successfully, and which you have not now in your dealings with Ireland. Well, then, so far as the United States are concerned, separation of Legislatures has brought about federal union, and not only brought it about, but has maintained it. So far as your colonies are concerned, separation of Legislatures has brought about Imperial unity at a time when Imperial unity was in danger. When a rebellion existed in Canada you quenched that rebellion by giving a separate Legislature to Canada, and you have continued on these lines from that day to this; so that not only have separate colonial Legislatures not brought about separation, but they have prevented separation. But really, people of Portsmouth, this talk about separation is the hollowest and most absurd talk that was ever given utterance to. (Cheers.) The men who raised this bogey, this bugbear, of separation before your eyes as a reason against conceding the just demands of the Irish people know perfectly well that there is not the slightest danger or risk of separation. How can Ireland separate from England? According to these loyal and patriotic Unionists, out of five millions of the Irish people two millions are what they call loyal. If they are loyal, how can the remaining three millions, even if you give Mr. Gladstone's settlement, bring about separation, not only against the two millions, but against the millions of Great Britain? (Cheers.) The thing is preposterous and absurd from beginning to end, and it is an appeal to cowardice. (Cheers.) It would be the verist cowardice for the great British people, with dominions upon which the sun never sets, to fear to do justice to a small people few in number like the Irish merely on account of this ridiculous cry. But then, finding that the talk about separation does not hold water, another cry is got up about the danger of the Protestant minority. I think some of their speakers go so far as to say that the lives and limbs of some of the Protestant minority are in danger under the present state of affairs (laughter), as in Belfast the other day, when some Orangemen began wrecking the houses of the Catholics (hisses and "Shame") and came into collision with the police. They found they were in danger, but why were they in danger? It was because they broke the law. Nobody in Ireland who observes the law under the new order of things will find that they are in danger of either life or limb. (Hear, hear.) There are 1,200,000 Protestants in Ireland of all denominations, including those who have no religion at all. I am a Protestant myself. (Cheers.) I know them very well. I believe from experience that the truth of the matter about the feeling of the Protestant minority is this, that the great majority of them do not feel very strongly upon the question one way or the other. They would rather, I think, of the two that things were left as they are, but certainly they have no fear of the Catholics of Ireland. There is a small minority of Protestants strongly in favour of Mr. Gladstone's settlement (cheers), and there is another small minority of Protestants, of Orangemen in the North of Ireland, who are strongly opposed to Mr. Gladstone's settlement. (Hisses.) That is how the matter stands. It is this small minority who are strongly opposed to Mr. Gladstone's settlement who have raised this question about the Protestant minority who are strongly opposed to Mr. Gladstone's settlement who have raised this question about the Protestant minority, and they ask you either to reject the Bill altogether or else to insert provisions in the Bill which will give special protection to what they call the Protestant minority. Well, I do not see how their claim is to be successful unless you reject the Bill altogether. I do not see how you can insert any other provisions than those which already exist in the Bill in the shape of the first order for the protection of the Protestant minority. (Cheers.) Under the system of the first order it would be possible for the Protestant minority to hang up any Bill they objected to for three years before it could possibly pass into law; and before the end of that three years if the Irish Legislature passed enactments oppressive to the Protestants of Ireland it would be possible for the Imperial Parliament to intervene and take away the settlement it would have given. (Cheers.) If the Irish Legislature did pass enactments in the slightest degree oppressive of the Protestants of Ireland, I should say that Ireland would justly deserve to lose her privilege. (Hear, hear.) But the difficulties about protecting the Protestant minority in any other way than those already existing in the Bill are enormous. One proposal was that there should be a separate Legislature for Ulster. Now a separate Legislature for Ulster would leave 400,000 outside Ulster without the protection of that Legislature, and only 800,000 Protestants within the province could possibly get that protection. (Hear, hear.) But, in addition to this, the Nationalists are in a majority in the province of Ulster. (Cheers.) They have returned the majority of Ulster members, and will return them again. (Cheers.) The result of the establishment of a separate Legislature for Ulster would be that the first, the only, and the last Act that would be passed by that Legislature would be one united itself with the rest of Ireland (cheers); so that, as you will see, Ulster cannot be protected as they want to have her protected by the establishment of a separate Legislature. They have seen themselves - I speak of the opponents of the Bill - the fallacy of this, and they now claim that the north-east corner of Ulster shall be protected. I do not know whether there is light enough in this hall for you to see what I wish to show you, but the map is one that represents Ireland, and this little yellow patch covered by my forefinger represents Protestant Ulster (cheers); and they say now that they want a separate Parliament for this little yellow patch up in the north-east. (Laughter.) But the majority of the Irish Protestants live outside this little yellow patch. Only five-twelfths of the Protestants live inside it, and the other seven-twelfths live outside it; so that it is these five-twelfths who live inside this north-east corner who want to have a Legislature set up for themselves and to leave the majority of their fellow-countrymen unprotected to us outside. (Hear, hear.) It would be like the garrison of a city which, finding itself hardly beleaguered, sought refuge within the citadel, and left the rest of the population of the city to be massacred. So you see, take it as you will, you will not protect them as they want - you will not protect the minority in Ireland by giving them a separate Legislature for Ulster. Unless you reject the Bill altogether there is no way in which you can effectually yield to the wishes of the small minority of Protestants. I am very sorry for having detained you so long (Cries of "Go on"), for I am afraid that it has been impossible for me to make my voice heard to any but a very small proportion of this enormous meeting, the largest indoor meeting I have ever addressed in my life. (Cheers and a voice. - "How about Lord Carnarvon?") But I should like to consider with you for a moment what are the alternatives to Mr. Gladstone's plan, that offer of settlement. (Cries of "None.") There is one other alternative, there is the alternative of coercion (hisses) - coercion continued, as Lord Salisbury has claimed (groans), for 20 years. Well, it has gone on for 700 years already, and things are not any better, and you are not any nearer to the end of the Irish question. (Cries of "We are.") So far as coercion is concerned, it has not brought you any nearer to the end of the Irish question; but what sort of coercion must it be? It must be all the acts of coercion that you ever employed against Ireland rolled into one, and sternly employed, as Lord Salisbury has said, for 20 years. (Groans.) But you must have a very good understanding with Lord Salisbury that when he gets into office he does not forget all about this talk about coercion. (Laughter.) It is a great mistake to suppose that the coercion which has been used for Ireland has been used against criminals and against the breakers of the law. One great fault in English coercion of Ireland has been that, no matter what your intentions have been when you had commenced coercion, you have never discriminated between political agitation and between the breaking up of the law. (Hear, hear.) Ministers have got Coercion Acts from Parliament as the late Mr. Forster (some hisses and cheers) got his Coercion Act - namely, on the promise that they should only be used against cattle-maimers and against doers of evil deeds and of violence. But what did Mr. Forster do? He used it against his political opponents and against none other, and as a proof of that I would remind you that the 1,000 men who were arrested and kept, many of them for 20 months, in prison without trial - hardly two dozen of them were ever put upon their trial or accused of any offence (cries of "Shame") - the cast majority of them were arrested for open speaking and for nothing else. That has always been the experience of English Coercion Acts in Ireland. You pass them with the honest intention of using them only against the breakers of the law. But excitement and political passion arise, and under the influence of excitement an political passion no statesman, however eminent, is to be trusted to use exceptional laws. These laws have always been abused, and they always will be abused. Well, you will have to go further in Ireland than you have ever gone before. I am not one of those who believe that you cannot put down political agitation for a time by 20 years' coercion as Lord Salisbury proposes to use it. (Groans.) I believe that you can put down political agitation, you can silence us in Ireland by our silence in the House of Commons, and the only way in which coercion against political opponents - which is after all what is really intended and really meant - can be successful even for a time will be by the disenfranchisement of Ireland and her exclusion from the English Constitution. (Cries of "Never.") Well, I do not know. If Lord Salisbury is returned to power ("Never"), and if he sticks to his guns - two pretty big "ifs" - if he is returned to power and if he keeps his promises. (Cheers and laughter.) The Tories did not keep their promises to us (loud cheers), and that is why I think that possibly they will not keep their promises against us. I said there was only one alternative, but I was wrong. There is another alternative, and that one is that if Lord Salisbury gets into power he will make Lord Carnarvon his Lord Lieutenant again, and we will get a better Bill than Mr. Gladstone's. (Cheers and cries of "Expose him.") No, I am not going to tell you anything more about it than I have told you already. You see we may be wanting to make a little treaty with these gentlemen by and by again, and it does not do to split too much against your old pals. (Laughter.) Now, without telling you all about it, I just want to point out one thing, that neither Lord Carnarvon nor Lord Salisbury has denied the two main features of my assertion. (Cheers.) What was that assertion? It was that when I made a speech at Wicklow about protection and the statutory Legislature, I had reason to believe that if the Conservatives got into power after the general election they would have given us a statutory Legislature. Well, now I had every reason to believe that, and they do not deny it. (Cheers.) What they deny is something else which I did not say at all. (Laughter, and a voice, "That is their policy.") Sir M. Hicks-Beach (hisses and groans) and Lord Carnarvon say that the Cabinet did not agree to give us a statutory Legislature; but what I said was this - that Lord Carnarvon came to Ireland and left everybody with whom he spoke on the question under the impression that he himself and more than one of his leading colleagues were determined to give Ireland a statutory Legislature. ("Traitor," and cheers.) That has not been denied ("No, no"), and it cannot be denied. Lord Carnarvon will not deny that he was as strong a Home Ruler as I was last August (cheers), and that when he went over to Ireland he became so, stronger and stronger every day he lived in the country. (Laughter.) There is another thing he has not denied. He has not denied that he sought an interview with me in order to speak to me and consult with me about a constitution for Ireland. (Hear, hear.) So, without telling anything more about it (loud cries of "Go on") I think that I have proved what has not been denied, and will not be denied, and cannot be denied, that Lord Carnarvon was strongly in favour last year of a statutory Legislature for Ireland. (Cheers.) But Lord Salisbury was only too anxious to be convinced, and Lord Carnarvon, as Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, strongly urged this concession on the Cabinet, and it was not refused by the Cabinet until two things had happened. One of these was the failure to give the Tories a majority at the polls (hear, hear), and the other was the rumour from Hawarden that Mr. Gladstone was going to offer a settlement. (Cheers.) Then Lord Carnarvon resigned his seat, and he behaved honourably (cheers), and the rest of the Cabinet Ministers behaved dishonourably, for they turned right about face. (Hear, hear.) They saw that up to that moment, during their five months' tenure of office, they had been only too anxious to give Ireland a Legislature because it would be good policy for them so to do. They saw afterwards that it would be a better policy to turn right round and denounce Mr. Gladstone as the betrayer of his country, and the disrupter of the Empire. ("Hear, hear," and "Three cheers for Gladstone.") Now you see there is another alternative besides the alternative of coercion, though of course it comes to the same thing, because if you allow yourselves to be bamboozled into giving the Tories another chance of making a treaty with us it will be found that it will be made next time so that they will not be able to break it. (Cheers.) No, men of Portsmouth, I believe that, summoned to the battle by your great leader, Mr. Gladstone (loud cheers), you will recognize the urgency of this question. (Cheers.) It is not given to men every day to do so right and so good a thing as justice to a sister nation. (Cheers.) What harm could poor little Ireland do to great and rich England if you were to concede her ten times as much as this? (Cheers.) It is only Mr. Gladstone's desire to conciliate prejudices that has made this settlement as small as it is. But small as it is we cheerfully accept it as a final one. (Cheers.) We will not take upon ourselves the responsibility of keeping open this dispute between the two nations. (Cheers.) Untold is the guilt of that man who, for party purposes, does not take advantage of the spirit that is abroad among the English to put together the hand of the Irish nation and that of England, to close the strife of centuries, a strife that has been of no good, no advantage, to the people of either country; a strife that has only been for the benefit of the money-grabbing landlords (hisses); a strife that has impeded popular progress in England as well as in Ireland, and that must continue to impede it; a strife which is fanned for the purpose of cheating you out of your right and to divert the energies of the newly enfranchised masses of Great Britain from the redress of their grievances, for the odious desire of oppressing and keeping down the small sister country. ("Shame.") I believe as one man you will indignantly repudiate these deceivers (hear, hear); that you will tell them that you are not to be led astray by lying tales which it is sought to thrust into your ears; and that you see now before you, like a star in the night, the great principle of asserting that Ireland shall govern herself as she is entitled to do. (Cheers.) While she does not seek to interfere in any matter which can imperil the Imperial Crown and dynasty of England, she is determined, as generations of Irishmen have been before and as generations of Irishmen, should need arise, will be again, to have this justice conceded to her; and with that determination she confidently appeals to the generosity and to the spirit of justice of the English people. (Loud cheers.)</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnels [sic], who was once more received with enthusiastic cheers, said, - I just wish to say a word, and only a word, in appreciation, not only of your kind vote of thanks, but also for the way in which you have listened to what I had to say to you this evening. I should have liked in my speech to-night to have spoken to you on many things in greater detail than I have been able to do in the case of so gigantic a meeting as this. But it was really impossible for me in consequence of the enormous mass here assembled to go further into detail than I have done. (Cheers.) I believe that the Irish people, when they hear that I have been received in the way I have been to-night by an English meeting of this vast extent, will think that the millennium has come. (Cheers and laughter.) I hope, and I confidently believe, that as the result of the great election now about to take place in Portsmouth and all over the rest of the country a happy day of prosperity will opened to the Irish people such as they have never before enjoyed. (Loud cheers.) Mr. Parnell concluded amid enthusiastic cheering, which was continued with the singing of "He's a jolly good fellow" for several minutes after he had sat down.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
