<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Second Reading. Adjourned Debate., Hansard's Parliamentary Debates, Thursday 17 June 1880</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Second Reading. Adjourned Debate.</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="81159818807513812830" level="m">Hansard's Parliamentary Debates</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1880-06-17">17 June 1880</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00059"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>hansard report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">   
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/commons/1880/jun/17/second-reading-adjourned-debate#S3V0253P0_18800617_HOC_154"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he confessed that he did not see how they could discuss the question of the relief of distress in Ireland within the narrow limits now proposed to be assigned to it by the Bill now before the House. In the judgment of all those who had lived longest in Ireland, and had most carefully considered the condition of the people of that country, it always had been apparent that the main cause of periodical famines there was the condition of Irish land tenure. It would, therefore, be a matter of practical impossibility for the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland, by the adoption of the course which he had now announced—namely, the withdrawal of the clause, Notice of which the right hon. Gentleman had given a day or two ago, to limit the discussion of the question within the very narrow limits he proposed. It would be his (Mr. Parnell's) duty to move certain clauses which would put the question of this distress in Ireland upon its proper footing before the country. They had too long been told that distress in Ireland proceeded from the laziness and want of thrift of the Irish people. They had been too long in the habit of appearing before the nations of the world as beggars for charity; and there were many people—in fact, the majority of the people of Ireland—who now thought that the time had come when this practice should cease, and that they should have the opportunity of living in their own country, and of obtaining prosperity from the natural riches and resources of the country—an opportunity which the laws of England had denied them for so long a period. What was wanted by the Irish people was not so much that they should be relieved from the necessities produced by famine out of Imperial funds as that they should be put in a position to manage their own business by an Irish Parliament, instead of being subject, as was the case under the last Parliament, to alien legislation. What was the Bill of the present Government? It was a Bill which simply sought to carry ought the policy of the Predecessors of the present Government—a policy which consigned 250,000 people to death by starvation. What were the steps taken by the late Government? The House would recollect that distress in Ireland had been predicted by those best acquainted with the circumstances of the country, and publicly predicted during the last 12 months. It was in the May of 1879 that public attention first came to be directed to the probability—the extreme probability—that the wet season would produce suffering in many of the Western portions of Ireland. These complaints were made publicly, and how were they answered by the late Government? He found that up to January the only answer given by the Government to the pressing needs of the country was the arrest of Mr. Michael Davitt and others upon the trumped-up charge of sedition—a charge which in the ordinary course of law the Government should have prosecuted; but in this instance they shrank from doing so. It was not until the middle of November, 1879, that the Treasury on the application of the Lord Lieutenant, authorized the Commissioners of Public Works in Ireland to lend money to owners of land, or, in other words, it was not until the middle of November that the Government took the first step to stave off the distress, which was then in full swing. They issued a Circular under date of 22nd November, and on the 12th of January, 1880, there was a fresh Notice amending the former one, and offering loans on still more favourable conditions. These loans were offered to landlords and to sanitary authorities for the execution of works of employment, and also for the purpose of executing works which sanitary authorities could execute under the Acts authorizing their existence. It was now found by the Report just issued by the Dublin Mansion House Committee, the chief charitable association in Ireland, that the net result of all the exertions of the late and of the present Governments had been the employment of 15,000 people on works of relief out of 500,000 who were in want. And at what expenditure was this infinitesimal result arrived at? The Act of last Session authorized a loan out of the Irish Church Fund of £750,000. The whole of that loan had been drawn out—nay, more, it had been largely exceeded, so that the present Government were obliged to come to Parliament for fresh powers, by which they sought by the Bill under notice to make an additional advance of £750,000, notwithstanding that the whole of the loan authorized by the Act of last Session had been largely exceeded. It was found that up to the present the result was that employment had only been found for 15,000 out of 500,000 persons who were in want. Such a fact alone was sufficient to condemn the Bill now before the House; and if they really wanted to relieve distress in Ireland they must go further than the limit of the Bill proposed. The chief provisions of the present measure were (1), the advance by the Irish Church Temporalities Commissioners of another £750,000 for the purposes of loans to the owners of land in Ireland; (2), power was given to the Commissioners of Public Works, with the consent of the Treasury, to make loans to railway and other public Companies having borrowing powers, upon the security of baronial guarantees given by extraordinary presentment sessions; and (3), a small grant was to be given of £30,000 for fishery piers. With regard to the proposal of doubling the grant to the owners of land in Ireland, he failed to find the slightest justification for such a course as regarded the ostensible purpose of the Bill—the relief of distress in Ireland. He failed to see on what grounds the Government now came to ask Parliament for a fresh application of £750,000 for such a useless undertaking. If the Government had shown that the application of the money already spent was of any advantage, or that any appreciable portion of it had reached those who were really in distress, he could then have understood their contention; or if they had been able to show that any proportion of the money which they now asked from Parliament was likely to reach the really destitute, he could understand their application; but as the Government had not professed that this money was to be used for the relief of distress, or that a very small and almost appreciable portion of it was likely to be applied for that purpose, he thought the House would not be doing its duty if it sanctioned the diversion of money for such an object. By the latest information—they had not, however, received very late information on the subject from the Chief Secretary for Ireland—it appeared that about £250,000 had been issued to owners of land in Ireland. How much of that sum had probably reached the persons who were in distress? They could not assume that out of £250,000 issued in that way more than two-thirds or one-half had actually been expended, because it was obvious that the expenditure of a sum of money for that purpose must take a considerable time. But assuming that two-thirds of £250,000, which was a very liberal estimate, had been actually expended by the landlords who had received it, how much of those two-thirds had probably reached the hands of the people who were in want of bread? Works of improvement, which were easily undertaken by owners of land in Ireland, required a considerable expenditure in skilled labour and material. Iron, timber, Portland cement, lime, drainage tiles, and so forth, had to be purchased; masons, carpenters, slaters, and other skilled mechanics had to be employed, and paid high wages. It would not, therefore, be an unreasonable assumption to state that of £ 180,000 expended by the landlords, not more than half, or £90,000, had as yet been expended in wages for unskilled labour. Of the £90,000 it would be a very liberal assumption to say that, up to the present time, only one-half had been applied to the relief of the people who were in actual distress. These relief works were scattered all over the country. The noble Lord the Secretary to the Treasury (Lord Frederick Cavendish) had stated that of the numerous applications made by landlords in the scheduled districts only 63 had been refused. They might, then, fairly assume, from information which he (Mr. Parnell) had received from those who had a knowledge of the facts, that the works set on foot were not, so far, at any rate, as the majority of them were concerned, in localities where distressed persons could obtain employment. Therefore, he was fully justified in reducing the sum to one-half—namely to £45,000. There was another objection to the principle of granting money to owners of land apart entirely from the useless-ness of the application, so far as the relief of actual distress was concerned. Landowners in many eases used the money lent to them as a leverage to obtain the payment of rents from then-tenants. It was worked in this way—the tenants who could not pay rent were, he had heard, informed that unless they paid it no works of improvement would be executed on their farms; and those tenants who did pay were favoured in comparison with those who could not pay, and if the latter were employed they were told that they would have to give back in the shape of rent the money they received for their labour.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR.PARNELL said, he was speaking generally of scheduled districts, and he could not then give particular instances. It was obvious that one of the chief designs of the late Government was not to relieve the distressed, but to relieve landlords who could not obtain their rents with the same celerity as formerly they could. He had no doubt that the leverage had been used and would be used again to a considerable extent. A further objection to the proposal of Her Majesty's Government was, that this sum of £750,000 was to be taken out of the Irish Church Fund. That application he considered to be in direct contradiction of the statute, as that fund was the only one which was available for many purposes in Ireland. It was exceedingly hard that the Government should seize upon that fund to provide against the consequences of an occurrence which was the result of the neglect of Parliament in years past. They might fairly ask, what was the necessity for such an appropriation of the fund? The security for the repayment of the sum to be advanced was unimpeachable. All former loans for the improvement of Irish land had been duly repaid; and why, therefore, should not this loan be advanced by the Imperial Exchequer, and the Irish Church Fund be left for purposes which might obtain the sanction of the majority of the Irish constituencies? Then, again, the Church Commissioners had no capital—they had only an annual income, and in order to make advances were obliged to borrow—sometimes from the Savings' Banks. In this case he understood they would have to borrow from the Commissioners for the Reduction of the National Debt. The money was to be borrowed at 3½per cent, and was to be lent to the landowners at 1 percent, so that there would be an annual loss to the fund of 2½ per cent, and that for a period of 37 years would amount to £250,000. If they agreed to take the money from the Imperial Exchequer, would it not be a fair and generous thing at least to lend the money at the same rate as it was proposed that it should be borrowed? He believed the calculated surplus of the Irish Church Fund was only about £4,000,000 at the present time, and the proposed charge of £1,500,000 would reduce it to £2,500,000. It was, therefore, obvious that the utility of the fund, in any future emergency, was very much impaired. It appeared to him that the ultimate loss to the fund would be avoided by the course he suggested; and he had reason to believe that the matter was so important that if a concession were made on that point, the opposition to the Government proposals would, he believed, be very much diminished. The next provision of the Bill was one by which power was given to the Commissioners of Public Works, with the consent of the Treasury, to make loans to Railway Companies and other Companies in having borrowing powers on the security of baronial guarantees obtained at extraordinary presentment sessions. That clause might shortly be described as the railway clause of the Bill; and he could not imagine how the Chief Secretary for Ireland could have been induced to pitchfork, so to speak, these clauses into the Bill if he had given the subject proper consideration. Under the present law, Railway Companies, before coming to Parliament for their Bills, were entitled to apply to baronial sessions for a guarantee. Up to 1874 the presentment of baronial sessions and the fiat of a Grand Jury were the only conditions requisite for the purpose of obtaining a guarantee; but in 1874 the House of Commons, in order to prevent the misuse of the grants, and to provide certain local checks and guarantees against jobbery, adopted a Standing Order by which the consent of as many local bodies as possible should be obtained before the Railway Companies could get a guarantee, and in addition to the baronial presentment, it became necessary that the consent of a Board of Guardians should be obtained before the guarantee could be granted. Thus they had, first of all, the check provided by the necessary consent of the Board of Guardians; secondly, the presentment of the baronial sessions of the associated cesspayers; third, the Grand Jury finding; and fourth, the power possessed by the rate and cesspayers to traverse the presentment before a Judge at Assizes. Thus there were four distinct cheeks provided by the Legislature in order to prevent abuse; and, although they had been found insufficient for their purpose, yet the clauses of the right hon. Gentleman proposed to sweep away those checks at one blow, and to introduce a variety of other changes by the proposed clauses. The Lord Lieutenant could call an extraordinary presentment sessions, and then a Railway Company which had previously failed in obtaining its baronial guarantee, which had gone before Parliament and obtained its Acts, and had been granted powers on condition that the whole of its capital should be subscribed, and one-half of it paid up, could now come forward and obtain a baronial guarantee without any check or hindrance from the extraordinary baronial presentment sessions convened by the Lord Lieutenant, and without having to fulfil any of the conditions provided by the Legislature as to capital. In other words, the Company, which had been unable to obtain its presentment before, and which had been unable to obtain a 6d. of capital or even its expense, could come forward and levy black mail by casting itself on the unprotected ratepayers, and obtain a guarantee for its own advantage and benefit. Before he left the Railway Companies he wanted to point out that the power which was to be granted by the Legislature might act in a very unexpected manner, and in a way not at all intended by the promoters of the Bill. There was nothing in the clauses as they at present stood to prevent any of the great Railway Companies in Ireland, such as the Great Southern and Western, the Dublin, Wicklow, and Wexford Railway, the Midland, Great Northern, and others, with plenty of means for obtaining capital for the prosecution of any work which was likely to pay—there was nothing to prevent them from enlarging their resources by obtaining baronial guarantee under the provisions of the Bill for the maintaining a branch line which could not possibly pay directly, but which might be of indirect value to the line, and which might act as a feeder to traffic on the main line, but be a work which, at present, and for all time hereafter, would necessarily be a burden on the ratepayers. With respect to the interest on the capital raised in the construction of the works, there were many branch lines which could be made which would be very useful to the main line, and which would probably pay indirectly, but which would never pay back directly any portion of the capital used in their construction; and there was nothing in the clause to prevent Companies such as those he had described from obtaining guarantees from the baronial sessions in the summary manner provided for. Then, again, the provisions with regard to public Companies was one of a very extraordinary character. Everything which he had said in regard to the Rail-way Companies applied to the public Companies; and any bubble Company sprung up in London, Australia, or anywhere else, provided they could obtain an Act of Parliament giving them borrowing powers, without the subscription of a farthing of capital, could go to Ireland and obtain a baronial guarantee and carry on works at the expense of the starving ratepayers of Ireland. He now came to the consideration of the question whether the clauses were likely to carry out at all the objects for which they were introduced. They had been told that there were railways in Ireland running directly through the distressed districts, which, if works in connection with them were commenced, would give employment to the people by the erection of the earthworks necessary. He asked the House to consider whether the clauses proposed would be effectual in the carrying out of the object. His own belief, based upon local opinion and information, was that the money should be lent for such purposes as cheaply as to the landlords. He had made some inquiries with respect to a railway which was projected in the county of Donegal, with reference to which a Memorial was presented to the Chief Secretary for Ireland some short time since. He had written to a respected parish priest who had been instrumental in bringing the Memorial forward, and who had given a great deal of time and attention to the relief of distress in his district—it would not be necessary to mention his name. He had written to that gentleman and asked him whether the cesspayers in his locality would consent to be taxed for the purpose of the erection of the railway. In reply he had received a letter which answered the question in the negative after making inquiries. He had also written another letter stating that those in his district were unanimously of opinion that Section 4 of the Bill, making a baronial guarantee a necessity, in order to obtain a Government loan, would prove futile. What they wanted was to have the Board of Guardians substituted for the baronial sessions. That change was warranted by the nature and objects of the Bill, which was ostensibly a measure to relieve distress. He thought he had said enough about those clauses to show that they opened floodgates to abuse, of which none could at present see the extent, without even remedying the chief misfortunes of the country, and, that under the plea of remedying distress in Ireland, the Government offered a prospect to jobbery which it was impossible to calculate with any certainty, and that the Government did not meet—as far as their calculations could be understood, they did not meet—the wants in question, and that the railways which were projected, and the making of which would relieve the present distress in Ireland, would not be able to obtain the loans under the proposed Bill. It was probable that parts of the Bill, as it now stood, would be hurtful rather than beneficial. He thought, at all events, that they should limit the extent of the clauses very carefully, and that the Companies should be named in a Schedule to which it was proposed to advance loans under the Bill now before the House. The Irish Members would then be able to see what they were asked to do, and would not be compelled to take extraordinary measures to find out what they were asked to agree to. He then came to the small provision for fishery piers. So far from the clauses in the Bill which referred to the fishery piers being an advantage to the fisheries, they were the reverse, as most of them were to be started on parts of the coast where they were not likely to be completed. The grants were also saddled with such conditions as it was not at all probable would be carried out, for in one part of the clause it was proposed that in any place where it was proposed to construct a new pier or harbour, the barony of that district must make a presentment to the effect, and undertaking to bear one-fourth of the excess of expenditure which must be incurred in carrying out such work. According to that, the barony must blindly bind itself to pay for the blunders of the Board of Works. For instance, if the Board of Works estimated that the erection of a pier or harbour would cost £6,000, and it was found that the cost was £12,000, the barony would have to contribute one-fourth before a single stone was laid of the proposed work; it would have to guarantee in all cases one-fourth of the excess expenditure. That was a proposition which he felt sure very few of them would feel inclined to accede to. There were a number of other objections to the details of the Bill which would, however, be best used in Committee; and, therefore, he proposed to pass them. Finally, the Canadian and Liverpool Fund granted £15,000 towards the fishery piers, and the Chief Secretary for Ireland only proposed to grant double that amount, namely—£30,000. If the right hon. Gentleman wished to carry out his avowed intention he would have to grant at least £45,000. The amount mentioned was altogether illusory, because Ireland had received nothing for a number of years from Parliament towards the erection of the fishery piers, Since the Union Scotland had received over £1,000,000 in grants in aid of fisheries, while during the last six years Ireland had received nothing at all; while he was informed that if the miserable pittance of £30,000, which had been mentioned, was granted, nothing more would be given for the next five years; in fact, the Chief Secretary for Ireland had set his bait with the little sprat of £30,000 in order to catch the magnificent mackerel of £750,000. For his own part, he (Mr. Parnell) felt disposed to leave the money in the hands of the Treasury. He did not intend to oppose the second reading of the Bill; but it seemed to him that it would be the duty of the Irish Members to try every possible way to amend it in Committee. At present it was practically a sham Bill. It did not fulfil the object it had in view—namely, the relief of distress in Ireland. It did not touch it. If they voted the money asked for, neither the £750,000 nor the £450,000 would reach the people for the next six months, which was when they wanted it most. He thought the Chief Secretary for Ireland had really underestimated the magnitude of the distress. He thought there would be a good harvest. He was sure he (Mr. Parnell) hoped there would be a good harvest; but not one good harvest, nor two good harvests, would remove the pressure in Ireland. The potato crop was, he was glad to say, doing very well, and it appeared to be one of the best that had been in Ireland for many years; but, at the same time, he must say the real suffering was due not so much to the failure of the potato crop in the past as to other causes. The distressed districts were generally those in the West of Ireland, where there were a large number of small holdings—little strips of land—and the tenants of those places were more in the position of labourers than that of farmers. There were about 150,000 of these holdings. Those men had been in the habit of going to England and Scotland and working for the farmers there in times of distress; but, owing to the state of manufacture in England, the urban populations of England had been driven to the country, and had taken the employment which used to be taken up by the Irish tenants. The consequence of that was that those men had scraped up every farthing of money to go to England in search of work, and when they got there they were utterly unable to obtain it. It was a great mistake to suppose that the poorer classes lived now, as they did before the Famine, entirely on potatoes. They lived far more upon Indian meal, which it required money to buy, as it required money also to pay their rents; and even if they had a good harvest the landlords might step in and seize the crops for the rent. The Bill of the right hon. Gentleman would not prevent that. He did not agree with his right hon. Friend the Member for Carlow (Mr. Gray) that the Irish Members could throw their responsibility upon the Government. The constituencies of Ireland had made the greatest sacrifices to return them; and if they threw their responsibility on the Government the constituencies would be deeply and bitterly disappointed. Therefore it would be their duty on that and any future stage of the Bill to point out its utter unsuitableness for its ostensible purpose, and to show the Government how they could meet the distress, which was still of great intensity. He proposed, when the Bill reached the Committee, to ask the House to assign the £750,000, which was intended by the Bill to go to the owners of land, instead of that to assign it to Boards of Guardians in Ireland, thus enabling them to lend money directly to occupiers willing to improve their land. He felt convinced that in no other way could they have the slightest hope of rescuing 500,000 of the Irish peasantry from the last stage of pauperism. In no other way could they check pauperism and emigration, which in time would sweep away every young man, woman, and child in the country. He believed if the Chief Secretary for Ireland would go down along Mayo and the other parts of the Western Coast of Ireland his heart would be almost broken down with what he would see there. He must not take too much time to consider the subject; and unless he did something in that Bill for the purpose of freeing the people from pauperism and from the necessity for emigration, both must go on, and he would not have any opportunity until next Session. While he was considering the question the people would be gone; it was impossible to stop it, if the Government deliberately refused to provide the people of Ireland with employment. They were deliberately encouraging outrage and revolution if the Government of the Queen showed itself insensible to the sufferings of multitudes. It lost its title to a responsible Government; and they could not blame the ignorance of the people of the West of Ireland if they should attempt to do for themselves that which the Government refused to do for them. For his own part, he should take every opportunity of showing the Government in the present crisis the urgent necessity of doing something more than they had been doing, and for attempting, at any rate, to put a stop to the terrible scenes of suffering and privation which at present existed.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL I am asking what amount of loans was sanctioned up to the time the late Government wont out of Office?</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he wished to ask the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary to the Lord Lieutenant whether he proposed to take the Committee on the Bill to-morrow (Friday)? There was not, he thought, sufficient opportunity afforded for preparing Amendments to the Bill; and although the Irish Members had done all they could to arrange about Amendments, there had not been sufficient time to bring them forward, and they had, therefore, made small progress in that direction. Of course, if the right hon. Gentleman really wished to get into Committee, they could then move to report Progress, with the understanding that some days, or perhaps a week, later the matter could come up for further consideration. He trusted that the postponement would take place—say, until next week, in order that they might have the opportunity of drawing up Amendments that would be satisfactory.</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
