<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Class III. - Law and Justice., Hansard's Parliamentary Debates, Thursday 26 August 1880</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Class III. - Law and Justice.</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="81159818807513812830" level="m">Hansard's Parliamentary Debates</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1880-08-26">26 August 1880</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00068"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>hansard report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">    
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/commons/1880/aug/26/class-iii-law-and-justice#S3V0256P0_18800826_HOC_338"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that no one regretted more than he did the course that they would be compelled to take by the action of the Government. It would have the effect of delaying, more or less, many valuable measures which were in progress. None of his hon. Friends wished to keep back the various measures,; but they wished to do all they could to support the measures which had been brought in by the Government. It was idle to charge them with Obstruction, when they had waited until the last days of the Session to commence a course of Obstruction. If they had desired to obstruct they would have commenced work long ago. He did think that many Members of that House did not fully realize the grave situation which at present existed in Ireland. He had failed to perceive, from the public utterances of the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary, that he himself appreciated the circumstances. He thought, from his general bearing, that if he were really acquainted with what had been done during the course of the winter, he would not hesitate to get Parliament together during the autumn, when it would be necessary to send another Bill back to the House of Lords. What were the facts with regard to the tenantry in the West of Ireland? He had his information from a gentleman constantly going over that district. He was credibly informed that half the tenantry of Ireland were under ejectment. These ejectments would be stayed until the harvest was gathered in, and a contest arose between the rival creditors of the unfortunate tenants. These creditors were not only the landlords, but frequently bankers and shopkeepers. It would take three harvests instead of one to pay one-half of what the majority of the tenants owed. That was the position before the tenantry of the West of Ireland at the present moment. The right hon. Gentleman brought in his Bill—a very insufficient protection it was—but he failed to carry it. He now proposed to let the House rise, and he gave no assurance of what he was going to do to meet the situation. He himself had made a re-assuring statement; but, after private communications with the Attorney General for Ireland, he did his best to diminish the force of his observations. That was the situation before them, and it was a situation of enormous gravity, and one which entitled them to some consideration from the Government in the matter. If the peasantry of the West of Ireland were slaughtered, he would tell the English Liberal Members that their blood would be upon their head. Those who had lived amongst the people, as the hon. Member for the County of Galway (Mr. T. P. O'Connor) had done for the last two years, and had witnessed their sufferings, had told them of the actual state of affairs, and it should be remembered that he spoke with knowledge and experience of what was going on. It seemed to him that the testimony of one who had spent his daily life amongst those suffering people was better entitled to be heard with regard to their condition than those who were unacquainted with it.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that if he might make an observation it would be this— it seemed to him that the Government were not acting reasonably in asking them to go on with Business after a certain time—that was, after 1 o'clock. It had always been the recognized custom in the House that when a minority was asked to go on with the Business after a reasonable time, it was entitled to use the Forms of the House, in order to protect itself from the majority. The Forms of the House were given to minorities in order that they might use them for their protection from arbitrary, or unjust, or hasty action on the part of majorities. Now, he and his hon. Friends thought that the action of the Government, in endeavouring to force them to proceed with the discussion of these Estimates after 1 o'clock, was of an arbitrary character, and that that was why they felt entitled to use the Forms of the House for their protection. For his part, he had no objection to resume the discussion of the Estimates after a few hours' sleep, and when what they had to say could be reported to the outside world. He desired to point out, though he did not wish to lay too much stress on the matter, that he had not spoken on the question yet. He thought he was entitled to speak upon it, and at a time when what he said could be reported. There were several of his hon. Friends in the same position. If the Government would now agree to report Progress, he would be glad to resume the discussion of the Estimates at the usual Morning Sitting. He could not see what reasonable objection the Government could urge to such a proposal.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, an hour-and-a-half ago he had made a proposal to the Government which was not accepted. In making that proposal a second time, he would only express his regret that these proceedings had taken place; and he could assure the noble Lord that, from every point of view, he had made a great mistake in taking up the attitude he had assumed. The proceedings of that evening were extremely disagreeable to him, and he much regretted that no way had been found out of the situation. He could not, however, take any part of the blame for those disagreeable proceedings upon himself. He thought the noble Lord had taken upon himself, as Leader of the House, a more headstrong course than he was entitled to pursue, and that, in imputing motives to some hon. Members, he had exceeded the rules of conduct sanctioned by the Rules of the Committee. They desired the Government to allow them to proceed with the debate on the Estimates at a time when they could be properly and legitimately discussed. There was not, and could not be, any foundation for the suggestion of the noble Lord, that any attempt had been made, or that any intention existed, to obstruct the Police and Constabulary Votes. The noble Lord himself was responsible for compelling the Irish Members to use the Forms of the House for the protection of the interests they had at heart. He seemed to suppose that, if he had agreed to their request, the same thing might have taken place at the end of the next night in Supply as had taken place last night. He could not understand how the noble Lord—still less the Chief Secretary for Ireland— could have made such a suggestion. Irish Members had kept faith with the Government both in letter and spirit. It was the right hon. and learned Gentleman the Member for the Dublin University (Mr. Gibson) who had originated a discussion in which he (Mr. Parnell) would like to have joined; but he had refrained from doing so, in order not to break the spirit of the engagement entered into and the understanding arrived at. What ground then had the noble Lord for the statement which he now made, that they had formed the intention to obstruct the Police Vote—that was to say, to debate them unduly. He would candidly admit that, at one time, previously to the statement of the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland, he had entertained the idea of using the Forms of the House to their fullest extent; but he had abandoned it on hearing the speech of the right hon. Gentleman. The Government must have known that the Irish Members did not intend to discuss the Vote on Tuesday; and yet, in face of that knowledge, both the Chief Secretary and the noble Lord rose and made these assertions. Now, he submitted that this was neither fair nor worthy treatment, on the part of those right hon. Gentlemen, to extend to Irish Members. They were told that they must not use the Forms of the House; but he could assure the Government that when they fettered Irish Members in this way, and prevented their enjoying the same freedom and liberties as the English Members, they were taking one step to render it impossible for Ireland to continue to send her Members here to claim any sort of justice whatever. He trusted that this disagreeable scene would be allowed to terminate, and that the discussion might be resumed at a time when hon. Members could do their duty, and when the public could be made to understand what was the actual position of Irish Members with regard to this Vote.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, it must be obvious to the hon. Member who had made this suggestion, and to the Chief Secretary who had repeated it, that he could enter into no such bargain in the absence of his hon. Friends; he could not even say that he could approve of such a bargain being entered into, for it would be grossly false on his part to undertake to do anything of the sort. He and his hon. Friends acted in consultation with each other, and they only acted after full consultation with each other. It had always been his boast that he had never yet done anything contrary to the opinion of the Party with which he had the honour to act; and, therefore, to ask him at a moment's notice to make a bargain of this kind, in the absence of many of his Friends who had just as much right to be consulted as he had, was practically absurd. He could only say if the proposition was repeated on the return of those who were entitled to be consulted that he should be happy to consider it. He should only like to point out, however, to the hon. Member for Liskeard (Mr. Courtney) that he was not very fortunate in his interpretation of the rights of minorities; in fact, his evidence on this subject was opposed to the evidence given by Mr. Raikes, the late Chairman of Committees, before the Select Committee on the subject, in which he plainly intimated that the use of the Forms of the House by minorities on the occasion of the obstruction to the Sunday Closing Act was not, in his opinion, such a use in the Forms of the House by minorities as could be called an abuse of them. He recollected upon that occasion, which was an all-night Sitting, when Motions to report Progress were made in great frequency, that the hon. Member got up and made a speech similar to that he had delivered that night. He told them then that he was a great supporter of the rights of minorities, and that he viewed this kind of work with dread, and that it would tend to restrict those rights. It was exactly the same kind of speech as that which the hon. Gentleman had just made now, when he had told them that the use of the Forms of the House which they were making was a use which the minority were not entitled to make. When, however, Mr. Raikes, the late Chairman of Committees, was subsequently examined on this question by the noble Lord the present Leader of the House, and the noble Lord asked him whether this opposition was not an opposition—by about the same minority as theirs that night—which could be called obstructive or an abuse of the Forms of the House, Mr. Raikes distinctly gave it as his opinion, upon that occasion, that the opposition which the hon. Member for Liskeard had stigmatised as an abuse of the rights of minorities, was not so, but was, on the contrary, a perfectly justifiable use of them. So that they had, on the one hand, the opinion of the hon. Member for Liskeard, and, on the other, the opinion of Mr. Raikes, who was called before the Select Committee on Public Business as the especial and official witness of the late Government for the purpose of giving his opinion, upon which a certain Rule was framed. This was very remarkable, as showing that the hon. Member for Liskeard was not such an authority in regard to the rights of minorities as he would have hon. Members suppose. His opinion was directly contradicted by the opinion of the late Chairman of Committees of that House, a gentleman whom no one would say was not infinitely better acquainted with the Forms of the House and with the powers and rights of that Assembly.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he had already stated his proposition two or three times, and his experience in regard to it, upon the last occasion, was not a happy one, because his words were taken hold of by the hon. Member for Northampton, and misrepresented in a way which to him was exceedingly painful. However, he would repeat over again what he had asked the Government to accept at 4 o'clock, just three hours ago. He suggested that, if Progress were reported, they would be very happy to go on with the discussion of the items in the Vote at the commencement of the Business in the usual way. They proposed that in order to show that they did not care, and did not wish to obstruct the Progress of Business, if the Government would agree to report Progress, and fix their Sitting in the usual way, he and his hon. Friends would be very glad to proceed with the discussion of the Estimates, and to a fair and bond fide discussion of those Estimates.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that a proposition had been made to them by the Government that he should ask his hon. Friend the Member for Galway City whether he was willing to postpone his Motion standing on the Paper for Friday night in the event of the Government consenting to report Progress then, and putting the Constabulary Estimates down as the first Order for Friday night, at 9 o'clock. He might say that he had communicated with his hon. Friend, and would leave him to speak for himself on that matter. In the event of his complying with the request, he wished his (Mr. Parnell's) position in the matter to be clearly understood. He trusted that, in the few words which he was going to say, there might be no misapprehension as to the statement which he was making. He had said that he was willing that Progress should be reported if the Government placed the Constabulary Votes down for some future Sitting, and that he should be willing, and would undertake, that the discussion should proceed in a fair and bond fide manner. He was not to be taken as admitting for a moment that the discussion upon these Estimates had, up to that time, not been carried on in a fair and bond fide way. He must guard himself against that; nor could he enter into any bargain, nor could he give any undertaking, or agreement, in the absence of his hon. Friends, that the Estimates would be finished on that evening. That was all he could say.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that it was hard for hon. Members to understand the position in which he was placed. The arrangements which were made before Mr. Speaker left the Chair had been previously agreed to by all his hon. Friends, and he was bound to [act with the majority on this occasion. He regretted very much that he could not say, straight out, that he would exert his influence with his Colleagues in this matter. He did not think it proper for him to say that he would, and he could not give any further pledge than he had already given.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that he was sorry he could not add anything more to the statement he had already made. He should be glad to do anything he could to lead the way out of the present difficulty. He must say that it would be more satisfactory if the arrangement he had suggested were made than if they waited until his hon. Friends reentered the House. He did not know that he ought to go any further than he had done. The result was much more likely to be satisfactory, if the arrangement he had suggested were carried out in the way he had suggested, rather than if they waited until his hon. Friends came in. He begged to move that the Chairman do now report Progress and ask leave to sit again.</p>
         <p>Motion made, and Question proposed, "That the Chairman do report Progress, and ask leave to sit again."— (Mr. Parnell.)</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, his difficulty was that he could not, in the absence of his hon. Friends, appear to lay down a policy or come to a decision. It would not be fair or right to them. He did not, in their absence, like to lay down any particular course, for it would be an indication on his part, in their absence, of deciding upon a particular course.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that, in saying he could not undertake to use his influence, he wished to be understood only as saying that he could not make any declarations to the Committee of what course he should take.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, the minority maintained that they were entitled to use the Forms of the House for the purpose of insuring to themselves another opportunity of discussing the Irish Estimates. That opportunity had been refused to them by the Government, and the last attempt made to bring about a compromise in that direction had failed, although the hon. Member for Galway (Mr. T. P. O'Connor) had offered to give place to the Government on Friday, provided the Estimates were put down for that day. The Government had refused to accede to this proposal unless some Irish Members gave a pledge that they would use their influence with other Irish Members to get them to allow the Estimates to go through on that evening. He felt that such a pledge could not be honourably given in the absence of the Irish Members interested; and,  therefore, the attempted compromise had fallen through and matters stood as they were. He regretted exceedingly that the compromise had not been accepted, and thought that the Government would have to reconsider the matter.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, if he was in Order, he was going to suggest that Progress should be reported temporarily, in order that they might have a statement upon this subject, and then, afterwards, Committee might be resumed. Of course, then, the question would remain unchanged as to what the Committee proposed to do with reference to this Business. The situation was unchanged, as far as he and his hon. Friends were concerned, although many of them had been deprived of their rest and sleep by the action of the Government—action which, as they submitted, was utterly unnecessary for the purpose which they had in view, the expedition of Public Business?— Business which he would maintain would be better provided for according to their Motion to report Progress. Had that been agreed to at 1 o'clock they would have been enabled to go away, and to come back ready to consider the Votes fairly that evening, instead of being in a position in which they did not know exactly how they stood. Propositions were made before the noble Lord returned to his place, of such a charater [sic] as to be satisfactory to himself, and not merely to himself, but to some hon. Members on the side of the noble Lord, so much so, that several who had been supporters of the noble Lord during the night in the Division Lobby voted with him in one division, and afterwards refused to take any farther part in supporting the Government. That was a very remarkable fact, and should be made known, because it should be understood that the responsibility of rejecting the proposal he had made rested upon the Government.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, it originated in a request from him. The proposition they then made was of such a character as to induce a considerable number of Members—[Mr. WARTON: No; only four.]—who had been supporting the Chief Secretary for Ireland to show that they thought his offer was a reasonable one and ought to be accepted. So much did they think so that they retired from the Committee, and refused to support the Government any longer. It was desirable that that statement should go forth, in order to show how thoroughly they had put themselves in the right during that night, and how willing they had shown themselves to be to agree to any compromise that could honourably be accepted. He regretted that that compromise had not been accepted, because the result was that they stood where they were now.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, as there seemed to be some inexplicable desire on the part of right hon. Gentlemen on the Treasury Bench to hear once again a proposition which he had several times already made, and which, as he thought, was thoroughly understood by the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary— and which he certainly might communicate to the noble Lord by his side—as he did not wish to appear discourteous in refusing the request of so many hon. Members who had not been there during the night, and were desirous of learning what was proposed, he would only say that his proposition was that the Government should report Progress, and that his hon. Friend the Member for the City of Galway (Mr. T. P. O'Connor), having agreed to postpone his Motion in favour of the Government, and the hon.  Member for the County of Louth (Mr. Callan) having also agreed to postpone his Motion in favour of the Government, that then Supply should be put down. He forgot the exact words that he used; but he believed he said that they would then proceed with a fair and bond fide discussion of the question. At the same time, he could not answer for the hon. Members who were absent; and he could not say for them, in consequence, that the Votes would be finished on Friday night.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, he hoped he might interpose for a moment. He thought the hon. and learned Member would see that after he had been explaining his proposal made during the night in the absence of the noble Lord, it was scarcely for the hon. and learned Member to criticize his conduct in repeating, to the best of his recollection, the proposition he originally made.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL was sorry that he had not responded earlier to the invitation of his hon. Friend the Member for Salford (Mr. Arthur Arnold). He had wished, before doing so, to see how the matter was going. He had now had an opportunity of consulting with many of his Friends; and he found that their opinion was almost, if not entirely, universal, that the Constabulary Estimates were of such a nature that they could not enter into any undertaking or understanding with regard to them. And now with regard to the question of another Sitting. He very much feared that a 9 o'clock Friday Sitting would not end satisfactorily to either Party; but he was free to say that he had no moral doubt whatever that an arrangement might be come to if the Government could see their way to giving a full Evening Sitting for the discussion of these Estimates—a discussion in which he would hope that some of the English Members would join, and give them the benefit of their opinion on these Votes; for it had been one of the most painful things to the Irish Members, and one of those matters that made them feel almost hopeless, to see the alacrity with which the English Members refused to join in any debate, and accused the Irish Members of obstructing the Business of the House, simply because they were desirous of bringing their grievances under the consideration of the House. Unfortunately, they had found themselves thwarted and hampered by the want of co-operation manifested by the English Members. He had now a question to put, which was this—He felt sure, and had no moral doubt whatever, as he had already said, although he should not and could not enter into any understanding or agreement—but he had no moral doubt that if the Government could see their way to affording another Evening Sitting, that the time thus given up would be sufficient for the discussion of the Constabulary Vote.</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL asked if the noble Lord could not take the other Irish Estimates at the 9 o'clock Sitting, so as to give a clear day's debate for the Constabulary Vote?</p>
         <p>...</p>
         <p>MR. PARNELL And the Constabulary Vote on Monday?</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
