<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Class III. - Law and Justice, Hansard's Parliamentary Debates, Monday 30 August 1880</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Class III. - Law and Justice</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="81159818807513812830" level="m">Hansard's Parliamentary Debates</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1880-08-30">30 August 1880</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7011781">London, England</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00070"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>hansard report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04"> 
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://api.parliament.uk/historic-hansard/commons/1880/aug/30/class-iii-law-and-justice#S3V0256P0_18800830_HOC_79"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>MR. PARNELL said, that he found that their position with reference to these Constabulary Votes had been somewhat misunderstood, and he wished to recall to the recollection of the Committee the statement which he made at the conclusion of Business, when Progress was about to be reported upon this Vote on Friday morning last. The statement was this, that he had found the almost unanimous opinion amongst Irish Members to be that the Constabulary Estimates were of such a character that no undertaking or understanding could be entered into with regard to them. They also felt that the result of resuming the discussion on Friday evening would not be satisfactory for their purposes. At the same time, he felt no moral doubt that if Progress was then reported, and the discussion resumed at the commencement of the Monday Sitting, that that would be deemed a sufficient discussion. He would draw the attention of the Committee to this statement, for he had seen it extensively stated in the newspapers that they had entered into an engagement to close the discussion that night. That was the thing they had always avoided doing. They found that they could not do it, for they felt that it would be adopting the principles of the cloture with regard to Irish discussions, and there was no precedent for such a course. He wished, however, to state his belief that the discussion that evening would be sufficient to enable them to come to a division upon the Estimates. He wished also further to say that subsequently to a speech which the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland delivered on Tuesday, the Irish Members abandoned their intention to use the Forms of the House to oppose the Vote. Up to that time, he admitted, that they all considered, in view of the entire absence of any statement of the right hon. Gentleman to the effect that justice would be accompanied by mercy, or that if Parliament were called together to renew the Coercion Act, that it would also be called together to prevent the injustice to Irish tenants—he felt it would be their duty to use all the Forms of the House against the Vote; but after the statement of the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland on Tuesday last, they considered that two nights' discussion would be sufficient for the purpose of putting the ground of their? [sic] opposition to these Estimates before the English public. Perhaps he might also refer to the criticism upon their opposition which was made by the hon. Member for Northampton (Mr. Labouchere). He seemed to think that they would have been justified in doing what they did on Thursday night, or rather on Friday morning, and if they had determined to use all the Forms of the House against these Votes for the purpose of entirely opposing them; but that they were doing an exceedingly disgraceful thing in using the rights of the minority for the purpose of only obtaining another day's discussion. He would remind the hon. Member for Northampton that this was a question upon which the Irish Members were responsible to their constituents alone for their actions. When they did come to a determination to take a certain course with reference to these Votes, he considered, and his hon. Friends with whom he acted thought, that they should do all they could to secure that action being successful. They desired a second night's debate upon those Constabulary Estimates; and they had, therefore, gained the object for which they initiated the struggle of Friday morning. Now, what he wished to do was to make certain suggestions or propositions to the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary for Ireland with reference to the administration of the law in Ireland during the ensuing autumn and winter, and particularly with reference to the use he might have to make of the police force in that country. No one could deny that the right hon. Gentleman stood in a most unparalleled position with reference to this Vote, and to the prospects before him in the coming winter. He had said publicly, on his authority as a responsible Minister of the Crown-— responsible for the good order and government of Ireland—that the late Bill for Compensation for Disturbance (Ireland) was necessary in order to prevent the Government from being under the necessity of using the powers of the police for the purpose of assisting landlords to work injustice. He qualified that statement by a further one, that a very small minority of the Irish landlords had committed injustice, or were likely to commit injustice; but, at the same time, the fact remained that the right hon. Gentleman was now asking them for a sum of money which he anticipated he would be obliged to use for the purpose of working injustice to some, at all events, of the tenants in Ireland, and for the purpose of defeating the object of the Legislature as defined by the Land Act of 1870. He had further given them on Tuesday last to understand that, if he found that the landlords compelled the Government, to any great extent, to use the law for the purpose of working injustice, and if he found that he could not enforce the law by the ordinary means at the disposal of the Government, he would apply to Parliament for fresh power, and ask Parliament to pass a Bill which would obviate the necessity the Government were under of working injustice. He wished to ask the right hon. Gentleman how he proposed to undertake to inquire into these matters, and what practical steps he proposed to take' in order to obtain the information which would be necessary to ascertain whether the landlords were likely to commit injustice? Perhaps he was also entitled to ask him upon what principles he would proceed in making those inquiries? Would he consider that a landlord was inflicting injustice upon a tenant if the tenant was in a state of starvation, and was turned out upon the road without any shelter or means of support? Would the right hon. Gentleman consider that a landlord was working injustice if he found that a tenant had been paying a manifestly high rent for many years, and that the attempt to pay this high rent for many years had left the tenant in such a position that it would be absolutely impossible for him to pay the rent in the current season and leave enough for him to support himself during the rest of the year? Of course, the right hon. Gentleman could only give them a general assurance; but it was obvious that it would be necessary for him to adopt some practical machinery; and he thought the Irish Members were entitled to have the views of the right hon. Gentleman, in respect to these matters, fully stated. He would also ask him whether he would undertake to inquire, so far as he could, into the merits of the cases of eviction where he was asked for police assistance to enforce the process of the law, previously to affording such assistance? It was obvious to everybody that such an inquiry by the right hon. Gentleman the Chief Secretary would be a very material caution to the bad landlords, as it would show them that their proceedings were being watched by the responsible authority; and that, if the responsible authority, on the one hand, was obliged to assist them in evicting their tenants unjustly, yet, on the other hand, the occurrence of that injustice was known to the right hon. Gentleman, and formed one of the grounds which would induce him to apply to Parliament for a Bill to protect the tenants from that injustice. The knowledge that that was likely to occur would have a very important effect upon public opinion among the landlord class in Ireland. If the Irish landlords once knew that acts of injustice inflicted by the minority amongst themselves were likely to lead to fresh legislation—were likely to lead immediately to fresh legislation, giving the tenantry of Ireland further protection against acts of injustice — he felt convinced that the public opinion of the landlord class would set itself in motion with a view of preventing those acts of injustice, and preventing the minority, whether large or small, from so using the law as to compel the Government to put a stop to their actions. He would ask the right hon. Gentleman, also, whether he would consent to lay upon the Table of the House a Return showing the number of such cases where, in his opinion, after making such inquiry, the enforcement of the law had been attended by practical injustice to tenants, and further showing the circumstances upon which such opinion was formed, and also giving the names of the landlord and tenant in each case. Further, he would ask him whether he would agree—and he looked upon this as a most important point— whether he would agree largely to limit the practice of charging the cost of extra police upon particular districts or baronies? With the permission of the Committee, he would beg leave to be allowed to say a few words with regard to this matter upon which the Government had informed the House, in reply to his question, that they had power. He was informed, upon good legal authority, that there was considerable doubt whether the Government had power to charge the cost of the extra police drafted into a district on the report of apprehended disturbances, or apprehended riots, or past disturbances, or crimes—there was doubt whether power existed in the Government, under the 4 [and] 5 Vict., to levy the cost of such extra police upon the districts or baronies into which they might be sent. He hoped that before the conclusion of these debates to hear from the Law Officers of the Crown in Ireland some explanation as to the method of procedure by which the extra cost of such police was now levied upon the ratepayers. Under the system in force up to the expiration of the Peace Preservation Act, the cost of the extra police was levied in a particular way, and it was possible for the ratepayers, upon whom the charges were levied, to traverse them, and to take the opinion of the Courts as to their legality. But he was informed that there existed no such mode of testing the legality of the charges under the present system. He believed that Grand Juries, or other bodies by whom the rates were levied, might levy a rate for the cost of such extra police, and that the ratepayers were absolutely unable, and had no power whatever, to take the opinion of any of the Courts in the Kingdom as to the legality of the charge; in other words, the rates were levied and were collectable by the whole force of the police, and yet the people who had to pay them had no possibility of obtaining the opinion of the Courts upon the legality of such levy. The way in which those rates were levied would scarcely be believed with reference to any part of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland in the 19th century. A police officer was sent down, and placed himself, with his iron hut, upon a vacant piece of ground, and levied the rate for the maintenance of himself and his men upon the inhabitants of the district or barony in which he might be. He thought that when they were asked for money, for the purpose of inflicting upon the people of Ireland further hardships, he was entitled to have some assurance from Her Majesty's Government that they would use this power with the greatest possible circumspection, and that they would largely diminish the number of cases in which this tax was to be charged upon the unfortunate people in the starving districts. In reply to a Question put earlier in the Session to the right hon. Gentleman, asking him whether the police tax had not been levied upon certain Crown lands or districts, and whether three-fourths of the people were not upon the Relief List, the right hon. Gentleman said that that was the case, and that that was one of the reasons which induced the Government not to renew the Peace Preservation Act. But it now turned out that the Government had precisely the same view in respect of levying the cost of extra police under the 4 [and] 5 Vict., as they had under the Peace Preservation Act, although the rate was to be levied for purposes not contemplated when that Statute was passed. The purpose of the Statute of the 4 [and] 5 Vict, was plain to anyone who read it; it was for the purpose of enabling the Government to charge the cost of extra police upon certain districts, when it was found necessary to remove a portion of the force from one county to another. The Government now turned round and claimed the credit, on the one hand, for not renewing the Peace Preservation Act, and, on the other, declared that they had precisely the same power for levying this rate under the 4 [and] 5 Vict. Speaking from his own experience, he should say that this tax was one of the most odious that had ever been collected—he would go further, and say that it was one of the least possible utility. It might be said that the tax would be inflicted because it was found that outrages had been committed, and that great difficulty existed in the districts amongst the people to give evidence and facilities for the purpose of obtaining the conviction of the offenders who had committed such outrages. He would ask Her Majesty's Government whether they intended to levy this tax from motives of revenge, or from a desire to alter the existing state of things? If they proposed to do so from a desire to alter this state of things and to change this disposition, which, he admitted, did exist amongst the people in the districts of Ireland where agrarian outrages were committed, and where there was a desire to shield a criminal from justice—if they acted in this way for the purpose of changing the feelings of the people, he might take it for the moment that if they were likely to succeed by this course of action, then they would be justified in pursuing it. But what had been their experience in reference to the infliction of these Acts upon the people in districts where crime was committed? Had it ever brought about a more favourable state of feeling amongst the people? Had they found that the districts, where the criminals were sheltered before, had changed their opinion, and become desirous of delivering up the criminals? Had they not rather found that many men who abhorred outrage and murder, when they found that those who were innocent were made to suffer for the guilty, had become exasperated with the Government—which was so far unable to govern the country except upon the most rudimentary principles'—as to confirm them in their desire to shelter the criminals? This blood tax, for it was nothing else, was really one of the relics of barbarism in Ireland. It had not produced the effect it was intended to produce, and it did not make it more easy to discover the criminal; on the contrary, the feeling produced was only one of exasperation and disaffection against the Government in Ireland. He would ask, in view of these circumstances, whether Her Majesty's Government could not give the Committee some assurance that whatever might be the powers they possessed, they would be used with the greatest possible discrimination and discretion, and that they would largely limit the number of cases, in which districts were taxed under the old system for the support of extra police force? For his part, he would say that if the Government showed that they were going to administer those excessive powers which they possessed in Ireland, but which they had not in England, moderately and justly, he should he very glad to use any influence he might possess with the people of those districts, both publicly and privately, to prevent the commission of outrages and murders. He had always felt himself that agitation in Ireland was a most unpleasant course for them to adopt. He had always regretted that circumstances should be such that, when their times and seasons of distress occurred, they should be accompanied by attempts on the part of ignorant persons to revenge themselves upon those whom they supposed had brought about that distress, by inflicting pain upon animals. But he considered that the existence of such outrages in Ireland had been much exaggerated. They must recollect that in Ireland, in the old times, the people had, from time to time, endeavoured to resist the oppression to which they were subjected by maiming the cattle, simply because they had no other way in which they could make their wrongs known. But now public meetings and other constitutional means of expressing an opinion were open to them, and they had not the same reason for maiming cattle in the manner described or for committing other outrages. He believed that during the last century the practice of maiming cattle had enormously diminished. The facilities which were now afforded to the people to meet together in public and to express their grievances constitutionally and publicly, and the power of combination which had been taught to them, had been largely instrumental in reducing the number of outrages both upon cattle and upon individuals; for, practically speaking, there had been but very few outrages upon individuals. He had no reason to suppose but that these outrages would still further diminish, and would eventually disappear altogether. The tenantry of Ireland were able to win this battle without inflicting injury upon animals or upon their landlords, and he was convinced that they would win in the long run. He would further ask the right hon. Gentleman whether, in the event of his finding it unnecessary to call Parliament together for the purpose of obtaining further powers for protecting life and property in Ireland—if that on the other hand the landlords were, to any material extent, making use of their powers so as to force the Government to support them in their acts of injustice, he would summon Parliament for the purpose of passing a Bill which would relieve the Government from the necessity of being obliged to support injustice? The way in which the right hon. Gentleman put the matter on Tuesday was scarcely fortunate. He told them, as he had previously done, that if he found the ordinary law insufficient to enable the Government to protect life and property, he would call Parliament together to obtain additional power; and, he added, that in the event of his finding that the landlords of Ireland were, to a great extent, compelling the Government to assist them in working injustice, he would also bring forward a Bill for the purpose of preventing the occurrence of such injustice, that was to say, some kind of Land Bill. He would put it to the right hon. Gentleman that the effect of that declaration was to tell the Irish tenantry that unless they committed outrage and murder, and rendered it impossible for him to administer the ordinary law of the land, he would not bring in a Land Bill for their benefit, notwithstanding that the Government might find that any minority of the landlords of Ireland were using their powers unjustly. If he put it in this way, he would announce to all whom it might concern that, whether he was able to govern Ireland by the ordinary method of the Constitution or not, and if he found that the landlords of Ireland were, to any extent, compelling the Government during the coming autumn or winter to enforce the law in such a way as to work injustice, he would call Parliament together for the purpose of passing a Land Bill, he would free himself very much from the imputations cast upon him, as he thought very rightly, by the hon. Member for Tipperary (Mr. Dillon) and the, other hon. Members who had spoken from the Conservative Benches, in critizing [sic] his speech of Tuesday last. In conclusion, he would say that although it would appear that the Government intended to carry out the decision of their Predecessors with regard to the maintenance of that Constabulary force, still, he must say, that he felt as confident as he was of his own existence, that if that force were abolished, the necessity for the majority of changes in the Land Laws would disappear. Some people had said that it was the landlords, and the state of the Land Laws, which rendered the Constabulary necessary. He would rather put it the other way, and say that it was the Constabulary that made bad landlords in Ireland. If landlords knew that for the enforcement of their rights they had just as much assistance from public opinion, and the forces at the disposal of the Crown, as they would have in England or Scotland under similar circumstances, it would be found that that enforcement of rights would be limited in the same way as they were in this country. The deplorable necessity that existed of frequently bringing before Parliament that question would cease, and a mutual arrangement would follow between landlords and tenants with regard to their respective rights in the land. The Government, unfortunately, proposed to adopt a different course—they proposed to keep that large military force of highly-trained men in existence. They had adopted, or proposed to adopt, a new method of armament; they intended giving buckshot instead of bullets for short ranges. The Government had not, in any one respect, intimated that the force that was maintained for the carrying out of what was acknowledged to be bad law was to be reduced in the slightest degree. On the contrary, the present large numbers had been increased. The force which the right hon. Gentleman had sent for the purpose of carrying out the evictions was larger than that sent by his Predecessor, and thereby the right hon. Gentleman had taken upon himself a grave responsibility. If the result was that during this autumn or winter hardships and suffering were being imposed upon the poor tenants, the right hon Gentleman the Chief Secretary would have taken upon himself a grave responsibility both as regarded the peace of Ireland and the future relations between the two countries. He (Mr. Parnell) could not conceive of anything more calculated to turn the mind of the people away, and prevent them from assimilating themselves as was desired to the English system, than the harsh enforcement of the English Law. If the result should be that large numbers of evictions took place, and were followed by violent resistance to the police in carrying them out—a course which, he must confess, he thought less criminal and less objectionable than assassination of landlords, or houghing of cattle—then the right hon. Gentleman would have a responsibility which he thought no public man would desire to have. He had just one more observation to make. They had the employment of police at all public meetings. He had attended, he believed, every one that had been held with the exception of those held during the electoral campaign. He did not refer to the meetings of the electoral campaign, but of those of the land agitation. A large force of police, numbering from 80 to 300, attended with their rifles, bayonets, and a plentiful supply of ammunition, He would ask what, in the name of conscience, did that intimate? As far as he knew, there had not been a single riotous or disorderly proceeding, not a single instance in that series of 150 large public meetings, at times when the minds of the people were certainly very much agitated and excited; and yet, whenever he went to a meeting, he saw flanking the platform a body of Constabulary, numbering 50, drawn up in battle array. For what purpose were those men stationed there, or was there any purpose? Their services had never been called into request, and the only reason that he could suggest was that they were there for the protection of the Government shorthand writers, and that, not from the violence of the people, but simply to protect them from disturbance while taking notes. He would tell the right hon. Gentleman that that attendance, at those meetings, of the police force—which was composed of the sons of farmers—wasono [sic] great reason in favour of their becoming demoralized from the point of view of the Government, but not from his (Mr. Parnell's) point of view. He had often been struck with the intense interest those fine young men took in the speeches, which were called revolutionary by some people, which had been made at so many of those meetings. He could not but think that if the right hon. Gentleman wished to keep the Constabulary force from having any sympathy with the Land League, it were far better that he should not allow them to attend those meetings. Considering the fact that there had been no breach of the peace at the 150 public meetings to which he had already referred, he was at a loss to understand why the Government should insist upon that absurd exhibition of force which had been initiated by the late Conservative Government. He could, of course, understand that when the present Government came into Office, the right hon. Gentleman was naturally guided by the officials of Dublin Castle; he felt, no doubt, that it was not necessary to make a hasty change; and, being absorbed by his Parliamentary duties, had not the time to examine the question. He (Mr. Parnell) believed, however, that when the right hon. Gentleman went into the question and the statement that he had then made, he would find that there was not the slightest reason for the practice to which he had alluded; and that, in the future, the land meetings might be held without the presence of a large force of the Constabulary. One reason suggested for that force being present was that the Government found it necessary to send shorthand writers to take notes of the speeches, and that the police protected them. In regard to that, he would say that the right hon. Gentleman would find, when he inquired into the matter, that no real attempt had ever been made to ill-treat those shorthand writers. He could assure the right hon. Gentleman that if it were made a point of honour with the promoters of the meetings, that if the Constabulary were kept away, the Government shorthand writers should be treated courteously, and with proper regard to the usuages [sic] of war, he would find that no sort of rudeness would be offered to any of those men. He did not wish to detain the Committee at greater length. He had endeavoured to put certain practical matters before them which, he believed, required to be considered before that Vote was put from the Chair.</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
