<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>For Ireland, Brooklyn Daily Eagle, Saturday 10 January 1880</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">For Ireland</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="127046050" level="j">Brooklyn Daily Eagle</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page"></biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1880-01-10">10 Januart 1880</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7007567">New York, United States</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00082"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">    
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="18800110 Brooklyn Daily Eagle For Ireland 001"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Chairman, Ladies and Gentlemen - I trust you will excuse me if I make my observations to-night very brief, indeed, because I regret to say that I am suffering from a severe cold. There are also other reasons why I should not trespass much upon your time, because there are several distinguished men on this platform who are well entitled to speak upon the question before us, and whom you will hear with greater pleasure than you will hear me. [Cries of "No! No! No!"] Now, we have assembled here to-night for, perhaps, the noblest of all objects - to extend help to a suffering people; the help, the assistance of the people of America to those who are starving in Ireland. It is being extended silently and without publicity in many different ways. I heard yesterday from a gentleman who is connected with one of the principal banks of New York that during the last twelve months he had remitted, and chiefly to the poorest people in the west of Ireland, the sum of £80,000 from their relatives in this country - that is $400,000. [Applause.] He told me also that the proportion of these remittances had been largely increased during the past five weeks, so that you see the relatives and friends in this country of persons who are suffering in Ireland are already coming forward and are relieving them in that way. Also, throughout the whole Union relief movements have been set on foot. In almost every city of the United States organisations, I am glad to say, have been started for the purpose of joining in this movement, and we have America as among the first of the nations to relieve Irish distress. [Applause.] For my part, as one who knows only too well the terrible suffering that now exists in that country, I wish to thank you here to-night and the people of this great country for their spontaneous generosity. I am glad to say that I have received a cheering telegram from Ireland. The news during the last few days had been looking very black, but I have just received a cable from Mr. Michael Davitt. [Applause]. It is dated at Carraroe, Connemara County, in the following terms. I must explain to you before I repeat the telegram that Carraroe is the place where the police had recently fired upon the people [hisses] and where one hundred and twenty-four evictment processes had been placed in the hands of the Sheriff's officers for service. The people were indignant at the threatened ejectments, and they burned out and took the rifles from the police. [Prolonged applause]. Now this telegram that I have received from Carraroe says:</p>
         <p>THE IRISH PEOPLE HAVE TRIUMPHED.</p>
         <p>"Disturbances are over. The people have triumphed. The ejectment processes have been abandoned, and the day for serving them has expired." [Loud applause.]</p>
         <p>A voice - We thank you for it.</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - No, I don't wish to claim any to credit for that result, the credit belongs to the patient and brave people of Connemara themselves [applause], and I think they are entitled to the thanks of the whole people of Ireland for their courage and for the stand they have made on this, the turning point of the Irish campaign. [Applause.] Just as your forefathers at Lexington are entitled to your thanks for what they did, so I say the people of Connemara are entitled to our thanks and to the thanks of Ireland for the stand, and, I thank God, successful stand, that they have made on the present occasion. [Applause.] Now, the Irish land question is a very old question. It is seven hundred years old. Various attempts have been made from time to time to bring it to a successful issue. The landlords on their side have endeavored to solve it by sweeping the people out of the country. The tenants, on their side, have endeavored to solve it in various ways - by constitutional methods and by forcible methods. But that question in Ireland still remains unsolved. It still remains engaging the situation of every person who desires to see a prosperous basis of living established in that country. Now, this question could never have been settled if unusual advantages did not present themselves to us, and in attempting to settle it we were chiefly guided by a desire to assist the natural forces that are now in operation in Ireland, and which are likely to lead to a successful issue. So long as very high prices ruled for agricultural produce in Ireland, the tenantry were content to pay excessive rents; but owing to the American competition - the beef and mutton that you have been sending over in such plenty to England during the last year or two - these prices have tumbled, and the tenantry are placed to such a position that they can no longer venture to think of paying the demands upon them. Now a crisis is coming on in Ireland similar to that which opened in 1847. In 1847 an organized attempt was made to direct the people, and to show them how they might snatch safety out of the danger by which they were surrounded. In 1847, or rather subsequently to the year 1847, a large quantity - one-third - of the land in Ireland came into the market. If that land were now to come into the market, the tenants could buy it upon very easy terms. A very large number of the Irish landed proprietors were ruined by the crisis of 1847, and they were obliged to sell their estates in the Encumbered Estates Court. Now, we are working with the object - of course, it is only a very small portion of our object - but we are working, among other things, with the object of obtaining in the case of estates [indecipherable] to be sold - to facilitate the purchase of those estates at a fair price by the occupying tenants. If that had been done in the years following 1847, one-third of the cultivated lands of Ireland would be now owned by the tenants without any further need to pay; but the opportunity was lost. No attempt was made to take advantage of the [indecipherable], and consequently those lands which were sold were purchased by a class of men who had made money and who invested in these estates with the intention of obtaining as much interest on their investments as they possibly could. These men raised the rents on the tenants in almost every case. They proved themselves to be the most exacting of landlords, far worse than the men who preceded them, and instead of obtaining a partial settlement of the land question, we had the evil of the situation intensified in a very extreme degree. Now, we see that a very great many of the Irish landlords are going to be ruined. They cannot help it. It is their own fault. They have lived on their means and we don't consider that it is any part of our duty to bolster up such men, by encouraging the tenants to pay them impossible rents. [Applause.] What we have said to the Irish tenantry is: You must not pay a rent which the land has not earned this season. You must go to your landlords and ask them for a regular statement, and where this is not given, you must refuse to pay any rent at all until your landlord comes to his senses and gives you an abatement. [Applause.] Now these are the recommendations we have made. Some of you will think me rather extreme, but if they hadn’t been made the people would have paid their rents as they paid them in 1847, and would have starved afterward. We have advised them to claim a fair abatement, and in the event of this abatement not being given, we have recommended them to maintain a firm and determined attitude, and the people of Connemara have been the first to carry our lesson and teaching with practical effect. [Applause]. Well, then, what will follow? I wish you to recollect that this is only a branch of the question; it is only a portion of what we propose. I propose only to tell you of this one branch to-night because to go into the details of a question like the Irish land question, would be impossible in one single speech. What will happen? These landlords who have dipped their estates - encumbered them - and who have to pay large sums of money in interest every year, cannot afford to give their tenants an abatement of rent. They must rack rent their tenants, and if the tenants are unable to pay these rack rents these landlords must be forced to sell in the Encumbered Estates Court. Now the only result of such a thing as this must be that the tenants will now get an opportunity of buying their farms when these estates are sold. Up to the present time when these estates have been sold the landlords have refused to sell them to the tenants because they preferred to dispose of them to a single purchaser rather than to divide them up into a number of small lots and sell them to a great number of buyers. It has been a matter of convenience with them to do this because it is more convenient to sell property to one man than to a great number of persons. They have also acted from a statement which prevails among the owners of property in Ireland and England, vis.; A desire to keep up the feudal aristocracy by keeping the lands in the hands of large owners by preventing it from falling into the hands of large owners by preventing it from falling into the hands of small owners and they have therefore obstructed the attempts made by tenants to buy their farms. Now, the Land Act of 1870 - the Bright clause of the Land Act of 1870 - provides that the Government may advance two-thirds of the purchase money to the tenants to enable them to purchase their holdings when they are sold in court. These clauses were proposed by John Bright, the eminent English reformer. [Applause]. He proposed them as an experiment. He believes, with us, that the land of the country ought to be owned by those who till it. [Applause]. But he was in advance of his time. That is eight or nine years ago, and as he could only get the Legislature to adopt his clauses as an experiment in this bill. During the eight or nine years that these clauses have been in existence they have remained a dead letter, because their operation has been obstructed by the landlords in the way that I have told you. The tenants have not obtained an opportunity of taking advantage of the British clauses. This continued up to the present year. When estates were sold in Ireland they were eagerly bid for by the neighbouring land owners, who desired to add to their prestige and influence in their counties by increasing their slave interests, and, as a consequence, the purchase prices of land in Ireland appreciated very rapidly. But as soon as the present movement commenced a very remarkable change took place. No landlord is now willing to increase his interest in land, and when an estate is to be put up for sale in the Landed Estates Court the landlord is obliged to go down upon his knees to his tenants and ask them to buy it under the Bright clauses. [Applause.] So far, then, as we have worked in this direction, we have produced this result: That where estates are put into the market for sale voluntarily by the owners the tenants are now able to purchase them under the Bright clause of the Land act, at a fair market price. [Applause.] Well, ladies and gentlemen, I think if we had only done this, that we could claim that we had effected very good work, but this is really only a small portion of our programme, because we are determined never to rest satisfied until we have enabled every tenant in Ireland, where it is at all practicable or possible, to become the owner in fee simple of his own farm. [Applause.]</p>
         <p>HOW OWNERSHIP IS TO BE ACCOMPLISHED.</p>
         <p>The means by which this can be accomplished are very various. Many plans have been proposed, and the English Liberal party is in sympathy with our project in this respect. Men like Sir Charles Dilke, Mr. Chamberlain, the Member of Manchester; Mr. John Bright, Mr. Mundella and advanced English reformers, believe with us that the landlord system is an artificial system, and that so long as it exists in the country so long will the soil be cultivated at a disadvantage. They have assured us that they will help us in sweeping away this system, consequently our prospects look very bright if we can succeed in keeping our people in Ireland. But a pinch is coming this Winter, and if we allow them to be swept away the opportunity now given for settling this question will be lost. Now, ladies and gentlemen, I said at the start that I did not wish to detain you, and I must not allow myself to be carried away into the [indecipherable] of this land question. I have simply desired to content myself with the statement of a portion of our case - the ways and means that we have already for making a very large number of the tenant farmers of Ireland owners of their own farms. That portion of our undertaking is being worked out already. Land has been reduced enormously in value - about forty per cent. during the last six months - and for the first time in the history of the question, it is possible for the tenant farmers on such estates as come into the market to become the owners of their farms under the Bright clause of the Land act. I will give you one example before I sit down, to show you how the operation of working under these clauses has been obstructed by the owners of the land. In 1876, only three years ago, a very large property in Ireland was put into the market, called the Harank estate. A bid was made for it by an outsider, a foreign landlord, of seventy thousand points. The tenants came in and offered seventy-five thousand under the Bright clause of the Land act. The other person came forward and offered eighty thousand pounds, and the tenants again came forward and offered eighty-one thousand. The person who made the original offer would not increase his price, but it was knocked down to him at eighty thousand pounds, and those who offered the eighty-one thousand were not given the preference. This was because it was easier to sell the estate to one person than to sell it to a large number, and, of course, it is perfectly natural that a man who is going to sell his property should desire to sell it with the least possible trouble and expense. He would rather have his money even if it were somewhat less, in a lump sum, from one person than to wait for it from a large number. And I believe that there were two or three hundred in this case. Well, the tenants appealed against the decision of the Landed Estates Court in this matter. They said they were entitled to be declared the purchaser of this property, and their appeal was allowed by the higher court. But another appeal was taken by the person to whom the property had been knocked down, and a still higher court decided in favor of him. The tenants then took the case to the House of Lords and they were beaten in the House of Lords upon a technical point. The farmers lost the opportunity of becoming owners of their farms, they spent five or six thousand pounds in costs, and are now many of them, in the most extreme destitution. Well, now, by this movement, we have brought things into such a shape that if the estate were to come into the market to-morrow, the owner of it would beg of his tenants to buy it, and in all probability instead of getting eighty thousand pounds for it, he would get either fifty or sixty thousand. Now you will have [indecipherable] from the drift of our remarks that our principal object in this matter is to make a settlement of this land question possible. In order to obtain a settlement of any question in Ireland from the Imperial Parliament you have to make it a burning question. Mr. Gladstone himself admitted the other day, when speaking in Mid Lothian, that it was not until a police constable had been shot at Manchester in the discharge of his duty, by the Fenians, and Clerkenwell Prison blown up that the Irish Church question came within the domain of practical English politics. He admitted in that way that you have to direct English public opinion, that you have to act upon it in some extraordinary and unusual way in order to obtain any consideration of the Irish land question. And this is only natural. The English people have their own business to attend to. They live in another country. Their affairs are not our affairs. It is not natural to suppose that Englishmen will turn aside from the consideration of their own domestic and political interests in order to interest themselves in any Irish question. We are in this unfortunate position, that in Ireland we are governed by a people who do not live in Ireland, who have no knowledge whatever of our affairs, and who have no interest or inducement to make them acquire such a knowledge. We are, therefore, in an exceptional position. Our difficulties are very great and you must therefore excuse us if in order to obtain a settlement we are obliged to make the stand we do. [Applause.] This movement has been a constitutional one and has been carried on without violence on the part of the people, but the English press has made vague assertions that landlords were being shot, and cattle being mutilated, but in no case have they ventured to bring forward any particular instance, and it is a remarkable fact that during the whole agitation there has not been a single outrage of any consequence committed by the people, and the only blood that has been shed is the blood of the peasants of Connemara, who were fired upon the other day by soldiers sent there by the landlords to aid the police. [Applause.]</p>
         <p>A CONSTITUTIONAL MOVEMENT.</p>
         <p>Ladies and gentlemen, this is a constitutional movement, and we have a desire to retain it within the strict letter of the law. we have told the people that they must retain an attitude of passive resistance, and up to the present time they have maintained that attitude most cheerfully, and we have assured them if they continue to do so their cause is won, and their fortitude makes us hope we shall pass over this Winter in safety and quiet, and we have strong hopes without much bloodshed and without much suffering. [Applause.] But let us not suppose that a great cause like this can be won without shedding a drop of blood, but the whole tendency up to this time has been toward the restraining of useless suffering, and as I said the other day we have saved the lives of the landlords and the lives of the people, for if the people had been left to themselves, as they were in 1847, then the landlordism was synonymous with evictions, but up to the present time there have been no evictions. I had the other day a letter from a gentleman who said that all he knew of the suffering in '48 he had learned from the Irish papers, but he wished to thank the gentlemen engaged in the present land movement, as he saw that while the papers of '48 teemed with notices of evictions, the papers of to-day teemed with notices of reductions. [Applause.] The people instead of being evicted, have been in many cases successful in obtaining a very large reduction in their rent. Now, we ask you to do your part in this great work, we don't ask you to sent armed expeditions over to Ireland. [A voice, "That is what we would like to do," and applause.] I know that you would like to do that very much. [Applause and "right."] I think I know what you are going to say, and what you would like to do, and how willing you will be to help us all. [Applause.] But we ask you to help us in preventing the people who have taken our advice, and who are exhibiting an attitude of devotion which has never been surpassed; what we ask you to do is to help us in preventing these people from being starved to death. That you can do, and while you are thus helping these people you will have the satisfaction of feeling that you are engaged in the noble work of charity; and while you are doing that you will know that you are assisting in breaking down a system which has proved the ruin and destruction of Ireland. This is not a new enterprise; this struggle has gone on for many centuries, and it is bound to go on to the bitter end, and in one way or another the Irish people will insist upon having the land of Ireland for themselves [applause], and the end of it will be that then the men who till the soil will also own it. [Applause.] The high heart of our country remains unquelled; the will and the courage of our race are unquenched, and they are strengthened by the spectacle of the fine estate and by the great power of our people in this free land. [Loud applause.] I feel confident that the day is very near at hand when we shall have struck the first blow, the first vital blow, at the land system as it now exists in Ireland, and when we shall have taken the first step to obtain for Ireland that right to nationhood for which she has struggled so long and so well. [Loud and continued applause.]</p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
