<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>The Home Rule League, The Freeman's Journal, Wednesday 1 December 1875</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">The Home Rule League</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="315698503" level="j">The Freeman's Journal</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1875-12-01">1 December 1875</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7001306">Dublin, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00029"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">     
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url=""></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, M.P., in proposing the election of Mr. Haley and Mr. Hackett as members of the League, said the well-attended meeting in the room showed to the English people that the people of Ireland had a great many things to talk of, a great many grievances to expose, and that they were able to expose them. they had the other day a very remarkable instance of the effects of the Home Rule meetings. Sir Michael Hicks Beach had been obliged to run off to Belfast to find an audience who would listen to him (laughter), for he could not find one in Dublin who would listen to a British statesman abusing seven-eighths of the people of this country. It was a lesson for us all when an English statesman went before a small section of the Irish people, and told them that he looked to that very small section as a help and assistance to England on some future occasion when Ireland's opportunity came. Sir Michael Hicks Beach thereby admitted a great weakness somewhere. He admitted that there must be some very lamentable and alarming defect in the State, but if the English Government would dare to trust the Irish people a little they would not find it so very hard to govern the country (hear, hear). From the beginning to the end there had been a want of trust and confidence. He was not prepared to say how long that would be the case, but he hoped the day would soon come when England would see her mistake, and recognise the people of this country as a self-[indecipherable] people, who would insist on their right to self-government, and who would have it (hear, hear, and applause). He did not care when or how it was to be, but he was convinced that whether by peaceful solution, by the pressure of circumstances, or by other methods which he was not there to enlarge upon, the day would come when the Irish people would be self-governing, self-reliant, and self-respecting (applause). Until then let not England go to war with any foreign nation (hear, hear). Let her not enter into any alliance offensive or defensive (hear, hear). Let her not back up certain Powers, like Egypt (hear, hear, and applause). England had to look to herself, for hers was a power that would want supporting if Irish grievances were not redressed. When events were going on in the world which at any moment might result in war it was time for Ireland to speak plainly and to warn England that she must redress Irish grievances. Let England have in the strong arms of the Irish people her best defences; if not, she was defenceless. Her money would not be her safety (hear, hear). Ireland would not always be foolish. She would not always miscalculate her own strength; but would constitutionally while she could work out her own future and her own safety (applause).</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
