<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Imperial Parliament, The Irish Times, Tuesday 8 June 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Imperial Parliament</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="144709869" level="j">The Irish Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-06-08">8 June 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7001306">Dublin, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00053"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">   
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/viewer/BL/0001683/18860608/097/0004?browse=true"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell (who was warmly cheered by his party) said - If I intervene in this contest of gravity which has been proceeding so many days it is not because I suppose my intervention is specially suited to the occasion. Under ordinary circumstances I should have lacked self-confidence following so able and eloquent a member of the House; but "Thrice is he armed who hath his quarrel just" - (cheers) - and, inferior as I am in many points of view, I hope I shall not be so far behind as usual. (Hear, hear.) Without intending to offer any disrespect to the right hon. gentleman, I could not help thinking, listening to his speech, that in all the lost causes with which I have seen him connected during many years past he was never so little effective as in contending against the bill we hope to read for a second time to-night. (Hear, hear.) He has sought, I think very unfairly, to cast a lurid light on the situation by allusion to</p>
         <p>THOSE UNHAPPY OUTRAGES IN KERRY.</p>
         <p>Sir, I join the right hon. gentleman in the expression of my contempt for those cowardly, disgraceful practices - I join him to the fullest extent. (Hear, hear.) but, sir, rather do I say it is because evictions have been more numerous in Kerry than in all the rest of Munster put together during months past. I do not say that that constitutes an excuse for these outrages, or any excuse for outrages, though it may supply us with the cause of them. But when I denounce outrage I denounce them in every part of Ireland, whether they occur in Ulster or in Kerry. (Hear, hear.) The right hon. gentleman himself is certainly free from reproach. He has not joined the noble lord (Churchill) and the right hon. gentleman (Mr Chamberlain) in the use of reckless language with reference to the affairs of a country which is not their country - (hear, hear) - an interference for which they have not even the paltry excuse that it was any business of theirs or that they had any interest there. My colleagues have in times past been reproached because they have not been careful into looking into the effect of their language, and the doctrine of indirect responsibility has been employed against them to the extent of imprisonment. If that doctrine of indirect responsibility were employed against the noble lord and the right hon. gentleman (Mr Chamberlain), the former might plead for excuse that he himself is nothing and nobody but himself, so that he could not expect any great importance to be attached to his declarations (hear, hear, and laughter) - while the right hon. gentleman might have said, and said very truly, that he was absolutely ignorant of all the circumstances of Ireland. His celebrated projected visit to that country last autumn not having come off, he really could not know what would be the effect of his language. (Hear, hear.) However, we have</p>
         <p>THE RESULT NOW IN ONE MURDER ALREADY COMMITTED IN BELFAST.</p>
         <p>And I trust that in future hon. and right hon. gentlemen will remember the importance and gravity of the occurrences which may follow in ulster. Those occurrences cannot go further at the outside than outrage and assassination, but will depend very much upon what is said on the subject, and the amount of importance given to the doings of Ulster men. We do say and admit that these occurrences are to be condemned and should be stopped; but while the noble lord and the right hon. gentleman say they must be put an end to by resorting to the coercion which they and their friends have been using in the last 86 years, we say with the Prime Minister</p>
         <p>"TRY THE EFFECT OF SELF-GOVERNMENT."</p>
         <p>(Cheers.) Then, if Kerry men resort to outrage, they will very soon find the rest of Ireland will put a stop to it. (renewed cheers.) Well, sir, the right hon. gentleman referred to the recent events in Belfast, but before I deal with that terrible matter I wish to give an explanation, because as usual some of the English newspapers have perverted for their own purposes what I believe actually took place. (Irish cheers.) I was pained to see that the struggle is alleged to have arisen out of an expression used by a Catholic to a fellow-workman who was a Protestant to the effect that in a short time more none of his persuasion should be allowed to earn a crust of bread in Ireland. That, however, does not accurately represent the state of facts as reported in the local newspapers. (Cheers and counter cheers.) According to them</p>
         <p>WHAT TOOK PLACE WAS THIS.</p>
         <p>A Catholic overseer of the works found fault with the way in which an Orange, or at all events a Protestant workman, was executing the digging of a drain. The overseer said, "That is a nice way to do the work," whereupon the Orangeman replied to his overseer, who happened to be a Catholic, "What does a Papist know about digging drains?" - (laughter) - and the overseer irritated - I do not say justly irritated, because it was absurd for him to have been irritated by such a remark - said to the Orangeman "You will never earn a crust on the works again," meaning that he was dismissed. Upon that the Orangeman took his shovel and left his work. I believe as he was going out he was assaulted by one or more of the workmen. (Derisive laughter.) It is very difficult to know actually what took place, but it is of great importance that the House should understand that the remark in question had not a general application, but only an individual one: (Parnellite cheers.) I do not attempt to justify the occurrence, because it was a very sad one. (Hear, hear.) Mr Goschen has spoken about</p>
         <p>THE SOVEREIGNTY OF PARLIAMENT,</p>
         <p>and upon this point I entirely agree with the definition given by the Secretary for Foreign Affairs. (Cheers.) We know perfectly well - we have always known since this bill was introduced - the difference between a co-ordinate and a sub-ordinate Parliament. (Cheers.) We knew that the legislature the Prime Minister wishes to constitute is a subordinate Parliament, not like Grattan's, which was co-equal - (Mr. Gladstone - Hear, hear) - arising out of the same constitution and in the same manner as this Parliament given by the Sovereign. (Ministerial cheers.) We understand this perfectly well, and we should undoubtedly have preferred, as I stated on the introduction of the bill, as showing that I could not accept this as a final settlement of the question, we should have preferred the restitution of the Grattan Parliament. (Parnellite cheers.) It would have been more in accord with the sentiments of the Irish people, and sentiment goes a long way with people like the Irish. (Cheers.) At the same time I am bound to say that if I should have preferred a Grattan Parliament there are practical advantages in the proposals before us which limit and subordinate the Parliament to that in which we now act. It may be of even greater advantage to the Irish people than a Parliament like Grattan's, and much more likely to be a final settlement of the question. (Hear, hear.)</p>
         <p>GRATTAN'S PARLIAMENT HAD MANY DISADVANTAGES.</p>
         <p>In the first place it had a House of Lords. (Hear and a laugh.) We get rid of the House of Lords under the constitution of the right hon. gentleman. (Cheers.) It is true there is to be in its place the first order - a very salutary provision - I do not pledge myself to all the details and qualifications - but I say, generally, that the first order is a very salutary provision, which will tend to prevent hasty legislation and immediate action - (cheers) - and I would rather see a bill hung up for ten years by a body like the first order in Ireland than I would see it hung up for a single twenty-four hours by this Imperial Parliament. (Hear, hear.) I venture to express the opinion that the constant action of the Imperial Parliament, the constant means of overseeing as is suggested by the member for West Birmingham (Mr Chamberlain) would not have the same success, and would not be so acceptable to the people of Ireland as the measure now proposed by the Government. (Hear, hear.) Indeed the proposals of the member for West Birmingham would, I believe, be mischievous and dangerous, and would prevent any settlement being arrived at satisfactory to the Irish people. (Home Rule cheers.) On the other hand, when we are assembled in our own Chamber in Ireland - all the different sections of the Irish people - those causes and effects which always arise will come into operation again, and will lead to satisfactory results.</p>
         <p>THE RESULT OF THE TWO ORDERS WORKING TOGETHER</p>
         <p>in the same chamber will enable great questions to be settled on a basis of compromise more or less satisfactory to all parties. (Cheers.) We understand perfectly well that the Imperial Parliament has the ultimate supremacy and the ultimate sovereignty. I quite agree with the Prime Minister - and I think it is one of the most valuable parts of the bill - I quite agree that that which the Prime Minister offers - namely, the responsibility of maintaining order in Ireland, by the Irish Parliament is a correct provision, and one which no State could exist without. (Irish cheers.) The supremacy of the Imperial Parliament, however, will not be affected by this if the Irish Parliament execute the powers given to it, whilst in some cases it may be rendered more effective than ever. (Hear, hear.) In accepting the bill we accept honourable obligations, and</p>
         <p>WE PLEDGE OURSELVES FOR THE IRISH PEOPLE</p>
         <p>as far as we can pledge ourselves - (derisive cheering and laughter) - that the powers given shall not be abused - (Parnellite cheers) - to devote all the energy, ability, and influence we may have with our people to prevent them abusing the powers entrusted to them. (Cheers.) But if abuses do take place the Imperial Parliament may intervene in cases of grave emergency. You have the power, you have the authority, you have the force, and, if crimes are perpetrated, you have the remedy in your own hands. (Hear, hear.) In a case of this kind you have just the same authority you would have whether the bill had been brought forward or not, and this we recognise. I said this on the introduction of the bill. I said we would accept it as a final settlement, and that I believed the Irish people would do so. I will say no more upon that point; but my words have been singularly justified. (Parnellite cheers.) We have had this measure accepted by all the leaders of every section of national feeling in Ireland and also outside Ireland, in the United States as well as in every country where the Irish people were found. (Cheers.) We have not had a single voice raised against the bill by any Irishman. (Cheers and cries of "Oh, oh.") Certainly not by any Irishman of Nationalist opinion, and of course, there are sections among the Irish Nationalists; just as there are sections in the great Conservative party. (Hear, hear.) In fact as far as it was possible for the nation to accept the measure cheerfully, freely, thankfully, and without reserve, I say that the Irish people have shown that they have so accepted this measure. (Cheers.) Even the terrible Irish World [italics] newspaper which has not been on my side for the last five or six years, says the Irish race at home and abroad have signified their willingness to accept the terms of peace offered by Mr. Gladstone. (Cheers.) I say then that</p>
         <p>AS FAR AS THE IRISH PEOPLE CAN ACCEPT THIS BILL THEY HAVE ACCEPTED IT,</p>
         <p>and they have accepted it without any reserve whatever as a measure which may be considered a final settlement of a great question. Now, sir, I leave the question of the sovereignty of Parliament, and go to another point which ahs been touched on by the right hon. gentleman the Member for East Edinburgh (Mr Goschen). He has fairly told us of his fears as to the abuse of power by</p>
         <p>THE IRISH PRIESTHOOD IN REGARD TO THE QUESTION OF EDUCATION,</p>
         <p>and he has not followed the example of other illustrious speakers by indulging in extravagant language in regard to this Catholic-Protestant question. (Hear, hear.) I may say that I am quite sure his apprehension is genuine as far as it goes, and that he does not desire to see anything in the shape of religious discord in Ireland. Indeed, I will not say that, as a Protestant myself, if I had not had abundant experience of the feeling in Ireland I might not perhaps be inclined to share his fear, but as it is I certainly have no such fear. (Hear.) It is rather remarkable in regard to this question of education that the right hon. gentleman the member for West Birmingham (Mr Chamberlain) proposed to give to a central council in Dublin the executive control over education in Ireland without any reserve whatever in regard to Protestants or Catholics. (Cheers.) It is, however, very hard to please everybody, and if we were to please the right hon. gentleman the member for West Birmingham by agreeing to give education to the control of the body which the Prime Minister proposes to establish we should be unfortunate in running foul of the right hon. gentleman the member for East Edinburgh. (Hear, hear.) But I think I can assure the right hon. gentleman that we shall be able to settle this question of education very well among ourselves. (Cheers.) There are many Liberal Nationalists. I call them Liberal Nationalists because I think it is the right phrase in reference to its application to education as to which they are Liberal - that is, they do not share the views of the Roman Catholic Church on the question of education. There are, I say, many Liberal Nationalists in Ireland who very much desire to see the people of Ulster sharing the responsibilities or the feeling they have with regard to education, and I can assure the House that with Ulster in an Irish Legislature, and with such representatives as we see coming from Ulster to this House, there would not be the slightest risk, even if there were any idea on the part of the Catholic Hierarchy of using their power unfairly against the Protestants, that such a thing would ever take place. (Cheers.) We should be able to settle this question to the satisfaction of everybody concerned among ourselves. (Cheers.) But, before leaving the question of education, there is one thing I must remind the House with reference to the question of education - namely, that denominational education would undoubtedly be established in Ireland. (Cheers.) This subject has been already considered. The right hon. gentleman the member for West Birmingham thinks that denominational education would be the right thing Ireland, and we may say that if Parliament remains as it is, and Ireland as she is, we should find denominational education, without effective control, impossible on the part of the Protestants of Ulster. The right hon. gentleman the member for East Edinburgh spoke of</p>
         <p>THE LINEN TRADE.</p>
         <p>I have not had the advantage of reading the correspondence to which he referred, but it appeared to me to tend to prove that the linen trade of Ulster not directly, but indirectly, has acted injuriously, because it had induced the peasantry to pay rack-rents which the landlords would not otherwise have insisted on. (Hear, hear.) I think the right hon. gentleman was not quite fair in regard to this question, and I observed a similar reticence to that which characterised his dealing with the matter just referred to when he dealt with the financial question, on which he made such a point on the first reading of this bill in a speech which undoubtedly produced a great sensation all over the country. I and others who listened to that speech understood him to argue that Ulster was wealthier than either of the other three provinces, and that so heavy a share of the burden would fall on Ulster that it would be impossible to carry on the Government of Ireland. The right hon. gentleman's comparison of</p>
         <p>THE GREAT WEALTH OF ULSTER WITH THE OTHER PROVINCES</p>
         <p>has been taken up by the Loyal and Patriotic Unions throughout the country as a sort of war cry. The right hon. gentleman chose as his standard of comparison schedule D of the income tax, referring to trades and professions, but surely the plain standards of relative wealth are the assessments under all the schedules, as well as the value of ratable [sic] property. Had he taken these he would have shown that so far from Ulster being the wealthiest of the four provinces she comes in reality third, coming after Leinster and Munster, and being only superior to impoverished Connaught. These standards of income tax show, for Leinster, £10 6s 9d per head; Munster, £6 0s 7d; Ulster, £5 14s 3d; and Connaught, £3 13s 7d. The relative proportions of wealth in decimals being 9.92 for Leinster, 5.78 for Munster, 5.49 for Ulster - or little more than half the wealth of Leinster - and 3.43 for Connaught. (Cheers.) If you take any other fair test the result will be the same. But the right hon gentleman also argued that there was great disparity between the Protestant counties, or the north-eastern counties, and the Catholic counties of Ulster, and he showed the disparity to be a great deal larger than it really is through the system of comparison. He chose a system that was not a fair one, but the one that would show best for his argument. Undoubtedly there is a disparity between the relative wealth of the north-eastern counties and the other counties; but the same disproportion runs through Ireland. If you draw a meridian line through Ireland, the counties to the west are comparatively poor. The reason is obvious. The wealth of the country goes towards the trading coast. The trade of Ireland, the ports and shipping and the main distributing centres, where men of business and wealth congregates, are found on the east, and as is only natural, the east of Ulster and Munster and Leinster are wealthier than the west of those provinces. (Hear, hear.) We come now to the question of</p>
         <p>THE PROTECTION OF THE LOYAL MINORITY.</p>
         <p>It is one upon which great attention has been bestowed. One would think that the Protestants of Ireland were going to be handed over to the tender mercies of Thugs and bandits. (Major Saunderson - Hear, hear.) The hon. and gallant member for North Armagh cheers that. I only wish I was as safe in the North of Ireland when I go there as the hon. and gallant gentleman would be in the South. (Home Rule cheers.) What do these gentlemen mean by the protection of the loyal minority? In the first place I would ask what they mean by the loyal minority? (Hear, hear.) The right hon. gentleman the member for East Edinburgh does not seem to have made up his mind even at this late stage of the debate as to what the loyal minority is. When asked he said that he meant the same loyal minority as that which was referred to by the Prime Minister in his speech, but he would not commit himself by telling us what significance he attributed to the Prime Minister's statemen. I have examined the Prime Minister's references since then, and I find the Prime Minister referred to the whole province of Ulster. He did not select a little bit of the province, because the Opposition had not discussed the point at the time; consequently I suppose I may assume that the right hon. gentleman the member for East Edinburgh also refers to the whole province of Ulster when he asks that special protection should be given. But he has not told us how he would specially protect it; but we may take it from the plans of some of his colleagues. It is one of the features of this debate that you have to go the round of the Opposition speaking, and select a little bit from one and a little bit from another and a little bit from a third, in order to make some sort of coherent plan of opposition, and even then the results are very unsatisfactory; but the right hon. gentleman the member for West Birmingham has supplied a plan. He has claimed for Ulster - and I suppose the right hon. gentleman the member for East Edinburgh, when the proper time comes, will support him in the claim - he has claimed</p>
         <p>A SEPARATE LEGISLATURE FOR ULSTER.</p>
         <p>Well, sir, you would not protect the loyal minority of Ireland, even supposing you gave a separate Legislature to the province of Ulster, because there are outside that province 400,000 Protestants who would still be without any protection. So far as you propose to give it then you would make the position of these 400,000 Protestants, by taking away Ulster from them, infinitely less secure. (Hear, hear.) You would not even protect the Protestants of Ulster, because the Protestants, according to the last census, were in the proportion of 52 to 48, and we have every reason to believe that now the Protestants and Catholics in Ulster are about equal in number. At all events, however that may be, the Nationalists have succeeded in returning the majority of the Ulster members. (Home Rule cheers.) The main reason why we have a majority of the Ulster members is that a large proportion of Protestant Nationalists voted in the closely divided constituencies throughout Ulster in favour of the Nationalist candidates, so you would still have the Nationalists to deal with in Ulster, even supposing you had a separate Legislature there, and the very first thing that an Ulster Legislature would do would be to unite itself with the Dublin Parliament. (Hear.) Well, sir, driven away from the fiction of Protestant Ulster, the opponents of the bill upon this point seek refuge in the North-east corner of Ulster, consisting of three counties. Then there comes in the difference that, instead of protecting the majority of Protestants, by constituting a Legislature for the North-east corner of Ulster, you would abandon the majority of the Protestants of Ireland to their fate under a Dublin Parliament. Seven-twelfths of the Protestants of Ireland live outside of the three counties in the North-east corner of Ulster, and only five twelfths of the Protestants live inside them, so that, whatever way you put it, you must give up the idea of protecting the Protestants of Ireland by the establishment of a separate Legislature either in Ulster or in any portion of Ulster. Now, sir,</p>
         <p>WE CANNOT GIVE UP A SINGLE IRISHMAN.</p>
         <p>(Hear, and cheers.) We want the energy, the patriotism, the talent, and the work of every Irishman - (hear, here) - to ensure that this great experiment should be a success. The best system of government for a country I believe to be one which requires that that government should be the result of all the forces of the country. (Hear, hear.) We cannot give away to a legislature any portion of the talent and influence of the Protestants. This class will form a most valuable element in the Irish legislature, constituting as they will a strong minority, and exercising through the first order a moderating influence on the making of laws. We have heard of the danger which will beset the first trial by an untrained and prentice legislature. I regard their presence as vitally necessary in the Irish Parliament. We want all creeds and all classes in our Parliament. (Hear, hear.) We cannot consent to look upon a single Irishman as not belonging to us, and however much we recognise their great ability - we admit the ability of the Irish Protestants and their influence - we cannot admit that there is a single one of them too good to take part in the work. We admit there is a small proportion of them who fear the treatment they will receive at the hands of an Irish Parliament. We shall do our best, as we have been doing, to allay the fears of this small section. When this bill becomes an Act we shall not cease from the work of conciliating the fears of this small section of the Irish people. Theirs is not the shame and disgrace of those fears. The shame and disgrace belong to the right hon. gentlemen and to the lords belonging to English political parties who for the selfish interests of these English political parties seek to rekindle the almost expiring embers of political and religious rancour. (Home Rule cheers.) Ireland had never injured the right hon. gentleman the member for West Birmingham. I do not know why he should have added the strength of his powerful aid, and why he should have thrown his sword into the [indecipherable] against us, and why he should seek to dash the cup from the lips of the Irish people - the first cup of cold water that has been offered to our nation since the recall of Lord Fitzwilliam. This settlement will, I believe, be a final settlement. (Hear, hear.) It has been reproached and it has been made an argument against the honesty of my declaration with regard to the final character of the settlement that I have claimed the right of protecting Irish manufactures, and that this bill gives no protection to the Irish manufactures. Well, sir, undoubtedly we claimed that right, but it was not when the Liberal party was in power. (A laugh.) That speech at Wicklow about protection was made at a time when we had every reason to know that the Conservative party, if they should be successful at the polls, would have offered to Ireland</p>
         <p>A STATUTORY LEGISLATURE WITH A RIGHT TO PROTECT HER OWN MANUFACTURES</p>
         <p>- (laughter, and loud Ministerial and Home Rule cheers) - and that this would have been coupled with a settlement of the Irish land question on the basis of purchase on a larger scale than that now proposed by the Prime Minister. (Renewed cheering.) I should not have thought, and I never did think, and I don't think now, of claiming the right of protecting Irish manufactures from the Liberal party. I never expected it, and I don't expect it now. Therefore I recognise the settlement as a final settlement without protection. But there is another and a stronger argument still. The Prime Minister showed us when he introduced the bill that we should lose £1,400,000 a year which will come to us as a consequence of fiscal union and the absence of protection is a very good quid pro quo, as I have said before, for the loss of protection. The question of</p>
         <p>THE RETENTION OF THE IRISH MEMBERS AT WESTMINSTER</p>
         <p>is one on which I shall touch very slightly. With regard to this matter I have always desired to keep my mind thoroughly open, and not to make it a vital question. I have seen great difficulties - difficulties rather from your point of view than from ours - and I think that when we come to consider the question in committee those difficulties will grow; but I don't desire in any sense to prejudge the question, I count the existence of a strong sentiment on the part of Liberal members. I won't say it is a very reasonable sentiment when I consider how many times my colleagues and I have been forcibly ejected, and how even the necessity of suspending the representation of Ireland in this House has been eagerly canvassed by the London Press, as the only necessary solution of the Irish question. It is a difficult question, and requires very serious consideration. When the Prime Minister has produced his plan we shall without binding ourselves to it beforehand, examine it candidly with the desire to see in it elements which will not injure the permanency of the settlement. We have gone through it all before. I know the reign of coercion there has been during the last five years. You will require</p>
         <p>AN EVEN SERVERER AND MORE DRASTIC MEASURE OF COERCION</p>
         <p>than you have now. You will require everything you have had during the last five years, and more besides - (Home Rule cheers) - and of what sort has that coercion been? (Renewed Home Rule cheers.) I do not say this to inflame passions and to embitter animosity, but you have had during these five years the suspension of the Habeas Corpus Act in Ireland, you have had a thousand of our Irish fellow-subjects held in prison without a specific charge, many of them for long periods of time, some of them for twenty months without trial and without any intention of placing them on trial. (Hear, hear, and cheers.) You have had the right of domicile infringed at any hour of the day or night, and you have fined the innocent for the offences committed by the guilty. (Hear, hear.) You have taken power to expel aliens from the country, you have renewed the Curfew law and blood money of your Norman conquerors, you have gagged the Press and seized and suppressed newspapers, you have manufactured now crimes and offences and applied fresh penalties unknown to your law. All these and much more you have done in the last five years - (Home Rule cheers) - and all this and much more you will do again. (Loud Opposition cheers.) The provision in the bill for terminating the Irish representation here has been vehemently attacked, and Mr Trevelyan said there was no half-way house between separation and the executive autonomy of the Irish people. I say with just as much belief and just as much experience as the right hon. gentleman that in my judgment there is no half-way house between granting legislative autonomy to Ireland and the disenfranchisement and disseverance of that country. But, sir, I refuse to believe that those evils will come. I am convinced that there are a sufficient number of members of this House who will disregard the appeal made to their passions which has been made, and that when the numbers in the division lobby shall have been told to-night it will be known that this Parliament in the nineteenth-century was wise enough and brace enough and generous enough to agree to give peace and happiness to suffering Ireland. (Loud and long-continued cheering.)</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
