<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Mr. Parnell, M.P., on Mr. Gladstone's Speech and the Irish Vote in Liverpool, The Weekly Freeman's Journal, Saturday 14 November 1885</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Mr. Parnell, M.P., on Mr. Gladstone's Speech and the Irish Vote in Liverpool</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="176484528" level="j">The Weekly Freeman's Journal</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">2</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1885-11-14">14 November 1885</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7001306">Dublin, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00078"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>police report; newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">    
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="NAI/CSO/INL 7"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr. Parnell, M.P., said - I cannot describe to you the pleasure and the gratification which it gives me to be once more amongst you in Liverpool (applause). You have many times gathered together in your thousands, in this and other halls in this city, for the purpose of cheering and sustaining me, in the days gone by, in the difficult work which we had in hand; and now, as the goal seems to be drawing near, when the hour of conflict and, as we believe, of decisive victory is at hand, I am glad to find my countrymen in Liverpool extending to me such a greeting as I have experienced, and do not think the less of me after so many years absence from them (applause). You are met together to consider a very grave and very important question - the question of how your votes shall be given in the approaching contests for the divisions of Liverpool (cheers). The Irish people in Liverpool constitute an important factor in each and all of these divisions, and I believe that recognising that truth they will hold themselves aloof from all English political parties (hear), just as your Irish members in the House of Commons do, and that you will give your votes apart from all local and personal considerations (hear, hear) on the side on which it may seem that you may most advantage the cause of Ireland (applause). That is what I am here to ask you to do - that you should refrain from joining any English political party in Liverpool (hear, hear).</p>
         <p>A Voice - So we will (cheers).</p>
         <p>Mr. Parnell - And that you should yourselves solely as Irishmen upon whom a great trust and solemn responsibility rests at this moment - a greater trust, I do not hesitate to say, than has ever rested upon Irishmen at any time in their past history (hear, hear). and I believe that recognising that responsibility you, the Irish people of Liverpool, will upon this, as upon every other emergency in your history, be equal to the occasion, and that you will do your duty by Ireland (cheers).</p>
         <p>THE IRISH VOTE.</p>
         <p>I have said that the Irish vote is an important factor in each of the divisions of Liverpool. In more than one of these divisions we seem, as far as we have yet been able to gather materials, to be in a position to return candidates of our own (applause) as members of the Irish Parliamentary Party (hear, hear). Our inquiries, however, have not proceeded to a definite and conclusive point as yet with regard to the relative strength of the party beyond the Scotland Division. In the case of the Scotland Division we are convinced we have ample strength enough to beat both the two great English political parties (applause), and it has been decided by my colleagues, with my full consent and approbation, to offer for your acceptance to-night Mr. Thomas Power O'Connor as a candidate (loud and prolonged cheering). We are convinced that this gentleman, from his services, his record, and his signal ability, is one who is well qualified and well able to carry your flag in the Scotland Division to victory (cheers), and that he will poll every Irish elector who is able to come to vote (cheers). It is unnecessary for me to talk to you about Mr. O'Connor. He has been my colleague for five years in the House of Commons, and I have never found a more faithful friend or an abler comrade to fight by my side in the thick of the battle (cheers). In sending him over from Ireland to you we regret his loss, but we recognise that you in England contend under difficulties superior to those which we have now to face in Ireland, and that consequently it is our duty to offer to you the ablest and the best man we can find in the country for the special and the important services that he will undertake when he stands for the Scotland division (hear, hear). We have followed out in this practice which we have pursued with regard to difficult constituencies in the North of Ireland. The ablest men of the of the Irish Party have in every case been sent to fight the difficult Northern constituencies (cheers), and in the same way we send Mr. O'Connor over to England to wage war in. the enemy's camp (applause), and we are confident that he will wage a most successful war too (applause). Now, gentlemen, there was for a short while before the public, and before the Irish electors, another candidate, Mr. Patrick Byrne (groans and applause), with reference to this division, and Mr. Byrne left the question of his candidature entirely in my hands (cheers), and expressed to me in terms, the absolute sincerity of which I do not in the slightest degree doubt, his great unwillingness to be any party to dividing the National strength (cheers). I ventured in the interest of that same unity to advise Mr. Byrne to withdraw his candidature in favour of Mr. O'Connor, and he has commissioned me to-night to say that he does unreservedly withdraw his candidature (cheers). I think that Mr. Byrne has acted most properly in this matter (laughter and applause). He has followed the example which has been set him in many parts of Ireland at the various Conventions which have been held, where candidates who have come forward, finding that they had not the support of the majority, and that their continued candidature was likely to prove a danger to the National strength, consented to forego their claims and retired in favour of those who were selected. One must therefore appreciate this action of Mr. Byrne as fitting and worthy of the occasion (applause). Now with regard to the other divisions of Liverpool; the Exchange, Abercromy, West Toxteth and Kirkdale Divisions. In all these four divisions the Irish vote is very strong. I can't absolutely say for certain whether in any one of them we are sufficiently strong to beat both the other two parties combined, but our inquiries are still proceeding, and we hope to have figures which will be conclusive one way or the other before us in a few days. Until then we do not consider it desirable to replace the vacancy which has been created by Mr. McCarthy forced removal to fight the City of Derry.</p>
         <p>THE SELECTION FOR ULSTER.</p>
         <p>I may explain with regard to Mr. Justin McCarthy's withdrawal from candidature of the Exchange Division of Liverpool, that this was a matter forced upon him by the necessities of the situation. You will all readily admit that the capture of Derry, if we succeed in taking it, and I believe we shall succeed (loud applause), will be one of the most glorious events in our country (cheers). It was thought that only two men of the Irish Parliamentary Party could win Derry. One of these was Mr. Sexton (applause), and the other Mr. Justin McCarthy (cheers), whose name has been previously mentioned for the Exchange Division of Liverpool, and who, indeed, had, I understand, consented to stand for that division. Mr. Sexton was asked to stand for the Western Division of Belfast, and it was represented to him and to us at the same time that only he could succeed in this division of Belfast. So we were in this predicament - that if we wanted to capture one of the divisions of Belfast, Orange Belfast (cheers), and if we wanted to take Derry, that we would have to do it with Sexton and McCarthy (loud cheers). We therefore detailed Mr. Sexton for that duty in Belfast, and we were obliged very reluctantly to ask Mr. McCarthy to give us his services in Derry; and in the same way I ask you to-night to ratify Mr. McCarthy's withdrawal from your town, and to forgive us for what undoubtedly was the very short notice we gave you when taking him away from your service in the Exchange Division (cheers). We do not propose to nominate or suggest for your nomination any candidate for the Exchange or any other of the three divisions of Liverpool until we see exactly how we stand in each of these divisions, and shall have the figures which are now being collected, and the collection of which will be very materially assisted by the School Board elections which are now going on (a laugh). We shall then be in a very much better position to advise you as to what is best to be done with the other four divisions; and meanwhile with regard to these four divisions a resolution will be submitted to you pledging you who are electers [sic] of those four divisions to hold yourselves entirely aloof from the English parties, and to refrain from pledging yourselves to either Whig or Tory until we have an opportunity of going amongst you again and consulting with you further in reference to the matter (applause).</p>
         <p>CHALLENGE TO MR. GLADSTONE.</p>
         <p>I shall now pass from the local questions of elections to the general questions of the day, which are of such surpassing interest to Irishmen all the world over at the present moment. Since I last had an opportunity of speaking to you upon the National question we have had two very important utterances from English Ministers regarding it - we had the utterance of Lord Hartington (groans) a few days ago at Belfast, and we have reported to-day the great speech of Mr. Gladstone in Scotland on the same subject (some hisses and cries of "order"). I have already dealt elsewhere with the Marquis of Hartington's speech upon Irish affairs (hear, hear), but I can't help contrasting the very great difference between the tone and the attitude of these two statesmen. The Marquis of Hartington appears to me to have approached the subject with a mind embittered against Ireland (hear, hear), and determined, if he possible can, to do what he can to prevent a settlement between the two nations (hear, hear). Mr. Gladstone, on the other hand, with that breadth of statesmanship for which his name is renowned, has approached the question of Irish autonomy of Irish self-government, in an entirely different spirit (hear, hear). Undoubtedly, the speech of Mr. Gladstone, although in many respects vague and unsatisfactory, is the most important pronouncement upon the Irish National question which has ever been delivered by any English Minister (hear, hear). But having said so much, I fear that I cannot say anything more in terms of unqualified praise, because I think that from the practical point of view, from his own point of view - for his speech was, or professed to be, entirely a speech of a practical nature upon the Irish question - from a practical point of view that speech seemed to me to fail entirely, and to fall very short of the exigencies of the position. Mr. Gladstone commenced by impressing upon his hearers, with that extraordinary wealth of language of which he is a possessor, the importance of the Irish question, above all other question, and in that he alone perhaps of English statesmen and English politicians at the present moment appears to discern the truth. The Irish question, gentlemen, is undoubtedly the most important question for consideration at the present moment by English politicians. Until the Irish question is disposed of it will be utterly impossible, I was going to say, for progress to be made, but if I was to make use of any expression like that I suppose I should be accused of threatening obstruction (laughter and applause), and I wish to guard myself at the outset against being supposed to have even the idea of a threat (loud laughter), much less any threat, of obstruction; but from the nature of things it is impossible until that great Irish national question is put to rest and finally settled - it is impossible for English questions to find room or to proceed (laughter and loud cheers). Well, then, I say that Mr. Gladstone showed a true and keep appreciation of the importance of the question appreciation of [sic] pressed it upon his hearers, but he seemed to me in his speech afterwards to take up rather an inconsistent position, because he said that question was such an important one that when the demands of Ireland, having regard to the supremacy of the Crown and the authority of Parliament, were presented to the new Parliament, it would be the duty of whatever Government was in power and of Parliament to give them the most serious consideration. In other words, he proposes to decline to make any proposition of his own to the electors of the kingdom at the general election with regard to the settlement of this question. Now, I am speaking entirely from a practical point of view when I say that it appears to me that if we take Mr. Gladstone at his word, and if the Irish electors of England take him at his word and vote for his candidates at the next general election, and give him the large majority, independent of the Irish party which he claims to be necessary for any English Minister, before he can consider the Irish National question, that we should find ourselves in this position - we should present our claims for the consideration of Mr. Gladstone with his large majority. If Mr. Gladstone agreed to them he would probably bring in a bill to carry them into law, and that bill would, after passing the House of Commons, go up to the House of Lords; and the House of Lords would say to Mr. Gladstone, "Well, you never submitted the principles of this bill or the details of this bill to the judgment of the electorate at the general election, and we consider that it right, on a question of such gravity as is this question of the settlement of national relations between England and Ireland - we consider it right that the electorate of England and Scotland should have an opportunity of passing judgment upon the matter, and we will throw out this bill and compel you to dissolve Parliament." Now, that would be a very abortive result of this great general election, and the return of Mr. Gladstone to power at the head of a large Liberal majority, if in the event of his acceptance of our propositions when we have brought them forward in the new Parliament, and the passage of a bill based on them through the House of Commons, it were to be found that the whole thing was going to be knocked on the head by the House of Lords, and under these circumstances it appears to me that the House of Lords would be only carrying out their constitutional right by rejecting such a bill - a bill the details of which had not been before the country at the general election. Now, Mr. Gladstone could avoid all this risk and all this useless trouble by simply bending his great intellect to the task of framing a constitution for Ireland. There is no man better able to do it (hear, hear), no living man better able to do it, and I invite him with all seriousness to lay his views as to the largest amount of self-government, subject to the conditions and limitations he has provided, which he has stipulated for regarding the supremacy of the Crown and the maintenance of the union of the Empire. I would invite him to lay his ideas upon the question before the public in order that the public of the three kingdoms may have an opportunity of judging and of passing a decisive verdict at the general election which is approaching upon them (loud cheers).</p>
         <p>A LIE NAILED.</p>
         <p>Now, I wish to notice a very infamous falsehood - well, I don't exactly like to call it a falsehood, because I am not in a position to judge and I have not sufficient evidence before me to know whether it was a premeditated falsehood or not - but a very glaring misstatement which appeared in to-day's London Times (hisses). I should not have noticed the matter were it not that considerable injustice is inflicted by the statement in the shape of a letter from Mr. Saunderson, a North of Ireland Orangeman (groans), upon a gentleman whom I believe to be perfectly innocent of the offence for which he is now suffering penal servitude - I refer to Mr. Patrick Nally (applause). Some days ago at the Mayo Convention a considerable section of the Nationalists of the county Mayo brought forward Mr. Patrick Nally as a candidate for the Parliamentary representation of one of the divisions of Mayo, and in my position as chairman of the Convention and also leader of the movement (loud cheers) I was obliged to refuse Mr. Nally's candidature, which I did with very great regret, because, as I have already said, I believe him to be perfectly innocent of the offence for which he was convicted, and also because his friends had a very strong conviction that if he was returned for Mayo it might have a beneficial effect in obtaining his release. However, I was obliged to object to his candidature, and his friends, after a great deal of good-humoured discussion, withdrew his name, and in referring to this at the public meeting afterwards I took occasion to say what I thought of Mr. Nally, and of his conviction, and of his imprisonment, just as I have spoken to you to-night. Well, this letter of Mr. Saunderson which appeared this morning in the Times referred to my speech about Mr. Nally, and gave a quotation from a speech from another Nally, the celebrated, or rather notorious, "Scrab" (much laughter), quite a different character in every respect (hear, hear). Well you can see the abominable unfairness of writing to the Times and making a deliberate misstatement - I won't call it a falsehood, because I don't know whether this Mr. Saunderson really knew that he was telling a lie or not - of making a deliberate misstatement with regard to a prisoner whose release we are attempting to obtain (applause). Surely some caution might have been observed by the writer of the letter to ascertain whether Mr. Patrick Nally had ever made a speech anything like the one quoted. Now, I know that Mr. Patrick Nally never made anything by the most moderate speeches during the course of the Land League movement, and that no single passage of any of his speeches could be pointed out which could by any possibility be connected or twisted into any incitement to crime or violence of any kind whatever. The speech which was quoted in the Times this morning, and which was commented on on [sic] in the leader of the Times as an argument against the concession of the national rights of Ireland, was a speech which was made by another Nally altogether, and it just shows you some of the difficulties that we have to contend with. I do not know whether the Times knew that there was no foundation for this accusation against Mr. Nally. I do not know whether Mr. Saunderson knew, but surely where important issues not only regarding the fate of an individual, but the relations between two nations are at stake (applause), public journalists in the position of the Times should hesitate before they insert every lie as Gospel which is sent to them (loud cheers). At the commencement of my remarks I said that I believed we were near victory, I believe that we are near victory provided we can fulfil two conditions, and these two conditions are - firstly, that we can keep our people at home and abroad united and free from quarrels and dissensions amongst themselves (loud cheers); that this united people should be true to the great traditions which they have inherited, and as it rests in their power to strike to-day what we believe will be a successful and a last blow for Ireland (cheers), that they will not shrink from striking hard and striking home (renewed cheering). Secondly, we require that those who are entrusted to bear our flag in the Parliament of Westminster shall be men who shall sink all personal considerations, who shall maintain the same union in their ranks that we the Parliamentary Party of 1880-1885 have maintained during the last Parliament (hear, hear) - that they shall crush down with an iron hand all dissension in their midst (applause), and above all, that they shall believe in themselves and in the work that they have in hand (applause). And, gentlemen, if these two conditions are fulfilled - if we have a united people and a determined body of men believing in their work, showing by every act, by every thought, by every word, that they believe in the right of Ireland to obtain national self-government, then the day will not be very far off when you, living as you are in another country, will have the gratification of witnessing the assembly of an Irish Parliament on Irish soil (loud cheers), with full power to guide and watch over the destinies of our nation (continued cheering).</p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
