<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- put file title here e.g.  Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, The Times, Wednesday 23 February 1881-->
            <title>Imperial Parliament, The Government of Ireland, The Irish Times, Friday 9 April 1886</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>          
            <publisher>Parnell's Speeches</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>            
            <availability xml:id="metadataRights" status="restricted">
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This metadata is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International (CC BY-NC 4.0).</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <!--put source author name with VIAF ID if applicable e.g. <author key="98043225">Smith, John</author>-->
                  <author key=""></author>
                  <!--put exact source title here e.g. Mr Parnell's Speech at Clara, level as appropriate-->
                  <title level="a">Imperial Parliament, The Government of Ireland</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <!--put publication title here with VIAF ID and level <title key="184285835" level="j">The Times</title>-->
                  <title key="144709869" level="j">The Irish Times</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <!--put pagination here <biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>-->
                     <biblScope unit="page">6-7</biblScope>
                     <!--put source date here numeric and text <date when="1881-02-23">February 23, 1881</date>-->
                     <date when="1886-04-09">9 April 1886</date>
                     <!--put publication place of source with Getty Thesaurus ID e.g. <pubPlace key="7011781">London</pubPlace> -->                    
                     <pubPlace key="7001306">Dublin, Ireland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <classDecl>
           <taxonomy xml:id="VIAF">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="https://viaf.org/">Virtual International Authority File</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="TGN">
              <bibl>
                 <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/">Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names</ref>
              </bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="SPEECHES">
              <bibl>Register of Parnell's speeches</bibl>
           </taxonomy>
           <taxonomy xml:id="ARTICLE_TYPES">
              <bibl>Typology of articles</bibl>
           </taxonomy>          
        </classDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <textClass>
           <keywords scheme="#SPEECHES">
              <list>
                 <!--put speech ID(s) here e.g. <item><term key="speech_00001"/></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term key="speech_00052"/>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
           <keywords scheme="#SOURCE_TYPES">
              <list>
                 <!--put typology of article here e.g. <item><term>newspaper report</term></item>-->
                 <item>
                    <term>newspaper report</term>
                 </item>
              </list>
           </keywords>
        </textClass>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2020-11-04">     
           Record created by Hugh Hanley
        </change>        
     </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
     <!--<graphic url="image100.tif"></graphic>-->
     <graphic url="https://www-proquest-com.ucd.idm.oclc.org/hnpirishtimes/docview/514231354/pageviewPDF/58167642D7DA405FPQ/1?accountid=14507"></graphic>
  </facsimile> 
  <text>
      <body>
         <!--put exact source text here in new <p></p> tags for each paragraph e.g. <p>Mr Parnell addresed the crowd [etc]</p>-->
         <p>Mr Parnell, who was greeted with loud cheers from the Irish party on rising, said - I am glad to find that we have not been disappointed by the lobby rumours which had been circulated for some days past regarding the right hon. gentleman the Member for the Border Burghs, and that he has after all, like the celebrated but unsuccessful French general who defended Paris from the Germans, got his own plan - (a laugh) - and that he did not fail at the close of his interesting speech to give us the details of this important plan. But I noticed the somewhat discouraging fact that his own valuable encomiums of his plan elicited no enthusiasm of any kind from any section of the House. (Cheers and counter cheers.) I noticed that it was not until he had pointed and pleaded those gentlemen - the members of the Conservative party - that at last some small section of them gave him a cheer or two, and that he did succeed in getting some faint applause from a few gentlemen belonging to that party. (Irish cheers.) The Conservative party has always been most remarkable in its discipline. Being sometimes a small party, and very often in a minority it is bound to be remarkable. Undoubtedly in its treatment with respect to the plan of the right hon. gentleman the Member for Mid-Lothian it had in its mind the declaration of the noble lord the member for Paddington, when he announced in a speech some two or three years since that nothing more should be conceded to the Irish Nationalists, neither in the direction of local self-government, county boards, or anything else. Of course the rank and file of the Conservative party under these circumstances could not have ventured to applaud the right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs, and break away from their allegiance to the noble lord the member for Paddington (Lord R Churchill). Some say the noble lord has been flirting with Home Rule and a separate Irish Parliament, the apprehension of which has caused so much consternation in the mind of the member for the Border Burghs. I know nothing about those things - (a laugh) - and I shall not express any opinions upon it. (Hear, hear.) But I do think that the right hon. gentleman opposite in attempting the comparison which he appeared to draw between the action of Earl Spencer in remaining in the Cabinet and his own action in leaving it to Lord Spencer's disadvantage, scarcely stood on fair, firm, or satisfactory grounds. Englishmen love a man who fights his own corner to the end. Lord Spencer certainly fought his own corner. (Hear, hear.) He went over to Ireland to fight out a battle which was not his, and to fight the battle of the Irish landlords, and he stuck to his post. (Loud Irish cheers.) He faced every danger and every risk, both personal and otherwise. Why, the right hon. gentleman did something more like running away - (Irish cheers and laughter) - though the right hon gentleman endeavoured to explain to the House his reason for leaving the Cabinet. He did not try to explain why he left his position as Chief Secretary. (Oh, oh, and cheers.) If the right hon. gentleman was willing to assume that office in Ireland it was not a very chivalrous thing for him to take the attitude which to-night he says he took with regard to the people generally. (Hear.) The right hon. gentleman attempted to prove what terrible things should have been done in Ireland when he was Chief Secretary, but for his administration, by reading the terms of a motion which I brought forward in 1883. I do not desire to go back over old quarrels: it generally happens that those who have been defeated in old quarrels like to refer to them. (Irish cheers and laughter.) What I said then I say now - that then there had been the execution and imprisonment of innocent men. I believed it then, and I believe it now, that innocent men had been executed. I never accused the right hon. gentleman, or Lord Spencer, of having believed the same thing, knowing that the executed men were innocent: but I can scarcely think that the right hon. gentleman thinks so now. How about the case of Bryan Kilmartin, who was sentenced to 15 years' penal servitude? (An hon. member - For life.) I am told he was sentenced to penal servitude for life, and whose case when brought forward was supported by the noble lord (R. Churchill) and one or two Conservative members, including the hon. member for Blackburn - (hear, hear) - and that man was found innocent, and I believe that this was during the tenure of the office then held by the right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan). The right hon. gentleman taunts us with the language of the resolution we then brought forward, and with the language of the address to Irishmen prepared by the hon. member for Liverpool (Mr. T. P. O'Connor), but I consider that these statements were correct, and that we had a right to refer to them, and because they related to the reign of terror which had then prevailed, I do not see how I could have acted otherwise, not only to my constituents, but out of regard for my public duty as regards law and order, of which the right hon. gentleman to-night poses as champion. (Hear, hear, and laughter.) I should have neglected my duty if I had refrained from bringing these matters under the notice of this House, and if the occasion rose now I should act in the same way. (Hear, hear.) When the right hon. gentleman used the expressions he had used with regard to my hon. friend (Mr. T. P. O'Connor), he forgot that he was no less a person than the Attorney-General in the late Government, who us4ed these words in speaking in Ireland - "The right hon. gentleman the late Attorney-General asserted at a public meeting that the blood of Giffen was upon the lead of Lord Spencer." (Irish cheers.) The right hon. gentleman the member for the Border Burghs has not censure for that language. He does not pick out that language as an example of the great risk of introducing the care of the lives of the Irish people to the future Conservative administration under the plans he has formulated to-night. No, he passes that by, but certainly no language which was every used by my hon. friends ever exceeded in gravity the charge I have just put - (cheers) - which was [indecipherable] by the Attorney-General that the blood of Giffen was on the head of Lord Spencer. The language used in the resolution and in the manifesto of my right hon. friend was mildness itself in comparison. But I hope the question will not be discussed with the heat exhibited by the right hon. gentleman. I do not with to go into a justification of our action in the last Parliament, although I could do so if I chose. I could remind the House of the agents used by the right hon. gentleman in the upholding of law and order in Ireland. I could remind them of the result of the trial in French's case, a man whom the right hon. gentleman actually did not shrink from defending in this House. But I do not desire to go into these things, but will leave history to report that in every resolution we moved with reference to the administration of the right hon. gentleman during his term of office we were more than justified in what we did. He was right in saying this assassination literature is not American literature, but if he had really devoted exclusive study to it he would have found that neither is it Irish literature. If the right hon. gentleman were to study the literature of America at the moment he would find sympathy for a just settlement of the grievances of Ireland by the concession of a domestic Legislature is shown by all classes, whether Irish or native-born Americans - (hear, hear) - and more especially native born Americans are welcoming the efforts of the Prime Minister in the belief that they will bring peace between England and Ireland, and more especially between Irish-Americans and England. It is a remarkable fact that the great meetings now being held in favour of any Irish Legislature are called together an organised by native-born Americans, by editors and conductors of purely American newspapers. We regard the fact that during the last five or six months we have succeeded in entirely gaining the sympathy of the two great political parties in America - the Democrats and Republicans - as a good omen for the future. The right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan) spoke about the Land Purchase Bill, and he turned to the Radical members near him to catch a cheer in his denunciation of the proposal to give money to an Irish Government, but I don't propose to enter into that beyond saying upon this and other matters, that it is not out of the mouth of the right hon. gentleman that such words should proceed, for did not the late Government bring in a bill to buy out the Irish landlords - (hear, hear) - a bill which if he had succeeded in passing - but fortunately it was added to a long list of failures - but if he had succeeded in passing it, and if it had been successful a still more doubtful prospect would have necessitated the additional payment of a very large sum of money towards buying out Irish landlords, the very thing he denounces to-day with so much eloquence. Leaving the right honourable gentleman, I may say as regards his picture of the horrible consequences that may result to Ireland and England if any proposal such as that suggested in the bill under discussion were adopted, I believe that so far from anything of the kind happening it contains a peaceful solution of difficulties between the two countries. And why? For several reasons. Why are there such troubles in Ireland now? Why is there talk of separation? Why does not my hon friend, the member for Tyrone write what he considers violent passages in United Ireland? It is because the people are desperate - they have nothing to lose. (Hear, hear.) But give them a constitution, and they will be proportionately careful not to lose that. (Parnellite cheers.) Every violent speech, every criminal action, will be so many nails driven in the coffin of that constitution. You will have every guarantee you have now, and those cannot be weakened very much. You will have the forces of the Crown, which will act just as freely and effectively as they can now. No possible adjunct in aid of physical force can be gained by the Irish Separatists by the provisions of such a measure as that explained to us; even the control of the constabulary is to be withheld from us until their character has been changed, because they are an armed force. You have required 15,000 armed policemen to govern Ireland, but we are expected to govern it with none at all. Then, too, you will have those guarantees of peace and contentment which have always accompanied the concession of measures such as this to the colonies as the surest and best guarantees in addition to those you possess at present. (Hear, hear.) I will pass on to the consideration of the bill, my attention to which has been withdrawn by the speech of the right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan). It is difficult to express a definite or positive opinion with regard to the bill before it has been printed, and I should like to reserve a too positive expression of opinion until I have seen the measure which I suppose will be issued on Monday; but still I think it is right that I should say something about its merits as they have been explained to us by the right hon. gentleman the member for Mid-Lothian. Allow me to say sir, that I think it will prove to be a happy and fortunate thing both for Ireland and England that there was one man living, an English statesman with the great power and extraordinary ability of the right hon. gentleman, to lend his voice to poor helpless Ireland on this question. (Loud Irish cheers.) He has devoted his great mind, his extraordinary energy to the unravelling of this question. It seems to many people that the task may be too large, too terrible even for the right hon. gentleman. I believe it will not be so - (Home Rule cheers) - but whatever may be the fate of the measure I believe the cause of Ireland, of Irish autonomy, will gain enormously in a way it never could have otherwise gained by the genius of the right hon. gentleman. (Home Rule cheers.) He had drafted his bill and explained it in a speech, which from anyone else might have been called extraordinary. To none of the sons of Ireland at any time has ever been given the genius and talent of the right hon. gentleman. Certainly nothing approaching it in these days; and I thanked him, therefore, for the energy and the time he has devoted to this matter, and I believe sincerely in my heart that the result will be that the people of England will recognise as the result of what he has done that he has been to them no less than to the people of Ireland a national benefactor. (Cheers.) But there are, undoubtedly, great faults and blots in the measure. The right hon. gentleman has had to meet a very critical and extraordinary state of affairs. He has seen his officers leaving his side one by one, and drawing their swords on him, as the member for the Border Burghs has done to-night. He has had, I suppose, to shape his measure to meet the tremendous opposition worked against it. But there are several points which it will be our duty when the measure reaches its committee stage to oppose very strongly, and to press for serious modification and amendment. The question of the Customs has been touched on. In giving up the customs, that would practically mean giving up to you the control of six-eighths or three-fourths of the revenue of Ireland. It would be absolutely as much in your power as it is now, both in regard to the original assignment of the taxes and the receiving of the money. The right hon. gentleman has, indeed, explained that if we were to insist on separate customs, that England could deprive Ireland by collecting in Ireland the duties on whiskey and tobacco of £1,400,000 a year. This would be a serious matter, and it may be fairly balanced against the control of the Customs and the Excise. But if the Prime Minister is to claim credit for giving us £1,400,000 of the retention of customs within the Imperial authority, he cannot claim credit for it over again, and make us pay out of that £1,000,000 a year for the Irish Constabulary, over whom we are, to have no control whatever, at all events for the present. Then there is the question of contribution to the Imperial Exchequer. I cannot admit - and I say it with great deference - I cannot admit either the justice or the liberality of the standard of comparison the right hon. gentleman could have chosen. Of course he is anxious to make the best bargain he can for England and to secure as large a contribution for the Imperial Treasury as is possible, but he should remember that Ireland is a very poor country, and that will such a small balance as he shows of about £400,000 a year it will be absolutely impossible for Ireland to have any credit in the direction of floating loans. Now we are able to borrow from the Treasury large sums of money for various purposes in Ireland. Irish landlords, Irish tenants, local authorities can borrow money. All these are very important matters, but we shall have to surrender them under the scheme of the right hon. gentleman, and we shall be left with a budget which will exceed the annual balance by about £400,000 a year, and a Budget arrived at on an estimate which necessitates that the consumption of spirits, not only in Ireland, but also in England, should continue at its present rate and that the duty should be kept as now, as I suppose it will be. It is scarcely fair to press us too closely, or to insist upon too hard or too close a bargain in regard to this matter. Of course whatever the sum agreed upon is, we must pay it, and we will pay it. (Hear, hear.) But it would be most unfortunate if the result of such a standard of comparison as the right hon. gentleman has selected should be to impoverish the Irish Exchequer. In that case only would there be any possibility of the danger which the right hon. gentleman (Mr. Trevelyan) has augured up with regard to an attempted repudiation of the Imperial debt, an attempt which if made would be entirely unsuccessful, because you would have the collection of the excise absolutely in your own hands. When you are proposing a great settlement which admittedly can only succeed if it is cheerfully accepted by public opinion in Ireland, if all its important provisions are recognised as just and equitable, is it worth while on the part of a rich country like England to drive too hard a bargain? I am convinced that we have a much stronger case for the adoption of a standard of 	1-20th or 1-22nd as the relative wealth of the two countries than the right hon. gentleman has for adopting the very unfavourable standard of 1-15th. I have every confidence that when the time comes in committee, and when we put our case regarding this most important financial question, that the consciences not only of the House of Commons, but also of the right hon. gentleman the Prime Minister, will be touched in this matter, and that he will see that his zeal for making a good bargain for his own country in the question of Imperial contribution has led him into doing an unintentional injustice to Ireland. Then, again, I think that the question of the Royal Irish Constabulary has been left in a most unsatisfactory state. It is unfair to ask us to pay for a force or a large proportion of a force over which we shall have no control whatever. But some light might be thrown upon that by a perusal of the bill itself when issued and by proceedings in committee. (Hear, hear.) Then came the vote by orders. That had been explained by the right hon. gentleman to be that it gave the first order - the 28 peers - the right to hand up any bill for three years - three years or a dissolution whichever was the longer. This it would be absolutely within the power of the first order to hang up any measure it pleased and so bring the whole proceedings of the Legislature to a deadlock. This is a very important point, and I say that I have strongly insisted upon such a proposition proportional representation of the Protestant minority as would give them representation according to their numerical strength, and as far as the first order is concerned it might be very well with a view to preventing any rash, hasty, ill-considered legislation, and with that I cordially agree - (hear, hear) - but so far as it acts or could be made to act as an obstruction to legislation, or as a means of bringing about a political deadlock on the part of a body of members who could scarcely be said to be representative, I think it should be moderated so as to make that impossible. (Hear, hear.) As regards the measure itself, the Prime Minister has truly said that it ought not to proceed unless it is cheerfully welcomed, not only by the Irish members, but by the Irish people. I quite agree with that. I am convinced that if our views were fairly met in committee with regard to the defects to which I have alluded, the effects of its working will be to agreeably disappoint the right hon. member for the Border Burghs, and that this proposal will be cheerfully accepted by the Irish people, and by her representatives as a solution of the long-standing dispute between the two countries, and that it will be to the prosperity and peace of Ireland and to the satisfaction of England. (Cheers.)</p>
         <p></p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
